<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The continuation of the actions, passages, and occurrences, both politike and polemicall, in the upper Germanie Historically brought downe, from the period of the last relation, till Aprill. Together with a various and intermixed historie, of what hath been done in Turky, Italy, France, the Netherlands, and elsewhere. Faithfully collected out of good and creditable originals and digested methodically, by the times, places, and actions.</title>
            <title>Diatelesma. Part 2.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 228 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 58 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4293.2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107079</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842782</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842782</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7470</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17472)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7470)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1599:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The continuation of the actions, passages, and occurrences, both politike and polemicall, in the upper Germanie Historically brought downe, from the period of the last relation, till Aprill. Together with a various and intermixed historie, of what hath been done in Turky, Italy, France, the Netherlands, and elsewhere. Faithfully collected out of good and creditable originals and digested methodically, by the times, places, and actions.</title>
                  <title>Diatelesma. Part 2.</title>
                  <author>N. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 46, 49-108 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E[lizabeth] P[urslowe, J. Dawson, and others] for Nathanael Butter, and Nicholas Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At head of title: Num. 2.</note>
                  <note>Part 2 of five news tracts issued from 1636 to 1639, of which the last three are entitled "Diatelesma". "To the reader" of other parts signed: N.C.</note>
                  <note>"Purslowe pr[inted]. at least quires A-D; Dawson at least E-G"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Leaf G4 (p. 47-48) is cancelled; text is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Leaf A4r, line 17 ends "Title of." Variant: line ends "Historiæ".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1616-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7470:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7470:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CONTINVATION OF THE ACTIONS, Paſſages, and Occurrences, both Politike and Polemicall, in the upper GERMANIE.</p>
            <p>HISTORICALLY BROVGHT downe, from the Period of the laſt Relation, till Aprill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Together</hi> With a various and intermixed Hiſtorie, of what hath been done in <hi>Turky, Italy, France,</hi> the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and elſewhere.</p>
            <p>Faithfully collected out of good and creditable ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginals and digeſted Methodically, by the Times, Places, and Actions.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>E. P.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Butter,</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Bourne.</hi> 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:7470:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7470:2"/>
            <head>THE PRINCIPALL HEADS of the Things contained in this Hiſtorie.</head>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> THe States of <hi>Sweden</hi> reſolve to continue the Warre. <hi>p. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> The <hi>Saxons</hi> preparation for Warre with the <hi>Swedes. p. 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> The <hi>Swedes</hi> counſell for managing the Warre. <hi>p. 3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> The Fort of <hi>Mansfeld</hi> beſieged. <hi>p. 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5 Dehne</hi> ſent to relieve it. <hi>p. 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> Three hundred <hi>Saxons</hi> ſlaine, and taken priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. The Siege raiſed, and the Fort relieved. <hi>p. 5</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> Two Imperiall Regiments defeated and routed by <hi>Banniere</hi> at <hi>Helmſtat. p. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8 Banniere</hi> marcheth into <hi>Thuringen. p. 6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9 Banniere</hi> ſends to <hi>Ertford,</hi> for reliefe for his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. The Magiſtrates anſwer. <hi>p. 8</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> The <hi>Swediſh</hi> Armie removeth. <hi>p. 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> The Imperialiſts march towards <hi>Franconia. p. 10</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> Foure Imperiall Regiments defeated. <hi>Goetz</hi> his flight. <hi>Hatzfeldt</hi> plundereth the Countrey as he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. <hi>p. 11</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:7470:3"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>13 Mellerſtat</hi> and <hi>Newſtat,</hi> in <hi>Franconia,</hi> taken by <hi>Stathanſe. Paderborne</hi> and <hi>Wartzburg,</hi> in <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> taken. <hi>p. 12</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> The <hi>Landgrave</hi> of <hi>Darmſtat</hi> moleſted. <hi>p. 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15 Elfeld</hi> taken and the Suburbs burned. <hi>p. 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> A Regiment of <hi>Crabats</hi> ſurprized, neere <hi>Wormbs,</hi> and their Colonell taken priſoner by <hi>Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey. p. 14</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> A Convoy of fortie Tunnes of Wine taken by be <hi>Hanawers. p. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18</hi> A foure moneths Truce concluded betwixt <hi>Darmſtat</hi> and <hi>Ramſey. p. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19</hi> A new King of <hi>Romans</hi> elected. <hi>p. 16</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20</hi> The Elector of <hi>Tryers,</hi> and <hi>Land-grave</hi> of <hi>Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell</hi> diſavow the election. <hi>p. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21</hi> The manner and Ceremonies of the Election. <hi>p. 18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22</hi> The Syndick of <hi>Cologne</hi> murthered at <hi>Regen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpurgh. p. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>23</hi> The King of <hi>Romans</hi> Crowned. <hi>21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>24</hi> The Queenes Coronation. <hi>22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>25</hi> New Knights of the Empire made. <hi>23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>26</hi> Strange Prodigies. <hi>24</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>27</hi> The death of the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond. <hi>p. 25</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>28 Ertford</hi> ſummoned. <hi>p. 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>29</hi> Beſieged by the <hi>Swedes. p. 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>30</hi> Surrendred upon compoſition. <hi>p. 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>31</hi> The Articles. <hi>p. 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>32</hi> Foure Imperiall Regiments defeated by <hi>Stal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ans. p. 31</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:7470:3"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>33</hi> Seven hundred of them ſlaine, and two Colonels taken priſoners. <hi>p. 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>34 Leipſick</hi> ſummoned. <hi>p. 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>35</hi> The Governour reſolved to defend it. <hi>p. 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colonell <hi>Dehne</hi> routed. <hi>34</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>36 Torgaw</hi> taken by <hi>Banniere. p. 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>37</hi> The <hi>Saxon</hi> Garriſon taketh pay of the <hi>Swedes. p. 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>38</hi> The Colonell <hi>Dehne</hi> beheaded. <hi>p. 36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>39</hi> A Troope of <hi>Swediſh</hi> Horſe ſurpriſed. <hi>p. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>40 Leipſich</hi> victualled and fortified. <hi>p. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>41 Leipſich</hi> againe ſummoned. <hi>p. 38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>42</hi> Beſieged by the <hi>Swedes. p. 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>43</hi> Holdeth out for the Elector of <hi>Saxony. p. 40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>44</hi> The defence made by the Garriſon, and the offence done by the <hi>Swedes. p. 41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>45</hi> The ſiege raiſed. <hi>p. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>46</hi> Thanksgiving for the Cities deliverance. <hi>p. 44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>47</hi> The Imperiall Armie re-united and re-inforced, marcheth towards <hi>Miſnia. p. 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>48</hi> A Conflict betwixt <hi>Stalhanſe,</hi> and the Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts at <hi>Sala,</hi> wherein foure Imperiall Regiments were ruinated. <hi>p. 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>49</hi> The <hi>Crabats</hi> under <hi>Iſolani</hi> oppreſſe the <hi>Haſſians. p. 46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>50 Budiani</hi> raiſed, and his Regiment routed by the <hi>Land-grave William. p. 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>51</hi> Eleven hundred <hi>Pollacks</hi> mutinying for pay, take ſervice under <hi>Wrangle. p. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>52 Truchſes</hi> arreſted, and ſent to <hi>Vienna, p. 50</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:7470:4"/>
            <list>
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>53</hi> The death of <hi>Bodiſlaus</hi> Duke of <hi>Pomerania. p. 51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>54</hi> The <hi>Swediſh</hi> Regiment under Colonell <hi>Poye</hi> rou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>p. 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>55</hi> The Vauntguard of ſome Imperiall Troopes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated upon the <hi>Mulda. p. 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>56</hi> Two <hi>Caeſarian</hi> Regiments ſurpriſed neere great <hi>Hahn. p. 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>57</hi> The Fort of <hi>Hermeſtein</hi> neceſſitated. <hi>p. 54</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>58</hi> The <hi>Landgrave</hi> attempteth to relieve it. <hi>p. 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>59 Ramſey</hi> relieveth it by a Stratageme. <hi>p. 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>60 Lemford</hi> taken by the Imperialiſts. <hi>p. 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>61</hi> The Preſidiaries of <hi>Minden</hi> and <hi>Oſnabrugge</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated at <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>epshold. p. 58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>62</hi> Surpriſe <hi>Hagell,</hi> and put foure Companies of <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſareans</hi> to the ſword. <hi>p. 58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>63</hi> The miſerable condition of the Dukedome of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xony. p. 58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>64 Kuſtrin</hi> beleaguered by the <hi>Swedes. p. 59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>65</hi> The ſiege intermitted. <hi>p. 61</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>66 Berlin</hi> regained by the Marqueſſe Elector. <hi>p. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>67 Brandenburg</hi> taken from the <hi>Swedes. p. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>68 Druſſen</hi> blocked up by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> and the ſiege relinquiſhed. <hi>p. 62</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>69 Lantzberg</hi> ſurrendred to <hi>Wrangell. p. 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>70</hi> Colonell <hi>Arnheim</hi> ſurpriſed by the <hi>Swedes</hi> and priſoner to <hi>Stetin. p. 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>71 Wrangell</hi> marcheth into <hi>Sileſia. p. 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>72</hi> A ſtrange prodigie at <hi>Iſenach. p. 64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>73 Stralen</hi> burnt by the <hi>Swedes. p. 64</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>74</hi> Two Imperiall Regiments defeated at <hi>Weurtzen</hi> by Colonell <hi>Slangh. p. 65</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:7470:4"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>75</hi> Two hundred Imperiall Horſe defeated by <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niere</hi> at <hi>Pegaw. p. 65</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>76</hi> Three Regiments of Imperiall Horſe routed by the <hi>Swede. p. 66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>77</hi> The head Watch of the Imperiall Armie forced to a confuſed flight. <hi>p. 66</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>78</hi> The Emperours Funerall. <hi>p. 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>79</hi> The Citizens of <hi>Liege</hi> complaine to the Pope againſt their Biſhops. <hi>p. 68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>80</hi> The Count of <hi>Warfuſee</hi> his treaſon at <hi>Leige. p. 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>81 Ruelle</hi> the Burger-maſter murthered. <hi>p. 71</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>82</hi> The Abbot of <hi>Mouſſon</hi> and others ſtrangely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered. <hi>p. 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>83</hi> The rage of the Cittizens, and the end of the Aſſaſſinates. <hi>p. 73</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>84 Warfuſee</hi> his counterfeited Letters. <hi>p. 75</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <head>The Table of the Title of <hi>Hiſtoria <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aria.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1</hi> The cauſe of the <hi>Turkes</hi> invading <hi>Tranſylva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia. p. 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2</hi> The King of <hi>France</hi> his order for proviſion for his Souldiers, and eaſe of his ſubjects. <hi>p. 80</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3 John de Werths</hi> flight. <hi>p. 81</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> Three hundred <hi>Wallon</hi> Horſe defeated, and ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed by <hi>Gaſſion,</hi> neere <hi>Neuf-maiſon. p. 82</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> preparations for war. <hi>p. 101</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6 Crequy</hi> ſent to the King of <hi>France,</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Savoye. p. 101</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:7470:5"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> The <hi>French</hi> project diſcovered at <hi>Diettenhofen,</hi> and their Forces defeated. <hi>p. 102</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> The Duke of <hi>Rohan</hi> his goods arreſted by the <hi>Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. p. 103</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> Commeth to Capitulation. <hi>p. 103</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> The conditions agreed upon betwixt the <hi>Griſons</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Rohan. p. 104</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11 Switz</hi> beſieged and taken by the <hi>French. p. 104</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12 Honorata</hi> recovered by the <hi>French<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> p. 105</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13</hi> Preparations for Warre by the Cardinall Infant, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited States. <hi>p. 105</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> A bloody fight betwixt a Partie of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and another of the States Souldiers. <hi>p. 106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> The Statiſts get the victory. <hi>p. 106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> The Prince of <hi>Orance</hi> his deſigne againſt <hi>Hulſt</hi> prevented. <hi>p. 107</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> The Baſſa in <hi>Morea</hi> rebelleth againſt the <hi>Turke. p. 107</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18</hi> The Vezier Baſſa imployed lately againſt the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian,</hi> fleeth to the <hi>Sophie. p. 107</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:7470:5"/>
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Hiſtorie of the Actions and Paſſages in the upper <hi>Germanie,</hi> ſince <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1636. <hi>Continued and brought downe to this preſent.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Parliamentarie Councell of the <hi>Swediſh</hi> States at <hi>Stockhohne,</hi> was not then diſſolved, when the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of their victorie at <hi>Witstock,</hi> were confirmed by two expreſſes, ſent from the Generall <hi>Banniere</hi> to the Queene and Diet there aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled. His Letters gave ſuch life to their counſels, that they which formerly tottered in their opinions (feare of the Emperours and the united Princes Forces, and ſuſpition of their owne weakneſſe projecting many doubts of ill ſucceſſe) tooke heart againe, and reſolved to have the Warre continued in the Empire, but eſpecially againſt the Houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria.</hi> The ſtate of the <hi>German</hi> Proteſtant Princes,<note place="margin">The States of <hi>Sweden</hi> reſolve to continue the Warre.</note> which had forſaken the Crowne of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and adhered to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> rather moved pitie then anger; and the Rix-Chancellor, by the advice of the whole Senate, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it fitter, to treat with them firſt as friends, then to fight againſt them as enemies; hoping by arguments,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:7470:6"/>to perſwade them to breake off their late alliance with <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and renew the offenſive and defenſive League, which they had formerly made with the Crowne of <hi>Sweden.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Mecklenburg</hi> (who ſince the Treatie of <hi>Prague</hi> had laboured, though vainely, with the <hi>Lunenburger,</hi> to diſclaime the Articles of <hi>Prague</hi>) was againe deſired to treat with the Elector of <hi>Saxonie</hi> to the ſame effect; and he, according to his inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, firſt putting the Elector in remembrance of the benefits he had received by the late King, of his ſlight forſaking the Confederacie, which he made to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Majeſtie; of the happie ſucceſſe of the Crowne of <hi>Sweden,</hi> in the late battaile againſt him; and the danger he expoſed himſelfe and his ſubjects unto, by provoking his faithfull friends to enmitie; adviſed him to renew his alliance with the <hi>Swedes,</hi> promiſing on their parts, an <hi>Amnestie</hi> of what was paſt, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe to complie with him in all mutuall offices of love. The Meſſage was delivered bluntly, without much Courtſhip, and anſwered in the ſame accent; neither did the Duke expect a pleaſing anſwer, neither could the <hi>Saxon</hi> (without ſhame, and note of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancie) fall off from <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and give one: as hee found it, ſo hee returned it to the Generall <hi>Banniere,</hi> whoſe Commiſſion was, to proceede with the Elector accordingly.</p>
               <p>Each unkinde office done by a friend, wounds true affection; but the iterating and reiterating of injuries, murthereth that amitie, which had its life from hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane politie; and it is more eaſie to ſtop the ſtreame of a quicke Current, then to reſtraine the iraſcible ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite, if it be thus provoked to wrath, and armed (though but in opinion) with power to execute re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. The Elector, who till hee had made his peace with his Imperiall Majeſtie, had made good uſe of the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:7470:6"/>
                  <hi>Swedes,</hi> for protecting of his Countrey; having now attained his owne ends,<note place="margin">The <hi>Saxons</hi> preparation for Warre with the <hi>Swedes.</hi>
                  </note> would faine be rid of them: and though his loſſe at <hi>Witstock</hi> had much weakened his power, yet himſelfe rayſed ſome freſh forces; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed all the Smiths and Carpenters in his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to prepare a new Artillerie, and their Carriages; commanded his ſubjects to fortifie his Townes, againſt invaſion by the <hi>Swedes;</hi> whileſt the Imperiall ſuccours (rallyed by <hi>Hatzfield,</hi> and ſupplyed with the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, under the command of the Field-Marſhall <hi>Goetz</hi>) might come in, to their reliefe; either by ſtopping the <hi>Swedes,</hi> in their victorious March; or, if haply it might be, by an happie Victorie to drive them quite out of <hi>Germanie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Swedes</hi> againe were become formidable to the Empire; and the feare of thoſe ſtrangers, ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the new band of alliance betwixt <hi>Caeſar</hi> and the native Princes of that Territorie. The Imperiall Bands ſent to the <hi>Saxon;</hi> under <hi>Marazim</hi> and <hi>Hatzfield,</hi> before the late Victorie, were but ſmall, to what was now intended for them. The Colonels, <hi>Wartenburg-Wahil,</hi> and <hi>Flanz,</hi> were deſigned to continue the Warre in <hi>Heſſen,</hi> whileſt <hi>Goetz</hi> with the maine Body of the Army, was deputed to joyne with <hi>Hatzfield;</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Dona,</hi> Generall Major for the Elector of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> to make head againſt <hi>Banniere</hi> and <hi>Leſle;</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Lignitz,</hi> the Colonels, <hi>Truchſes,</hi> and <hi>Knowbeldorfe,</hi> were appointed to raiſe forces in <hi>Sileſia,</hi> and conſigne them over to the Generalate of Count <hi>Mansfeld,</hi> to withſtand <hi>Wrangell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Swedes</hi> counſell for managing the Warre.</note> who threatned to Winter in <hi>Sileſia.</hi> The <hi>Swediſh</hi> Generals not ignorant of theſe preparations, endeavoured firſt, with ſome part of their forces, to hinder theſe forces from mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; <hi>Leſle</hi> undertaking <hi>Goetz,</hi> in <hi>Westphalià; Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niere, Hatzfield,</hi> about <hi>Fulda; Wrangell,</hi> the Imperia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:7470:7"/>about the <hi>Oder;</hi> and then, with the other part, under the command of <hi>Stalhanſe,</hi> to invade <hi>Miſnia,</hi> the upper <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and the other Territories, which either then actually did, or might afterwards, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently accommodate or appertaine to the Elector of <hi>Saxonie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The meeting of the two Imperiall Generals, was of as much difficultie as conſequence; neither of them, ſingle, was able to ſtand before the <hi>Swedes;</hi> which fleſhed with their late Conqueſt, carryed all before them; nor could they come together, without danger; the one being to make his way with the Sword to the other, through the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Armies, and their forces yet every way inferiour to their adverſaries. <hi>Hatz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> which by flight from <hi>Pomerland</hi> ſaved himſelfe in <hi>Miſnia,</hi> being purſued by <hi>Banniere,</hi> was conſtrained more Southward ſtill; and had not (in probabilitie) beene able to have re-enforced his Armie at all, had not the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Generall ſtayed a while by the way, in the Countie of <hi>Mansfeld,</hi> to ſubject it to the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of his Armie, either by a willing ſubmiſſion, or neceſſitie. And yet, his ſtay there was not long; the timerous people being readie to ſubmit, and the Townes generally comming in, ſave onely the ſtrong Fort of <hi>Mansfeld:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Fort of <hi>Mansfeld</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged.</note> which (not yeelding to his firſt ſummons) the Garriſon being confident, that their owne, and the Caſtles ſtrength, was able to hold out, till they might haply be relieved; hee firſt block'd up, and then began to batter, though vainely; his deſire to reach <hi>Hatzfield</hi> (as ſoone as might be) prompting him on, to depart thence with his maine Body, and to leave foure Regiments onely, before the Fort: which, though they performed as much as ſo ſmall a number could, were forced to riſe within few dayes, by <hi>Adolphus Dehne,</hi> the <hi>Saxon</hi> Colonell;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:7470:7"/>who knowing the weakeneſſe of the Campe, by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the Elector, marched thither-ward <hi>Novemb.</hi> 4.14. with ſeven Regiments of Horſe and Foot,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dehne</hi> ſent to relieve it.</note> to relieve the neceſſitated Garriſon. The <hi>Saxons</hi> march was diſcovered to the Campe the next day following; and the Armie (not yet intrenched) to avoid the danger of being compaſſed in, reſolved to meet the <hi>Saxon</hi> upon the way, and to give him battell betwixt <hi>Cracow</hi> and <hi>Seburg,</hi> about twentie <hi>Engliſh</hi> miles from the Fort:<note place="margin">Three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Saxons</hi> ſlaine, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken priſoners.</note> The <hi>Swediſh</hi> Armie fell upon the <hi>Saxons</hi> avantguard, conſiſting of three hundred Horſe, envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roned them round about, put the greater part to the ſword, and tooke the reſt, both officers and common ſouldiers, priſoners.</p>
               <p>This beginning was of a faire aſpect, and promiſed a better iſſue, then attended it: the undanted <hi>Saxon</hi> Commander (for this ſmall defeat not dejecting his courage, but raiſing it to a higher pitch,) went on with his Battalia, and in a well ordered fight,<note place="margin">The ſiege rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and the Fort relieved.</note> charged upon the Swediſh Armie, which conſiſting meerely of Horſe, without any Infanterie, being galled with the Muske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers, was compelled to retire to <hi>Aſcherleben,</hi> in the Biſhopricke of <hi>Halberstat,</hi> where <hi>Bannieres</hi> Forces were lately inquartered for ſafety, leaving the Fort to be releeved by the <hi>Saxon</hi> Commander; and hee <hi>Novemb.</hi> 11.21. furniſhed it with freſh Men. Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, and Ammunition, according to the Electors di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
               <p>Thoſe accidents, which to the eye of reaſon, ſeeme fortunate; doe ſometimes prove unhappy beyond ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation: The departure of the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Generall from <hi>Mansfeld,</hi> gave liberty to the place, and plained the way for the Colonels preſent honour, yet the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in fine, was pernicious to the <hi>Saxons,</hi> being fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall to the Commanders perſon, and of dangerous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:7470:8"/>to the Electors Territories. The Generall <hi>Banniere,</hi> muſtering his Forces at <hi>Aſchlerben</hi> and <hi>Eglen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Two Imperiall Regiments de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated and routed by <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niere,</hi> at <hi>Helm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat.</hi>
                  </note> received aviſoes of two Imperiall Regiments inquartered at <hi>Helmſtat,</hi> not farre from thence, made up to them, defeated and routed them totally, and purſuing his conqueſt, marched with all ſpeede into <hi>Thuringen,</hi> (where <hi>Hatzfield</hi> and the Saxon Armie appointed to meete,) to prevent their forming of a Reall Armie, which being conjoyned, might have ſome power to make head againſt him, and his ſpeedy removall, made thoſe Saxon Troupes, which the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor had raiſed for the ſafeguard of his Countrie, to leave the <hi>Elve,</hi> and repaire towards <hi>Sala,</hi> to the great affrightment of the Miſnians, that Territorie, being by this meanes, deſtitute of defence, and open to the Swediſh invading Armies.</p>
               <p>But the ſtorme which threatned <hi>Miſnia,</hi> was for a time turned to <hi>Thuringen.</hi> The Swede held it fitter as yet, to chaſe the Imperiall Armie under <hi>Hatzfield</hi> in open field, which muſt either flie before him, or fight deſperatly, and upon diſadvantage; then to ſit downe before any fortified Townes; where a Winters Siedge might conſume him, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance there, give the <hi>Caeſareans</hi> opportunity to re-en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force their weake Armie. Notice was given him, that the Generall <hi>Gleene,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Banniere</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth into <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringen.</hi>
                  </note> had received commandment from <hi>Caeſar</hi> (then at <hi>Regenspurgh</hi>) to muſter up the Imperiall Troopes, which then lay in the Dukedome of <hi>Wertemberg,</hi> and to carry them through <hi>Franconia,</hi> to the generall Rendezvous at <hi>North-auſen;</hi> that <hi>Goetz</hi> had made his way as farre as <hi>Oſterode,</hi> in the Territory of <hi>Grubenhagen</hi> in <hi>Brunſwick-land,</hi> to the ſame intent, though hee ſuffered much by <hi>Leſle,</hi> who ſtopped his journey, and ſlew ſome of his men in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall skirmiſhes; that the Lantgraviate of <hi>Thuringen,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:7470:8"/>upon which (in regard of the late alliance, betwixt it and the Crowne of <hi>Sweden</hi>) hee tooke much compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, indured much violence, by reaſon of the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Army, which firſt exacted great contributions of the Imperiall Cities, <hi>North-auſen,</hi> and <hi>Mulhanſen,</hi> and afterward pillaged them, though yet they were of the ſame party, and burned the villages as farre as to <hi>Ertford,</hi> and as well to preſerve the Country from further ſpoile, as to prevent the <hi>Caeſarians</hi> in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of meeting, hee removed his Campe out of the Biſhopricke of <hi>Halberſtat,</hi> ſending before him the Generall Major <hi>Stalhanſe,</hi> with ten Regiments, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing himſelfe with the groſſe body of the Army. The preſence of the Swediſh Forces removed the Imperiall Generall from his quarter, but not out of that Country, his intention was, to abide about the River of <hi>Werra,</hi> where the Field-Marſhall <hi>Goetz</hi> had order to meete him, and though purſued by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> flitted onely from place to place, fled not, being aſſured that <hi>Goetz,</hi> though danger threatned him in the proſecution of his deſigne, would leave no ſtone unmoved, that might hinder his journey towards him. His firſt ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was at <hi>Crewtzberg,</hi> a Towne appertaining to the Duke of <hi>Eiſenack,</hi> where being reinforced, by ſome <hi>Saxon</hi> Regiments, hee fortified the paſſage, by which the <hi>Swedes</hi> muſt paſſe, if they marched after him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving not to ſtirre from thence, till his partner was arrived with his Forces to aſſiſt him. And now began the time of action, <hi>Leſle</hi> having much waſted <hi>Goetz</hi> his Army by ſundry Skirmiſhes, ſtill wayted upon him, expecting more opportunity to fight, the Imperiall Commander ſtill marching warily, and not expoſing his Army to any diſadvantage; and now, like two pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallell lines, which alwayes obſerving an equall diſtance, though neere each other, never meete, both made
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:7470:9"/>their way towards <hi>Thuringen,</hi> to joyne with their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall confederates.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Swediſh</hi> Army in all, thirty thouſand ſtrong, Horſe and Foot, joyned together <hi>Novemb.</hi> 5.15. in the <hi>Bayliwick</hi> of <hi>Ringleben,</hi> and the Towne of <hi>Gebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen. Banniere</hi> having his head Quarter at <hi>Werninhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen</hi> three Engliſh miles from <hi>Gebezen,</hi> and ſixe from <hi>Ertford,</hi> and the Imperiall Army the ninth of the ſame month at <hi>Trefort,</hi> nothing having paſſed betwixt them memorable, ſave onely the defeature of ſome Imperiall Companies at <hi>Sommerda,</hi> a paſſage betwixt <hi>Gebezen,</hi> and <hi>Werninghauſen,</hi> ſince the firſt day of the <hi>Swedes</hi> arrivall thither, and a little ſcuffling betwixt ſome parties of both the Armies, which met together in the Territorie of <hi>Eiſchfeld, Novemb.</hi> 8.18. being ſent abroad by their Commanders for Forrage, and other Proviſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Banniere</hi> ſends to <hi>Ertford,</hi> for reliefe for his Army.</note>
                  <hi>Banniere,</hi> in this time of his reſt, ſent a Trumpet to the Citty of <hi>Ertford,</hi> (which hitherto ſtood as a neutrall, and had flatly denyed the entertainement of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Garriſon, though the Elector had few dayes before ſent thither an agent to that purpoſe,) deſiring food for his Army, and their beſt aſſiſtance for his expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to the Capitulation of the deceaſed King his Maſter, and the Magiſtrate of that Citty in the yeere 1631. The Magiſtrate deſirous to continue the neutrality,<note place="margin">The Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrats anſwer.</note> and unwilling to provoke the <hi>Swede</hi> to doe the Citty any act of hoſtility, denyed neither, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed himſelfe for not complying to his deſire in both requeſts, the laſt being expreſſely againſt the Treaty of <hi>Prague,</hi> which he ſaid, was not accepted by the Citty, without conſent of the Rix-Chancellour, who drew out the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Garriſon, which they had formerly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained, and the firſt ſuch as might provoke the <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſareans,</hi> with whom they had yet good termes and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:7470:9"/>correſpondence, to be their profeſſed enemies. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe, that the Generall might know, that their former alliance could not be forgotten, hee would give free ingreſſe and egreſſe for the Officers of his Armie into the Citie, for their refreſhing: but againſt the common ſouldiers, whoſe rudeneſſe and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude might oppreſſe him, hee would keepe the Gates ſhut; not for any ill affection towards them, but the preſervation of the eſtates of the Citizens. The Officers, for the preſent, were not diſpleaſed with his anſwer, but uſed the libertie granted them: but the enraged common ſouldiers, without the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals knowledge, pillaged the bordering Villages; till complaint being made by the Peaſants to the Generall, he made a ſearch, to finde out the Ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders in thoſe diſorders; and by a publike Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation through the Armie, commanded his ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to doe no more detriment to the Territorie of <hi>Ertford:</hi> of which, he profeſſed that he was as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, as of the Duchie of <hi>Weymar,</hi> into which he had layd ſafe guards, for D. <hi>Bernhards</hi> ſake; whoſe former ſervice, and preſent faithfulneſſe to the Crowne of <hi>Sweden,</hi> had deſerved that and many farre greater favours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Novemb.</hi> 11.21. the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Armie was ordered by the Generall, to meete at their common <hi>Rande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous,</hi> in the Bayliwike of <hi>Ringleben:</hi> the ſafe guards, which had beene layd abroad the Countrey,<note place="margin">The <hi>Swediſh</hi> Armie remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth.</note> being ſummoned the day before to returne to the groſſe Body of the Armie at <hi>Henſleben,</hi> a Citie upon the River of <hi>Vnſtrut,</hi> about ſeven <hi>Engliſh</hi> miles Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from <hi>Gebezen:</hi> from whence, the Armie that day marched forward, toward the Imperiall Campel the Cavallarie, by the way of <hi>Langen-ſalſa;</hi> and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:7470:10"/>the Foot, by <hi>Tonna,</hi> towards <hi>Creutzburg,</hi> upon the River of <hi>Werra:</hi> The deſigne of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, being firſt to aſſault the then joyned Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts, before any new accreut could be brought unto them; and afterward, to invade the Electors Territories.</p>
               <p>His directions were obeyed punctually; and what hee had adviſed diſcreetly, was put in execution as ſpeedily; and his fortune ſtill attending him, the counſell and action were ſeconded with a proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous iſſue. <hi>Guntrad,</hi> Field-Marſhall to the <hi>Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> of <hi>Caſſell,</hi> had much impeached <hi>Goetz</hi> in his march, before hee came to <hi>Trefurt,</hi> as well as <hi>Leſle,</hi> and for his part, ſlaine and taken priſoners eight hundred of his men: and now the Generals as well wanting men, as foode for thoſe they had, knowing themſelves unable to encounter the <hi>Swedes</hi> Brigades, being advertiſed by their Spyes of <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nieres</hi> deſigne; marched ſpeedily by the Abbyes of <hi>Fulda</hi> and <hi>Hirzfield,</hi> towards the Biſhopricke of <hi>Wirtzburg,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſt, march towards <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conia.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Franconia,</hi> to joyne with <hi>Gleene,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they would adventure to put their fortunes to the hazard of a Battell; being ſtill followed by <hi>Banniere,</hi> who haſted to overtake them. It might have ſtaggered the <hi>Swedes</hi> deſigne, could they have reached thither; but there fell out a Rub by the way: The Count of <hi>Eberstein,</hi> Lieutenant Generall to the <hi>Lantgrave William,</hi> lay then in <hi>Caſſell:</hi> and hee hearing of the Imperials march, and the <hi>Swedes</hi> purſuit after them, ſeconded by the Governour in the Fort of <hi>Zigenheim;</hi> made all the haſte hee could, to ſtop their journey; but the Vant-guard, under <hi>Hatzfeld,</hi> was paſſed, before hee could reach them: Onely the Rere-guard, commanded by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:7470:10"/>
                  <hi>Goetz,</hi> was ſtayed by the <hi>Heſſian</hi> Forces, neere <hi>Rotemburg,</hi> upon the River of <hi>Fulda:</hi> where,<note place="margin">Foure Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Regiments defeated.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compaſſed in behinde and before, by the <hi>Swedes</hi> and <hi>Haſſians,</hi> foure of his Regiments were utterly defeated; three Peeces of Canon, thirteene En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, three hundred Horſe, and two hundred Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, being taken by the <hi>Swedes</hi> and <hi>Haſſians:</hi> all which were ſent immediately to <hi>Caſſell</hi> himſelfe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Goetz</hi> his flight.</note> and the other part of his Armie hardly eſcaping by flight, through the Countie of <hi>Waldeck,</hi> into <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Earle of <hi>Hatzfeldt</hi> having eſcaped this Bruſh, ſtill made on towards <hi>Wirtzburg,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hatzfeldt</hi> plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth the Countrey, as he goeth.</note> but not without plundering the Countrey-Villages of the <hi>Lantgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> as hee went, (<hi>Bannieres</hi> ſtay, to take order with his Armie, giving him opportututie to doe violence to the unarmed Peaſants) though not without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangering the lives of many his friends, Priſoners at <hi>Zigenhaim,</hi> whom the enraged Governour once reſolved, (and was hardly diſſwaded from that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution) to deliver up into the hands of the <hi>Boores,</hi> that by the loſſe of their lives, by thoſe (then fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly mad, and mercileſſe men) they might give them ſome ſatisfaction for their goods, and houſes, which the Imperiall Generals ſo hoſtilely had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed.</p>
               <p>The ſeparation of the Imperiall Armies, cauſed the <hi>Swedes</hi> alſo to divide theirs: and <hi>Stalhanſe</hi> was ordered, with ſix thouſand Horſe, and ſome Regiments of Foot, to purſue <hi>Hatzfeldt</hi> into <hi>Franconia; Leſle,</hi> with foure thouſand foot, and twelve hundred <hi>Haſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi> Horſe, to follow <hi>Goetz: Banniere</hi> reſerving the reſt of his Armie, to proſecute his deſignes againſt the Electorate.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:7470:11"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stalhanſe</hi> ſtrucke the <hi>Franconians</hi> into ſuch a ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, that like diſtracted men, diſtruſtfull of preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their lives, and livelyhoods otherwiſe, they conveyed their goods into <hi>Wirtzburg,</hi> and ſome other fortified Townes, and retyred themſelves into the Woods, leaving the Territorie to the mercie of the Invaders:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mellerflat</hi> and <hi>Newflat</hi> in <hi>Franconia</hi> taken by <hi>Stalhanſe.</hi>
                  </note> who tooke and plundeted <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerſtat,</hi> and <hi>Newſtat;</hi> and had done more there, had they not beene reſtrained, by order from the Generall, from engaging himſelfe too farre; and had not the care of the Biſhop of <hi>Wirtzburg,</hi> arming ſome thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of men ſpeedily, with the Garriſons of <hi>Swine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furd,</hi> conſiſting of eight hundred, and that of <hi>Kizin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guen,</hi> of five hundred men, made ſome head againſt them, <hi>Leſle,</hi> aſſiſted with his <hi>Haſſian</hi> Forces, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing able to reach <hi>Goetz,</hi> who ſhifted from place to place, declining any encounter with his Enemie, in reſpect of his much weakened Armie; that he might not returne to the Generall, without ſome tokens of his actions,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Paderborne</hi> and <hi>Wartzburg</hi> in <hi>Westphalia</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</note> firſt aſſaulted <hi>Paderborne,</hi> and tooke it by Onſlat: then ſummoned <hi>Wartzburg</hi> (a Towne of note ſtill in <hi>Westphalia,</hi> though ſomething eclipſed of her firſt ſplendour, as having beene the head of a Countie, ſtiled by that name, and now a <hi>Minor</hi> Citie, in the Dioceſſe of <hi>Paderborne,</hi> ſituate upon the Northerne Banke of <hi>Dimula</hi>) and tooke it in by compoſition; the Citizens prefering the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of their perſons, and families, before a little Money; and ſo purchaſing their quiet, rather then hazarding all to the fortune of Warre. And now both theſe Commanders, being ruled by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, returned to the groſſe of the Armie, in <hi>Thuringen;</hi> giving leave to the Imperiall Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals to meete againe in <hi>Westphalia,</hi> and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enforce
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:7470:11"/>their Armies, with the Troupes belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Marqueſſe of <hi>Darmstat,</hi> the Generall <hi>Wahle,</hi> the <hi>Major Fehle,</hi> and the Count of <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temburg:</hi> All which, wee muſt leave a little time in the Biſhopricke of <hi>Cologne,</hi> and about <hi>Dortmund:</hi> doing more dammage to their friends, by lying ſtill, and conſuming the Victuals of the Countrey, then to their Enemies, by any Hoſtile action.</p>
               <p>The beginning of <hi>December</hi> was the time when the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Commanders were repairing backe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and then began that horrid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, which hapned upon the Elector and his Allyes, in his owne and Confederates adjacent Territories. The <hi>Lant-gravate</hi> belonging to <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Darmſtat,</hi> was not onely threatned with a ſtorme, as bad as a Weſt-Indian <hi>Hericano,</hi> but a skirt of the cloud fell upon it; <hi>Gieſen,</hi> where the <hi>Lantgrave</hi> himſelfe was in perſon,<note place="margin">The <hi>Lant-gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate</hi> of <hi>Darm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat</hi> moleſted.</note> for his better ſecurity having ſent his wife and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren into <hi>Eaſt-Frizeland</hi> was menaced. The In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of <hi>Marpurg</hi> (the Metropolis of <hi>Haſſia,</hi> and an Univerſity famouſed by <hi>Hyperius</hi> the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, <hi>Eohanus Heſſus</hi> the Poet, and <hi>Johannes Oldendorpius</hi> the Civilian) both Students and, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidans, betooke themſelves to flight; <hi>Smalkalden</hi> ſurprized and pillaged, the Cittie of <hi>Elfeld</hi> was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by aſſault, and the Suburbs burnt downe to the ground,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Elfeld</hi> taken and the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs burned.</note> and this diſtreſſe cauſed the <hi>Lant-grave</hi> to write a dolefull Letter to the Elector of <hi>Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> his father-in-law, deſiring him to take com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration of his Subjects, who was able to pitie him onely, but not for the preſent to releeve him.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:7470:12"/>
               <p>But the mayne tempeſt fell not in that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, it ſteered more North-eaſterly, into <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> and <hi>Thuringen,</hi> where what ſpoyle it made, ſhall be related afterwards. The <hi>Lant-grave-George</hi> thus diſtreſſed by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> of the one ſide, and receiving divers by-blowes by the Garriſon of <hi>Hanaw,</hi> at the ſame time haſted to treat with them of a Truce, and ceſſation of Armes for a time to be preſcribed and agreed upon, fearing that if the <hi>Swedes</hi> ſhould thrive, and come neerer the <hi>Wete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raw,</hi> there would neither be time, nor place for any Compromitters to mediate betwixt him, and our Noble Countrie-man, (as wiſe in his dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, as nimble and valiant in the executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,) <hi>Ramſey</hi> Governour of the Militarie men there.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A Regiment of <hi>Crabats</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed neere <hi>Wormbs,</hi> and their Colonell taken priſoner by <hi>Ramſey.</hi>
                  </note>About the tenth of <hi>December, ſtilo vetere,</hi> ſome ſelected Troopes being drawne out of the Preſidiarie Souldiers, to ſcoure the Countrie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about, paſſed the Rivers of <hi>Mayne,</hi> and the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and at <hi>Dirmſteim,</hi> a village neere <hi>Wormbs,</hi> lighted upon a Regiment of <hi>Crabats,</hi> and their Colonell <hi>Diſhchlier</hi> with them. The <hi>Crabats</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how they were ſurprized, prepared at once, (according to their cuſtome, borrowed from the <hi>Parthians</hi>) both for fight and flight; but being ſurrounded by the <hi>Hanawers,</hi> and forced to their Tackling, they fought till the major part of them being ſlaine, the Colonell and the reſt, ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelves as priſoners of Warre, they were carryed thence to <hi>Hanaw,</hi> with five Cornets, ſtore of money, and other good booty. One Prize prepareth the way for another; upon their returne homeward, intelligence was brought them, that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:7470:12"/>forty Tunnes of Wine were to be tranſported the next day from <hi>Franck-ford</hi> to <hi>Gieſſen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A Convoy for forty tunnes of Wine, taken by the <hi>Hana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer.</hi>
                  </note> for the uſe of the <hi>Lant-grave</hi> of <hi>Darmſtat.</hi> The Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der was made acquainted with the buſineſſe, and hee inſtantly arming foure hundred men, ſent out to attend the Convoy, which they met with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all fortunately, before they had paſſed a quarter of the journey, and in a ſhort conflict, having ſubdued the Waggoners which drove it, and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers which guarded it, brought it home to the Garriſon, with the Lieutenant which commanded it. This ſmall loſſe incenſed the <hi>Lant-grave</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Frank-forders,</hi> (whom hee accuſed as conſpiring with the <hi>Hanawers</hi> againſt him, though five of their men were ſlaine in ſeeking to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the charge committed to their truſt, preſſing them to make it good, otherwiſe menacing to confiſcate their goods which were in his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions) but haſtned the Treatie with <hi>Ramſey,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A foure mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths Truce concluded be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Darmſtat</hi> and <hi>Ramſay.</hi>
                  </note> to prevent any further detriment, which he follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo cloſely, that by the fourth of the month en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing a Truce was concluded on, to indure till <hi>May,</hi> with conditions of free trade and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce betwixt both parties, and that the <hi>Lant-grave</hi> ſhould furniſh the City with ſome thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands Malders of Corne, at ſixe Rixe-dollers the Malder, and if ſo much could not be obtained in the publike Markets, it ſhould then be taken out of his private Granaries. And this concluſion was joyfully received of all parties: however the premiſes were diſpleaſing, the <hi>Frank-forders,</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping by this meanes to enjoy the benefit of thoſe <hi>Muſarum Nundinae,</hi> their Mart, the <hi>Hanawers</hi> a time of breathing, and the <hi>Lant-grave</hi> more
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:7470:13"/>liberty to arme himſelfe for the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Saxon</hi> and Imperialiſts his Confederates.</p>
               <p>The Electorall Diet convented and commenced at <hi>Regenspurgh</hi> the laſt Summer, went on all this hurly-burly notwithſtanding; Many and ſeverall dayes were appointed for the Election of a King of the Romanes,<note place="margin">A new King of <hi>Romans</hi> elected.</note> and at the laſt, the twelfth of <hi>December</hi> old ſtile, was reſolved for the time, when without further delay the choyſe ſhould be. The Circumſtances required by the Golden Bull of <hi>Charles</hi> the fourth were all obſerved, ſave onely in the time of conſultation, the place of Election, and the perſons of the Electors. The time of conſultation preſcribed was bounded formerly with 30. dayes, and if in that ſpace the Electors could not agree, <hi>omnibus aliis detractis cibariis, praeter panem, &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam, nihil aliud illis detur,</hi> The Electors were to be fed with bread, and water, and nothing elſe till their votes were given up; yet here had beene a conſultation above foure moneths ſpace. The Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction was confined to <hi>Frank-ford,</hi> and there to the Church of Saint <hi>Bartholomew,</hi> this was made at <hi>Ratisbone.</hi> The power of Election was given to three <hi>German</hi> Prelates, <hi>Mentz</hi> the Arch-chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour of Germanie, <hi>Cologne</hi> Arch-chancellour of <hi>Italy, Triers</hi> Arch-chancellour of <hi>France;</hi> and three temporall Princes; the Prince <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine</hi> Arch-ſewer, the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> Sword-bearer, and the Marquis of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> High Chamberlane, theſe ſixe being all to be ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Elector of <hi>Mentz,</hi> and not to loſe their ſuffrages, unleſſe by a will-full default of abſence; yet here the Elector of <hi>Triers</hi> was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely denyed admittance, and the Elector <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:7470:13"/>never called, but another thruſt into his place, by the Title of the Elector of <hi>Bavaria;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Elector of <hi>Triers</hi> and <hi>Lant-grave</hi> of <hi>Caſſell.</hi>
                  </note> to the juſt greevance of ſome <hi>German</hi> Princes, who queſtioned the Juſtice of this Election, and not without ſome ground proteſted againſt it, not in reſpect of the perſon elected by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, being reported an hopefull Prince, of a good nature, and promiſing condition, but the indirect meanes of that Election. But diſputes were vaine, the Gowne-Law could not proove the Courſe illegall, and what-ever objection could be made to the contrary, the Electorall Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege proceeded, according to their firſt determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. To this end the Magiſtrate of <hi>Ratisbone</hi> attended with the Burgeſſes and the Governour, the Colonell <hi>Nidrun,</hi> wayted upon by the men of Armes aſſembled in the Towne-houſe, and by an oath of Allegiance confirmed the aſſurance of their loyalty to the Electors. The Bull required a privacie, that the Electors might conferre toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther freely, without interruption by the Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadors of Forraine Princes, or the Nobilitie of the Empire, by whoſe ſollicitation in behalfe of their particular friends, their Conſultation might be diſturbed, and a worke of this high conſequence be hindred. The ſame Evening therefore, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſearch was made throughout the Citie for all ſtrangers and ſuch as had no dependance upon the Emperour or the Electors, that they might be warned to depart the Citty, and not to returne thither, till the King of <hi>Romans</hi> was choſen, and this inquiſition was done ſo effectually, that the Spaniſh Embaſſadour, and his retinew retired the ſame night to <hi>Straubinguen,</hi> to abide there, till
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:7470:14"/>hee might without offence to their proceedings returne to <hi>Ratisbone.</hi> The day following the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> and his Lady, arrived at the City in great ſtate, and the next day <hi>December</hi> 11.21. about nine in the morning, the Electors having before that fathomed each other, and deſigned the perſon privately whom they meant that day to proclaime publikely, repayred firſt to the State-houſe, the place appointed for their meeting, and thence marched magnificently towards the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall Church, where they were to give in their ſuffrages.</p>
               <p>The proceſſe of all was thus: the preſent Electors and the Deputies of them which were abſent, having uſed the State-houſe as a Veſtry for putting on their Electorall Robes, went thence to the Thumb (or Cathedrall Church) in this order. They were divided into three rankes, which in State obſerving an equall diſtance, each from other, were thus marſhalled. Firſt went the Electors of <hi>Ments</hi> and <hi>Cologne;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The manner and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection.</note> 
                  <hi>Mentz</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the right-hand File, and <hi>Cologne</hi> the left; The next to theſe were the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> on the right-hand, and the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> on the left, and laſt <hi>Frederick</hi> of <hi>Metſch,</hi> repreſenting the Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> who had on his left-hand the Count of <hi>Swartzemburg,</hi> as Deputie in the preſent Diet for the Marqueſſe of <hi>Brandenburg.</hi> Before them was carryed a Sword in its ſcabberd, but as ſoone as they came to the Cathedrall, the Sword-bearer retired, the Church doores were made faſt, a Maſſe ſung by the Elector of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logne,</hi> and then, after ſome few other Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, which laſted till about twelve of the clocke,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:7470:14"/>
                  <hi>FERDINAND the Third,</hi> King of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garie,</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> eldeſt Sonne to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> was proclaimed the Elected King of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Ceremonies paſt, the Emperour adorned with his Imperiall Habite was brought in a chaire to the Church, and <hi>Te Deum</hi> being ſung, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingled with many great thunderclaps from the great Ordnance and Muſquets, the Electors tooke horſe, twenty foure Trumpets and a Kettle-drum ſounding before them, the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the Ball of the Empire, <hi>Metſch</hi> and <hi>Swart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zenburg</hi> the Scepter, and the Marſhall <hi>Pappen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heim,</hi> a naked Sword immediatly before <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who followed in a Chaire of State, with the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Crowne upon his head attended by the King of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> both of them being under a ſtarry Canopy, guarded with the Elector of <hi>Mentz</hi> on the right hand, and the Elector of <hi>Cologne</hi> on the left, and ſo paſſed upon a Galle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie addreſſed for that purpoſe to the Emperours Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, where they were entertained the next day with a ſumptuous Feaſt, the Confectioners ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their Art to ſet forth a Banquet, and his Imperiall Majeſtie deſiring to expreſſe his grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full heart for their willingneſſe to ſuffragate ſo unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly for the Kings election.</p>
               <p>Nothing was then wanting, which could be expected at a dayes preparation, but the Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the new King, <hi>December</hi> 19.29 was with much more ſolemnity then his Election, and the Coronation of the Queene, though celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more privately, was nothing inferiour to the Kings in glory. The time betwixt his Majeſties
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:7470:15"/>Election and Coronation, was ſpent in ordering of things required for ſuch a day, and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of Civill Juſtice. The dignitie of State required the firſt, the ſafety which by impunity of offenders muſt needs be endangered, preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the other. The Royall Veſtiments which from the time of <hi>Charle-Magne,</hi> were cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily uſed at ſuch Solemnities, were then at <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remberg,</hi> and thither a Currier was diſpached to the Magiſtrate and Governour for them, who upon ſight of the Letters, attended with them per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally to <hi>Regenspurgh.</hi> Thus this order was obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved faithfully; but the deſigne for execution of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice fell not out ſo happily; <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſchius</hi> a Doctor of Lawes,<note place="margin">The Syndick of <hi>Cologne</hi> mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſpurgh.</hi>
                  </note> and Advocate for the Elector of <hi>Cologne,</hi> was murdered in his owne lodging by ſome malitio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s aſſaſſinates, who either ſought his life, or treaſure, of which though they were ſeized, yet fearing it ſeemes to be diſcovered,</p>
               <p>(<hi>Quinam hominum eſt, quem tu contentum videris uno Flagitio?</hi> One ſin never comes unattended) they deprived him alſo of the other, and remaining ſtill unknowne, the Magiſtrate propounded great rewards to them, or him that could reveale them, whether parties in the crime or not, and to the firſt a pardon for their treſpaſſe, beſides the pecuniary guerdon, upon condition onely, to deſcrie their, or his complices, but all was frivolous; the nigh-birds kept ſtill cloſe together, and all they which once had ſo farre exceeded the bounds of honeſty, were reſolved to continue in their courſe and not reveale the villany.</p>
               <p>Yet, though the courſe of Juſtice was thus impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited, the Pompe of State went on: The prefixed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:7470:15"/>day, for ſetting the Crowne upon the Kings head, was obſerved; and then the King,<note place="margin">The King of <hi>Romans</hi> crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> to ſhew his Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence ſcattered ſome Medalls of Gold and Silver amongſt the people, whereon his Armes, Name, the day and yeere of his Coronation, were engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. An Oxe roaſted whole, larded with Partridges, and ſtuffed with a Calfe, and two Muttons, was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the ſpoyle of the common people: The great Conduit ranne White and Claret Wine. The Marſhall of the Empire, having brought a great heape of Oates into the open ſtreet, carryed away a ſmall Meaſure, and left the reſt, not to be ſhared amongſt the people by meaſure, but caught up and carryed away by as many as would and could catch it; tore the Cloth in pieces, with which the Bridge was covered that day, for the paſſage of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and the Grand States of the Empire, and diſtributed it amongſt the common people. And thus the Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Ceremonies, for that day, were accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed.</p>
               <p>The Queene as yet remained uncrowned: for hough the King and ſhee made but one Body, and it might be ſuppoſed, that in him ſhee had ſeiſure of that Character of Royall Dignitie, yet her tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples were to bee impaled alſo with a materiall Crowne, according to the cuſtome of the Empire; and <hi>Decemb.</hi> 29. <hi>Jan.</hi> 7. was deſigned, for that Rituall tranſaction. Three dayes before, were ſpent in revelling; the Queene giving entertainment to the Empreſſe, the Ducheſſe of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> and the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Court, with Feaſts, Muſicke, Maskes, and what-ever elſe could be thought of, requiſite for the <hi>Bien-venu</hi> of ſuch great Perſonages. This time thus expired, the ſolemne day for the Queenes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auguration
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:7470:16"/>was come: and then ſhee in State being brought into the Church, after a Maſle chaunted by the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Queenes Coronation.</note> was carried in a Chaire to the high Altar, cloſe to the King her Husbands ſide, and had the Crowne put upon her head; which, though weightie, ſhee wore by the ſpace of a quarter of an houre, and returned to his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Majeſties Palace.</p>
               <p>It was a day of much joy to the <hi>Spaniards</hi> then at <hi>Ratisbone;</hi> and they, to expreſſe the content re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by this Solemnitie, made the Night aemulate the Day, ſhining as bright with Piles of artificiall Fires, rayſed before their Doores, as the Sunne in his glory. But the Embaſſadour, as in dignitie of place alone, ſo in expence there, exceeded all the reſt joyntly; the night did not terminate his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The next day, hee invited the new King and Queene, and the perſonages of qualitie in the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Court, to his houſe, entertained them with a ſtately Banquet; during the which, tenne Hogges-heads of Wine being brought, one after another, into a great Bay-Window, were rapped, and let runne into a Ciſterne below, for the uſe of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; who ſhared therein, and in many pieces of Gold and Silver, halfe Piſtolets, Ryals of eight, and leſſer Money, which hee ſcrambled amongſt the people, to be divided by fortune, not his owne arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trement.</p>
               <p>The former Magnificence, was in expence of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; but another ſort followed it, by advancement of ſome perſons of qualitie to ſome Titles of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. The Kings comming to the Crowne, was not in all points like the Sunnes appearing in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon, to eclipſe the glory of the <hi>Minor</hi> Starres,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:7470:16"/>and burie their ſplendour in his owne; his promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the height of Majeſtie, was the exaltation of certaine Peeres to more Honour: Sixteene Noblemen were created Knights of the Empire; namely, the Lord <hi>Maximilian Williband,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">New Knights of the Empire made.</note> Earle of <hi>Wollfseck;</hi> the Earle <hi>Adam Budiani; John Jacob,</hi> Earle of <hi>Zyll; Peter,</hi> Earle of <hi>Goetſen; John Anthony,</hi> Earle of <hi>Cratz; Henry Erneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerpen,</hi> Earle of <hi>Toringe; Ladiſlaus Schechii; William Voight,</hi> Lord of <hi>Maxwein; John Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolph,</hi> and <hi>George Rudolph,</hi> of <hi>Haslang;</hi> the Baron <hi>William Dieterick,</hi> of <hi>Runen; John Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,</hi> of <hi>Startzhauſen; George,</hi> of <hi>Seibolſdorff; Stephen Esterhaſi; John Philip Gunter;</hi> and <hi>Henry Christopher,</hi> of <hi>Flaus:</hi> The Duke of <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> attending upon the King, in the qualitie of a Cup-bearer; and the Prince of <hi>Anhalt</hi> perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Office of his Carver, during the time of feaſting at this Solemnitie.</p>
               <p>THE Aſtrologians benigne Starre, <hi>Iupiter,</hi> ſeemed now to ſmile upon the Court at <hi>Ratisbone,</hi> with a ſweet aſpect, but <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Saturne</hi> reigned abroad; Prodigies terrifying the hearts of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, while the Princes and Peeres were in this jollitie; and Warre, with his grim atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, Famine, Peſt, Feare, and Diſtraction, raging abroad in the Empire. What might happen, by the fault of a careleſſe or unskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:7470:17"/>Maſon, not well bedding or cementing the Stones,<note place="margin">Strange Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies.</note> at the building of a new Steeple at <hi>Vienna,</hi> was by the conſtruction of the vulgar ſort counted ominous: The Spire of <hi>S. Shotten,</hi> lately built, fell downe ſuddenly, about the time of the Coronation, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moliſhed the Church, and that was made portentous; the rather, being accompanied with another of the ſame time at <hi>Rome;</hi> where, a great blazing Starre, called by the Naturaliſts <hi>Cometa Crinitus,</hi> appeared for a ſpace, and then vaniſhed away ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, over S. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, with a noyſe; And diverſe Monuments, placed in the Church, fell downe, and were defaced ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:7470:17"/>
               <head>CHAPTER II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The death of the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond: with the ſiege and taking of <hi>Erford</hi> by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> and other things.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T would reliſh of over-much boldneſſe to peepe into the Arke of the divine ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, nor dare I, nor can I conclude any particular conſequences to haue been portended by the accidentary fall of the Pyramis, yet doubtleſſe the Comet though cauſed by the meeting of ſecondary and naturall cauſes, was the ſignificator of what enſued about that time, and not long after. Within the ſpace of a moneth a titular God of the world, and one that claimed a ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oritie aboue the reſt (though all abſolute and undependant Princes, which hold the Scepter by inheritance, not ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, may juſtly vie with him for eminency of place) <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond, who had long been ſickly at <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſpurgh,</hi> and then removed to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ienna,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The death of the Emperor <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond.</note> gaue a teſtimonie of his mortalitie, by ſubſcribing to the lawes of Nature, and exhaling his laſt ſpirit, <hi>Feb.</hi> 2/15. betwixt 8. and 9. of the clock in the morning, to the great griefe of the Court and City, which had prepared triumphs, and tournaments, and in much bravery determined to receiue the new King of <hi>Romanes,</hi> but by this occaſion laid aſide their gallantrie, put on the face and weeds of ſorrow, and by their dejected lookes and mourning apparell, ſhewed their anxietie for his loſſe, who ſo long had ſteered the ſhip of State, to their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:7470:18"/>content, and was then taken from them when the tottering Empire, freſhly aſſaulted and ranſackt by ſtrangers, requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſuch a <hi>Neſtor,</hi> as by ſage directions, grounded upon mature deliberations might preſerue it from feare of ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ruine. The ſame afternoone his bodie was embalmed, and two dayes after he was laid in the <hi>Antecamerâ,</hi> to the ſight of all that came in: and <hi>Feb.</hi> 8/18. his corps was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into his own Chappell at the Palace, to be kept there till the King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> (who was then upon the <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nubie,</hi> returning with his Queene from <hi>Ratisbone</hi> by wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) was come thither to giue order and inſtructions for the manner of his interrment.</p>
               <p>About the ſame time, abroad, the <hi>Swedes</hi> growne eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where Maſters of the field, began againe to take in Townes, giue Lawes to the Citizens, ſweare the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates to alleageance to the Crowne of <hi>Sweden,</hi> take Hoſtages for performance of Conditions, plunder the Countrey, where they enquartered, to furniſh their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies with neceſſaries, and force the Cities which ſtood in faire tearmes of agreement with <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the Elector of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and the other Princes, which either ſided with the Emperour, before the treatie of <hi>Prague,</hi> or came in to him thereupon, to renounce their alliance, and take in their <hi>Swediſh</hi> Garriſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leſlie</hi> the Feeldmarſhall, being come back from <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalia,</hi> from purſuit of the <hi>Caeſarean</hi> Generall <hi>Goetz,</hi> was come back to the Lantgravate of <hi>Heſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Caſſell</hi> wher mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Generall, he received a new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, to returne towards the <hi>Weſer,</hi> to haue an eye upon the <hi>mperialiſts,</hi> and the League, <hi>Bannier</hi> ſuppoſing that bodie of an Armie which himſelfe commanded, ſufficient for performance of his own deſignes in the upper <hi>Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> there yet appearing no adverſe Armie which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſtand againſt him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leſlie</hi> conformed him to his Generalls Command, and <hi>Bannier</hi> without further ſtay marched with his forces towards <hi>Miſnia.</hi> But <hi>Ertford,</hi> that goodly Citie of <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringen</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:7470:18"/>againe preſented it ſelfe to his fancy, as he was upon the way; ſomewhat he reſolved to doe there, yet what or how he made a pauſe on; to leaue it behind him, he concluded to be no part of policie, the place being of great receit, and well fortified, both with a Moat, good walls, and the ſtrong Caſtle of <hi>Ziriacksburg,</hi> and ſo, if once furniſhed by his enemies but with fifteene hundred preſidiaries, might moleſt his Armie; to attempt it by force, or a long Siege, might waſte his forces, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume much time: Theſe doubts ſtumbled him, yet in fine he reſolved to take it by a fineneſſe (if it might be) and if that way thrived not, to worke otherwiſe. And take it in the end he did, nor was the deſigne any remora to his further proceedings, being but a whet to ſharpen the courage of his Souldiers, no ſtop or let to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes. <hi>Decemb.</hi> ½ 1/1. <hi>Bannier</hi> tooke up his head-quarter at <hi>Deberſtead,</hi> a village not farre from <hi>Ertford,</hi> and the ſame Evening, to loſe no time, firſt preſented part of his Forces in a ſmall Battalia before the Fort of <hi>Ziriacks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> and then rode in perſon to the gates of the Citie, demanding of the Governour,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ertford</hi> ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned.</note> whether he would declare himſelfe a friend or enemy to the Crowne of <hi>Sweden?</hi> The former paſſage, and treatie before his purſuit of the confederate Imperiall Generalls, made him confident, that the Governour would anſwer his demand modeſtly, without any rude expreſſion of hoſtilitie: and modeſtly he anſwered indeed, that he had no order from the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate to declare himſelfe an enemie, when the <hi>Swede</hi> catching the words from his mouth, before he could make an end, replyed mildly, Nor am I yours. The Governour intended to tell him, that he would conferre with the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, and follow the order which he ſhould preſcribe, but <hi>Bannier</hi> unwilling to admit any demurre in the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſtayed not to attend their conference, but inſtantly having before hand expreſſed himſelfe by writing, called for a Trumpetter and ſent him into the Citie with Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, requiring the Magiſtrate to ſend his Deputies to the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:7470:19"/>Campe, with whom he would parlee for the benefit and preſervation of that Citie. The Magiſtrate regarding the ſafetie of the Citizens, and conceiving that the <hi>Swede</hi> would demand nothing but a ſupply of neceſſaries, as cloaths and victualls for his Armie; ſent ſome of the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Burgheſſes the next day to deale according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, which himſelfe by adviſe of the Senate the night before had concluded on, and confined them to. Early in the morning the <hi>Swede</hi> roade about the Citie, viewed the fortificatio s, and before the Deputies came, was returned to his tent. Yet at laſt they came, were entertained kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and with many proteſtations of his affection to their State, which he deſired, that they would anſwer againe with a Remonſtrance of the like loue to him, by renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the treatie, and concluſions at <hi>Prague,</hi> by remaining conſtant to the Crowne of <hi>Sweden,</hi> as they had been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly, by ſurrendring unto him the Fort of <hi>Ziriacksburg,</hi> and accepting of a <hi>Swediſh</hi> Garriſon; which conditions if they liked of, he promiſed to protect them, and would neither deſire any ſupply of money, or other neceſſaries from the Citizens.</p>
               <p>The Burgheſſes perceived, that his Oration which at firſt was ſmoothed with oylie words, came off with a ſharpe twang, that a bitter pill was tendered them, though covered with gold, and though they might haue anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him without pauſing, being inſtructed by their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, yet deſired leaue to goe backe to the Senate, promiſing faithfully to returne an anſwer the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Their deſire was granted by the <hi>Swede,</hi> and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed anſwer was ſent by a Trumpeter according to the ſet time by them; but not ſuiting to the demand, ſaue onely in flat deniall, the Citizens having reſolved to ſtand upon their defence, and rather endure the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences which attend a Siege, than ſubſcribe to thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</p>
               <p>The Generall was the ſame day invited to dinner by Duke <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Wymar,</hi> and had appointed to meete
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:7470:19"/>him, that their alliance might be renewed, and by a good correſpondence, they might be aſſiſtant, each to other; and this occaſion hindered the <hi>Swede</hi> from planting his battery againſt the Citie that day, conceiving that unleſſe his eye was over the worke, it would not be done to the beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage: onely for that preſent, he gaue order to ſome Troopes of Horſe, to ſcoure the tetritorie about the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of <hi>Saal;</hi> which was done, and at night they returned to the Campe,<note place="margin">Beſieged by the <hi>Swedes.</hi>
                  </note> bringing with them ſome <hi>Saxon</hi> Officers priſoners. The next morning very early the Generall commanded his Canons to be planted upon an hill neere <hi>Daberſtead,</hi> and then the Gunnes played their parts ſo well, that fiftie great ſhot in a ſmall ſpace were diſcharged againſt the Citie, and more were readie, but that a Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball caſt into the Towne, having fired two Barnes, and a dwelling houſe, the Generall gaue order to giue off ſhoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, till he had againe felt the pulſe of the Magiſtrate, by ſending a Drumme unto the Citie, to wiſh the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants to treate with him fairely, and not haſten their own ruine, promiſing that whatſoever was paſt notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, he would uſe them with all lenitie, and lay no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable burdens upon them. The Senate gaue audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Meſſenger, and ſent two ſelected men of qualitie, to conferre againe with the Generall, yet firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Hoſtages for the ſafetie of the Senators (Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Goltz,</hi> and his Lievtenant) a ceſſation of Armes for twenty-foure houres was the firſt propoſition made by the Agents for the Citie, and that obtained, they craved leaue to depart, ſhewing a contentedneſſe in their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances, that they could ſo eaſily prevaile for what they deſired with him, which not many houres before ſeemed an implacalbe Enemie. But the Campe made better uſe of this time of forbearing offenſiue Armes, than the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie did; defences were not prohibited, it was lawfull for either partie to doe any thing in that ſhort time of truce, for their owne defence and ſafetie; though not to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment of the other: and <hi>Bannier</hi> uſed not his men as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:7470:20"/>Souldiers, but pioners, their weapons that day were mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tock and ſpade, and thoſe proved as ſerviceable for his purpoſe, as the thundering Ordnance. The Briarean hands of the labouring men, not hindered by any adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, made a quick diſpatch of much worke; by the Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, the approaches were brought to the very gates of the Citie, and the Caſtle-walls, and then both the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the Militarie men,<note place="margin">Surrendred upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polition.</note> and the civill Magiſtrate, perceiving how the <hi>Swede</hi> had over-reached them by a fineneſſe, feared his force, and yeelded themſelues and the place upon theſe enſuing Conditions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That the ſort of <hi>Ziriacksburg</hi> ſhould receiue for a Garriſon,<note place="margin">The Articles</note> a hundred of the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Souldiers, and a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the Citie, all to be commanded by a <hi>Swede,</hi> who ſhould giue an oath of loyaltie, both to the Crowne of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and the Citie.</p>
               <p>Secondly, The Citie ſhall not be charged with enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of any Souldiers, but its owne, and which ſhall be governed by a particular Commander, and both the Souldiers and their Chieftaine ſhall ſweare as well to the Crowne of <hi>Sweden,</hi> as the Citie.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, The Keyes of the gates ſhall be kept by the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, The Citizens ſhall abide true and faithfull to the Crowne of <hi>Sweden,</hi> till a firme and conſtant peace be ſetled in the Empire, &amp;c. that the Citie at all times when neceſſitie requireth it, ſhall giue free paſſe and repaſſe to the <hi>Swedes,</hi> according to the occaſion.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, The Citie ſhall pay the Souldiers in the Armie 36000. Rix-dollars, whereof 10000. ſhall be paid imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately in readie money, and 16000. in wares, and the reſt within the ſpace of ſix weekes.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, In this agreement ſhall be comprehended all the Nobilitie, Gentry, and <hi>Saxon</hi> Officers, which are fled to the Citie for refuge and protection, with their moveables, and other goods.</p>
               <p>Theſe Articles were ſealed on both ſides <hi>Decemb.</hi> 16/26.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:7470:20"/>the gates of the Citie ſet open for the <hi>Swedes</hi> entry, the Caſtle delivered, and a <hi>Swediſh</hi> Commander put into it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gleen</hi> according to the order received from <hi>Caeſar,</hi> was then upon his march towards <hi>Weſtphalia</hi> to unite his <hi>Wirtembergers</hi> to <hi>Goetz</hi> and <hi>Hatzfie dt;</hi> when <hi>Bann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er</hi> thus thrived in <hi>Thuringen.</hi> The depth of winter could not ſtay his journey, nor the cold of the ſeaſon congeale the burning deſire the Imperiall Commanders had generally, to inable themſelues to meete and fight with the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Armie: but ſuccours came in ſlowly elſe-where, the Duke of <hi>Lunenburgh</hi> ſtood a while as a newter, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring himſelfe till the Spring approached: onely <hi>Gleen</hi> the moſt forward for the preſent, proved moſt unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. Foure compleate Regiments by the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Land-grave</hi> of <hi>Darmſtad</hi> he had drawen together,<note place="margin">4. Imperial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Regiments defeated by <hi>Stalhaus.</hi>
                  </note> and knowing where the groſſe of <hi>Banniers</hi> Army was, thought to finde a way from <hi>Franconia</hi> to <hi>Weſtphalia</hi> by <hi>Heſſen</hi>-land, or if any ſtragling <hi>Swedes</hi> ſhould happen by the way; able to encounter with them, and chaſe them, and ſo cleare the paſſage by his power. Some <hi>Swediſh</hi> troopes appeared in <hi>Franconia</hi> upon the river of <hi>Sala,</hi> and they deſcrying the <hi>Caeſarean</hi> Commander upon his march, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred as afraid of him, into the Foreſt of <hi>Thuringen.</hi> It is the condition of an ambitious man to thinke all others ſtand in awe of him, and he that concludeth of colours by a falſe glaſſe, apprehendeth things otherwiſe then they are; The <hi>Caeſarean</hi> tooke their retirement, for a plaine flight, and thinking to over-reach and ſurpriſe them, ſpurred up after them; when ſuddenly himſelfe was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertaken being encountred by <hi>Stalhauſe,</hi> (whom till then they had nor diſcovered) unexpectedly. There were in that Army ſome men of qualitie, and of a ſpirit tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending the condition they were then in; the Count of <hi>Furſtemburg,</hi> the Colonels <hi>Princk, Mantenfell,</hi> and <hi>Ramſdorff,</hi> all daring men, and as able for ſervice, as da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, though now they were unhappily over-weighed. Theſe great hearts ſaw the preſent danger, yet undaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:7470:21"/>with it they rather armed for battel, then either to run or yeeld,<note place="margin">700 of them ſlaine, and 2 Colonels ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken priſoners</note> and fight they did valiantly, but not fortunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and the <hi>Wirtemberger</hi> Regiment encouraged by the example of their Leaders, followed on as reſolutely, holding out almoſt to the laſt man. The horſe onely play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the jades, for the Cavalliers ſeeing the <hi>Swedes</hi> come on impetuouſly and finding themſelues a little galled by the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Musketiers, inſtead of fighting againſt them ranne unto them, leaving the foote to the mercie, or furie of their enemie, who ſlew 700. upon the place, tooke neere as many priſoners, and amongſt the reſt, the two laſt-na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Colonells, gained three peeces of Ordnance mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked with the armes of <hi>Gleen,</hi> and purſued the reſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to <hi>Wertzburg</hi> where <hi>Princk</hi> who had his horſe ſlaine under him in the battell, and <hi>Gleen,</hi> and <hi>Furſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> ſaved themſelues with much difficultie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bannier</hi> having ordered things at <hi>Ertford,</hi> marched thence with his Armie conſiſting of ſixteene Regiments of horſe, and two thouſand foote <hi>Decemb.</hi> 21. <hi>old-ſtile,</hi> when taking up his head quarter at <hi>Eckersburg,</hi> and <hi>Schult-porten,</hi> he firſt ſummoned <hi>Naumburg,</hi> the firſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in <hi>Misnia,</hi> on the weſt ſide of <hi>Sala,</hi> and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander there refuſing to come in upon his ſummons, hee planted a batterie, and without much expenſe of powder and ſhot, the Citizens carefull to preſerue their owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, diſſenting from the Praeſidiarie Souldiers, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained the Burgeſſes friendly, but forced the men of Armes to come in upon diſcretion; and the <hi>Saxon</hi> Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Colonell which commanded there, the Major and two Captaines he detained as priſoners of warre, yet the common Souldiers, 150. in number, obtained their lives and liberties by taking ſervice under him. Thence hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved his Campe towards <hi>Moerſburg,</hi> an Epiſcopall Citie upon the ſame River, which ſubmitting it ſelfe to the <hi>Swede</hi> upon the ſighf of his Army,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leipſich</hi> ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned.</note> he conducted his forces immediately towards <hi>Leipſich,</hi> where finding two reſolute Commanders the Earles of <hi>Tranſdorff,</hi> arming
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:7470:21"/>themſelues and fortifying the place againſt the furie of his ordnance, and danger by the granadoes, veſſels of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being placed in the ſtreetes, the houſes covered with wet skinnes, and nothing omitted which the caſe of a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged place required for its conſervation. <hi>Ian.</hi> 1. <hi>old ſtile</hi> he ſummoned the Citie, and the Caſtle of <hi>Pleiſemburg</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning to it, and receiving a joynt anſwer of refuſall to ſurrender, from the brethren which commanded ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Fort and Citie, he threatned to enforce it, yet for the preſent onely blocked it up, and before he had ſpent a ſhot againſt ir, or received one from it, marched thence with the other part of his Army towards <hi>Eulen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> whither he had ſent <hi>Stalhauſe</hi> before him,<note place="margin">The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour reſolved to defend it.</note> with the greater part of his Cavallarie to diſcover the power and poſture of the Generall Major <hi>Dehne,</hi> whoſe purpoſe by intercepted letters directed to the Governour of <hi>Leip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſich,</hi> being to bring 2000. men which he had then at <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenburg</hi> in foure Regiments for his aſſiſtance, was by this meanes prevented, and way made for the <hi>Swedes</hi> further conqueſts. The <hi>Saxon</hi> Commander had notice of the <hi>Swedes</hi> before hand, and halfe an houre before that <hi>Stal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſe</hi> his Avantguard could reach to his late quarter, was riſen and rode upon the ſpurre toward <hi>Torgaw,</hi> the care of that Citie being committed to his truſt by the Elector, who himſelfe being ſecure no where, went from <hi>Leip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſich</hi> to <hi>Torgaw,</hi> upon the firſt report of the <hi>Swedes</hi> being at <hi>Ertfort,</hi> and thence to <hi>Dreſden,</hi> every where as hee paſſed giving a great charge to the Commanders and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, and taking oathes of them, to ſtand to him faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and not deliver up his townes, unleſſe by neceſſitie into the hands of his enemies.</p>
               <p>Yet the fate of the Generall Major depending upon that dayes ſervice, though he had gotten the advantage of way, and was upon the ſpeed, could not preſerue the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, nor his forces. <hi>Stalhauſe</hi> ſeeing him gone made after a-maine, and though he could nor overtake the Avant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> wherein <hi>Dehne,</hi> and <hi>Wilſdorffe,</hi> his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:7470:22"/>aequall in militarie dignitie was, he overtooke the Reere conducted by the Colonell <hi>Shletonitz,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Colonel <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hne</hi> rowted.</note> and after a ſmall battell, wherein he had ſlaine 200. of his men, tooke the Colonell himſelfe, and 200. others priſoners, deprived them of foure Standards and Enſignes, and purſued the Generall Major to the gates of the Citie, which though it held out that night, was ſurrendered the next day to the Generall <hi>Bannier,</hi> as ſoone as he appeared before it with his Army, the ſeaſon favouring his attempt, glazing up the <hi>Elve,</hi> and expoſing the Fort before the Bridge, and the Bridge too, to his obedience, upon conditions to ſpare the lives and liberties of the Praeſidiarie Souldiers, both Commanders and ordinarie men, they againe condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to depart without weapons, &amp; to deliver the <hi>Swedes</hi> the Enſignes, and 32. Standards which were then in the Citie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:7470:22"/>
               <head>CHAPTER III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Torgaw</hi> taken from the <hi>Saxon,</hi> the Garriſon turne to the <hi>Swedes,</hi> with the ſiege of <hi>Leip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſich,</hi> and the abandoning of it againe by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> and other things.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Conqueſt was of no ſmall conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, the <hi>Saxons</hi> loſſe was greater in the concluſion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Torgaw</hi> taken by <hi>Bannier.</hi>
                  </note> then in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and the <hi>Swedes</hi> advantage much more. Beſides 1200. foote which were garriſond in the Citie, there were at the ſame preſent alſo 2500. men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to ſeverall Regiments fled thither for their ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, and theſe upon the ſurrender of the place, thinking to have had libertie to depart, with their Armes and bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, as being none of the Garriſon, were upon their march in a fayre aequipage, with 12. Enſignes, &amp; 5. peeces of Canon, which the Electour had ſaved from the <hi>Swedes</hi> at the battell of <hi>Witſtocke.</hi> But upon them too the <hi>Swede</hi> ſeized, and giving libertie to the Commanders to be gone but not without a checke, and ſome reproaches for their perfidious dealing with the Crowne of <hi>Sweden</hi> (to which they had once ſworne fealtie and ſincere alliance) and ſurpriſall of their baggage,<note place="margin">The <hi>Saxon</hi> Garriſon ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth pay of the <hi>Swedes.</hi>
                  </note> he diſmounted and diſarmed the under-officers and common Souldiers, who percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving their nakedneſſe of a ſudden tendered him their ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:7470:23"/>and tooke pay under him, hoping of better wages from him, then they could expect from the Elector; <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nier</hi> having lately taken from him the moſt part of his treaſurie at <hi>Leichtenburg,</hi> and now enriched with a new bootie, valued at above one million, 16000. Rix-dollers whereof lately appertained to the Generall Major <hi>Deh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some men haue got wealth by their loſſes, like <hi>Pompo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius Laetus</hi> in <hi>Sabellicus,</hi> who having his houſe pillaged, received double ſo much as he loſt by the bountie of his friends. But the <hi>Saxon</hi> Generalls caſe was otherwiſe, with the Citie,<note place="margin">The Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Dehne</hi> beheaded.</note> (to the Government whereof he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended by the Elector for his good ſervice in relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Fort of <hi>Mansfeldt</hi>) he loſt his eſtate, and life, the <hi>Swedes</hi> having got his treaſure, and the Elector ſoone after cutting off his head, for ſurrendring the Citie; and the Elector himſelfe, with that particular place, loſt more, <hi>Meiſſen,</hi> the chiefe Citie of <hi>Miſnia, Eulemburg, Grim, Borne, Debitz, Bitterfeldt, Belgeren,</hi> and <hi>Hall,</hi> yeelding inſtantly to the Conquerour, having no hope of reliefe by any confederate Armie; Onely <hi>Dreſden</hi> of all the umbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall Cities of <hi>Saxonie</hi> held out ſtill, yet not without feare of being made the ſpoyle of ſtrangers, the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Armies, being ſo farre from their ſuccours, that their march and places of reſt, were unknowne to the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens.</p>
               <p>But the loſſe of <hi>Torgaw,</hi> was no ſmall meanes for the libertie and deliverance of <hi>Leipſich;</hi> the vigilant Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander there, ſlipt no opportunitie, which preſented it ſelfe unto him, and perceiving the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Armie, both horſe and foote diſcamping <hi>Ian.</hi> 4. <hi>old ſtile,</hi> and upon their march towards <hi>Torgaw,</hi> the ſame night ſent forth three hundred Musketiers and two hundred horſe, to ſearch for the ſtragling <hi>Swedes,</hi> which were lurking about the Villages neere <hi>Eulenburg,</hi> and were not gone with the maine body of the Armie. The <hi>Saxon</hi> Souldiers went on with as little noyſe as might be, and covering the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:7470:23"/>with the darkneſſe of the night, fell unexpectedly upon a ſmall Troope of <hi>Swediſh</hi> horſe,<note place="margin">A Troope of <hi>Swediſh</hi> horſe ſurprized.</note> which had taken up their nights lodging in one of the Villages, and ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed them. The <hi>Swediſh</hi> Ritmaſter, whoſe courage ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounted his preſent power, began to make ſome reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, yet oppreſt with a farre ſuperiour number of <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and dangerouſly wounded, was forced to yeeld, and himſelfe and the moſt part of that Cavallary, ſome few onely ſaving themſelues by flight with a Preacher to the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Armie, were made priſoners, and carried to <hi>Leipſich.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This proſperous deſigne, gaue the Souldiers and Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants a ſmall aſſurance of ſpeedie deliverance; ſome concluded, that the <hi>Swedes</hi> had received notice of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall ſuccours, which the <hi>Leipzickers</hi> expected daily; others, that <hi>Mansfeild</hi> with his <hi>Sileſian</hi> Armie, had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded the Marquiſate of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and was too ſtrong for <hi>Wrangell,</hi> to whoſe care that Province was left, and that <hi>Bannier</hi> was enforced to march backe againe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue him; others, <hi>(it is common with men to beleeue what they deſire)</hi> that <hi>Bannier</hi> and his Armies diſcamping,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leipſich</hi> victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aled and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified.</note> was rather a flight for their owne preſervation, than a warlike March for further execution, and with confidence fed with ayerie hopes, proclaimed their owne deliverie. But the provident, and valiant Commander, fore-caſted what might enſue, and as one not fearing any preſent danger, opened the Grimmer, or South gate, yet as not ſecure, kept the reſt locked up, and knowing, that beſides offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue and defenſiue Armes, Victualls, and other proviſions neceſſarie for life, were required to hold out a Siege, in the abſence of the <hi>Swedes,</hi> which continued the ſpace of ſeaven dayes, ſent into the Countrey, for Cattell, Corne, Hay, Oats, and Wood, which he beſtowed in the Zim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer houſe, and <hi>Baarfuper</hi> Church, (neceſſitie cauſing him to turne that conſecrated ground to a prophane uſe) as in two Magaſines: armed two thouſand luſtie young Pren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:7470:24"/>and Journeymen, to ſerue as Souldiers, ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the fortifications, and omitted nothing which might ſeeme needfull to preſerue the Citie, ſuſpecting the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne of the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Forces thither.</p>
               <p>His conjecture was not miſplaced, <hi>Ian.</hi> 12. <hi>old ſtile,</hi> the avantguard of the <hi>Swedes</hi> was diſcovered upon <hi>Gods<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aker,</hi> early in the morning, and were ſaluted with ſome Volleyes of Canon-ſhot, from the Fort of <hi>Pleiſſenburg,</hi> and Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Bulwarke, yet without any offence done, (the Ordnance not anſwerable to the Commanders de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leipſich</hi> again ſummoned.</note> could not reach them) the whole Hoaſt, deſigned for that ſervice, with their Waggons and baggage were deſcryed, comming over <hi>Schoenfeldt,</hi> under their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall the Earle of <hi>Brandeſteine.</hi> The <hi>Swedes</hi> obſerved the methode of a faire Enemie, ſending word firſt by a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peter to the Citie of their purpoſe, intending to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for the blow, if the anſwer did not ſuite with their demand: The inſtructions given the Meſſenger, were in round and peremptorie words, to tell the Commander, that his Generall deſired to know, whether he would ſurrender the Citie upon a faire Compoſition, or ſee it become a pillar of fire, and ſmoke; and though delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red rudely, was anſwered as roundly: the Commander replying, that he could not, nor would complie himſelfe to his deſire; and that, whatſoever the <hi>Swede</hi> had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to himſelfe, it was not in his owne abilitie to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme; but muſt be referred to the fortune of warre.</p>
               <p>Words were bootleſſe, the <hi>Swede</hi> prepared preſently for the Siege, and the next morning was ſtrongly entren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched before the Grimmer gate, upon the ſtone way, and planted himſelfe in the New, and Back ſtreets, and other houſes neare the Citie. And the Earle of <hi>Tranſdorff,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, neglected not to make his defences, armed the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, which were neare the wall, namely, Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> Colledge, the Great, and New Colledges, and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Thomas</hi> his Schoole, with Souldiers and Artillerie, making a vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:7470:24"/>for the Students, by converting thoſe Nurſeries of pietie, and policie, into Blockhouſes, Bulwarkes, and Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadels, repleniſhed with militarie men, and inſtruments of war; the preſent adverſary being not to be repelled with ſcientificall demonſtrations, or probable arguments out of Topicks, but with fire and ſword, ſhot and powder, from the throats of the roaring Ordnance.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Beſieged by the <hi>Swedes.</hi>
                  </note>Now the confuſion which attends upon warre, began to appeare attired in her proper dreſſe; houſes flaming and ſet on fire, not by the enemie, but their proper ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that they might be no ſhelter for the adverſaries. Churches, Altars, and the dwelling places of the Muſes battered by the Canon, endangered by the fire Morterers, and Granadoes; the Ports boared on the one ſide with ſhot from the Campe; and ſtuffed againe with wood and dung by the defendants, to keepe their owne people from going forth, and excluding their foes; Sallies made out deſperately, Mines wrought with difficultie, and where force avayled not, for the aſſaylants; threats and fiery menacing Letters ſent to the defendants, and by them anſwered as ſpightfully. It is almoſt beyond be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, that in ſo ſmall a ſpace, as this Siege endured, which was but from the twelfth of <hi>Ianuary</hi> till the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth of <hi>February,</hi> ſuch, and ſo many things ſhould be done. But thus I finde them ſet downe in a Journall by one which was engaged in the action, and therefore to be credited.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ianuary</hi> 13. <hi>Old ſtile,</hi> from about eight in the morning till nine at night, the <hi>Swedes</hi> played upon the Citie, with their Canon, fire-workes, and Granadoes; and the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon upon the Campe, with their great Ordnance, duble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haukes, and Muskets, yet without much detriment to ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, the Commander within, having well provided to prevent the miſchiefe, which might be done by the Granadoes, and the <hi>Swedes</hi> without, being ſo ſtrongly earthed, that they could not eaſily receiue damage.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:7470:25"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Holdeth out for the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onie.</hi>
                  </note>They who ſtayed in their trenches, were ſecure, but ſome few others which ranged abroad, to pleaſe their genius, became the ſpoyle of the Garriſon, which ſally<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out in the Evening, found eight men of the Armie in an houſe without the <hi>Rhaniſh gate,</hi> which had former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beene a Taverne, and put them all to the ſword. Thus that day was ſpent in thunder, which was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine ſo violent, till about ſeaven dayes following, the Souldiers on both ſides in the meane time, being employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed rather to ſtrengthen their defences, than otherwiſe. The Commander within, firſt gaue order, that from that day, till the Siege was done, no clock ſhould ſtrike, no bell be tolld, thereby teaching the people, that the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the time was ſuch, as required all their hands, men, women, and children, and would not giue leaue to liſten after what's a clock? And the next day having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Letters from the Elector, to doe his endeavour for preſervation of the place faithfully, and to perſwade the Inhabitants to conſtancy, imployed as many as were ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable in raiſing of Palliſadoes, ſtuffing of packs with wooll, and bringing them into the ſeverall ſtreets neare the wall, to be in a readineſſe, to fill up ſuch breaches as might be made in the wall; and the Generall without, imployed his Souldiers, in rayſing of batteries, digging of Mines about the Grimmer-gate, and other fortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not omitting ſometimes to ſend a Salute by ſhot to the Citie, and ſeldome fayling of an anſwer: yet the adventure of ſome of the Garriſon, <hi>Ian.</hi> 18/28. is worth a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, for ſeeing the <hi>Swedes</hi> intended to make uſe of a Glaſſe-makers houſe for a battery, they ſallyed forth, and after a ſharpe Skirmiſh, which endured the ſpace of an houre, burned the houſe to the ground, and returned to the Citie; and the day following, perceiving the <hi>Swedes</hi> to begin to plant many Canon-baskets, upon the foundation of the ſame houſe, which was of ſtone, and ſo eſcaped the fire; cut off the Damme betwixt the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:7470:25"/>
                  <hi>Pleiſſenburg,</hi> and the Towne Moat, without Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> gate, and by that meanes drowned the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation under water, and prevented the deſigne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The defence made by the Garriſon, and the offence done by the <hi>Swedes.</hi>
                  </note>But the 20/30. of that moneth, and from thence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to the time of the <hi>Swedes</hi> riſing, were each remarkeable dayes. A great peece of Ordnance cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Lazie maid,</hi> and three Morterers placed on the Grimmer gate by the Garriſon, were then im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed againſt the Campe, without any more inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, than was neceſſary to coole them, and make them ſerviceable againe. Sallies were made daily by the praeſidiarie Souldiers, and to keepe the <hi>Swedes</hi> from the Caſtle, fired the Suburbs without St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> gate, and the Water-arch, as farre as to the Sand-ſtreete, thinking it better to demoliſh thoſe ragged buildings, which in time of peace had beene of ſome uſe, for the meaner ſort of people, no orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Citie, than to haue them imployed by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> for execution of their hoſtile purpoſes. The <hi>Swedes,</hi> againe imployed all their diligence to bring the Citie to obedience, battered and boared the Grimmer-gate with three Demi-Canons, and other great Pieces, ſlung maſſie ſtones into the Citie, by helpe of the Morterers, threw in fire bals and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadoes, and <hi>Ian.</hi> 22. <hi>Old ſtile,</hi> ſent a Drumme againe to require the Governour to ſurrender, threatning that if it was taken by aſſault, no perſon of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or ſex ſo ever, ſhould finde mercy; and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a ſcornefull anſwer by the Commander, who had received new Letters from the Electour, with a promiſe of the Imperiall ſuccours, very ſpeedily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke themſelues againe to their tackling, blew up a Mine neere the Grimmer-gate, and having dreſſed themſelues with plaited ſtrawe about their hats and armes, the ſame cogniſance by which they were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Saxons</hi> in their day neere <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocke,</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:7470:26"/>(thinking thereby to diſhearten the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants) ſtood in battellaray, as if they intended a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent aſſault.</p>
               <p>A threatning countenance may daunt a Coward, and the repreſenting of thoſe Inſtruments to a dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous ſpirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which haue beene formidable unto him formerly, may ſtrike him into an amazement, though there be no cauſe for it: They were but the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian</hi> ſlaues, which having beate their Maſters with Martiall weapons, yeelded upon ſight of the whip, the Commander was of another mould, and anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them in their owne tearmes, from the mouthes of the tall and <hi>Lazie Maids,</hi> two great Gunnes, and ſmaller Pieces, and that ſo inraged the <hi>Swedes</hi> (who by this were ſupplyed with ſome thouſands of freſh men, from the Campe neere <hi>Torgaw,</hi> and twelue new Pieces from <hi>Ertford</hi>) that to worke they fall againe, as not meaning to parlee any more, and followed the deſigne ſo hard till the beginning of <hi>Februarie,</hi> that (although they could not conquer the Citie, they did much deface, and ruine it, the wind-mill ſtreete being burned to the earth, ſome Churches, eſpecially that of Saint <hi>Nicholas,</hi> and that of St. <hi>Paul</hi> (the firſt having his roofe broke downe, and the other the Steeple battered with the Canon, and falling upon the roofe, utterly demoliſhing it, to the greaterrour of the people, who were more rerrified by another ſhot from a Demi-canon, which ſmote the Altar, the Organs, and carried away one moytie of the Apoſtles Statues) and the Colledges being much ruined by the violence of thoſe ſtormes, attended with artificiall thunder.</p>
               <p>A ſmart reſiſtance was made by the defendants, which ſometimes viſited the <hi>Swedes</hi> in their trenches, yet that had ocene truitleſſe, had not the ſuccours come in maturely; but thei eſtate being growne
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:7470:26"/>almoſt deſperate, newes was brought to them, and the Campe, of the comming of the Imperiall Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie. The Campe was leſſe diſheartened by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, than the Citie incouraged, and to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, that they played not in jeſt, but earneſt, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to attempt ſome-thing againe, before the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Hoaſt could march unto them.</p>
               <p>To this end, <hi>February</hi> the ſixt <hi>Old ſtile</hi> being Saint <hi>Dorotheas</hi> day, they played afreſh upon the Citie, with foure Demi-canons, eight great field Pieces, and ſome leſſer Gunnes, and in the ſpace of fiue houres, by force of the Ordnance, which had vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted three hundred thirtie and fiue times upon the wall, and vertue of their Mines, made two breaches, one upon the Eaſt, another upon the Weſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſide of the Grimmer-gate, (like <hi>Sampſon</hi> in the ſacred Storie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> doing the <hi>Saxons</hi> more miſchiefe at the laſt concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than in the whole time of their continuance there) and ſtood in Battalia againe, as if they meant to aſſault it.</p>
               <p>The Commander, a man never enough to be pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for his undaunted courage, <hi>(vertue where ever it is found is amiable)</hi> drew out foure Companies of ſelected foote, armed them with ſhort Pikes, two-handed-ſwords, Morning ſtarres, (a deadly wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon where it falls) and Muſquets, and marched him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the head of them to the breach, to encounter the <hi>Swedes,</hi> if they adventured to enter by thoſe breaches forcibly; It was done carefully, but need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly; an expreſſe was brought to the Campe, that the untied Forces under <hi>Hatzfield,</hi> and <hi>Goetz,</hi> were within a dayes march, and the <hi>Swedes</hi> thought it fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to retire with their unbroken Forces ſafely, than to expoſe them to a double hazard,<note place="margin">The Siege rayſed.</note> and goe on de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately: and <hi>February</hi> the ſixt, <hi>Old ſtile,</hi> betwixt ſeaven and eight at night, while the Morterers caſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:7470:27"/>great ſtones and Granadoes into the Citie, and the Garriſon was buſie to prevent the miſchiefe which might enſue thereby, the Canons were drawne from the batteries, the Armie began to march and the <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh</hi> Generall tooke up his head Quarter at <hi>Stote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the ſpace of almoſt ſix weekes, ſince the firſt ſummons, <hi>Ian.</hi> the firſt, <hi>New ſtile,</hi> the Citie was thus troubled with an uncouth Feaver, neither alwayes intermittent, nor continuall; but the ſeaventh of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruarie</hi> the malice of the diſeaſe appeared to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated, though ſome grudgings thereof, like the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-drops of a violent ſhower, were ſtill remaining. The Arriere of the <hi>Swedes,</hi> that day ſet the Superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendents Gaden-houſe on fire; and the day enſuing, the Villages neighbouring unto it, inferious mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring members to that more worthy body, were ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulcan;</hi> fifteene ſeverall Hamlets were ſeene from <hi>Leipſich,</hi> flaming at once, and at <hi>Grolz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchoker,</hi> a Dorpe exceeding any of the other in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the fire appeared biggeſt.</p>
               <p>The ninth day brought with it an happie <hi>criſis,</hi> the fag end of the <hi>Swedes,</hi> was not to be diſcovered, the Auantguard of the Imperiall ſuccours appeared to the view of the almoſt diſtracted Citizens; the clocks were permitted againe to giue notice of the houre, the Bells were rung to congregate the people to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſervice; and the tenth day, the Rhaniſh gate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing opened, the Countrey people and Souldiers brought in greatſtore of wood, ſtraw, and hay, into the Citie: in fine, upon the twelth day was a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne aſſembly,<note place="margin">Thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving for the Cities deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance.</note> and the people were ſummoned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, in all the Pariſhes, to render thankes to him, who had watched over the Citie, for its preſervation and deliverance, and to joyne in prayers, for a firme, honourable, and generall peace.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:7470:27"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hazardous adventures are not ſurpaſſed vithout dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie; yet induſtrie and diligence perfecteth any Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culian enterprize.</hi> Famine, and extreame danger at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the <hi>Imperialls</hi> march, yet but a Citie in <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringen,</hi> famouſed of old for excellent wine, the name being thence derived, as <hi>Stigelius</hi> probably conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Quippe vocat Iaijn, ſolymae pius Incola terrae</l>
                  <l>Hoc, quod nos Latio dicimus ore merum.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Armie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>united, and re-enforced march to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</hi>
                  </note>And of late for their Theriacall Antidote, relieved the firſt; and their valour overcame the later; 200000. pound of bread, was extorted by the Imperiall Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, from the Citie, and the Armie thus refreſhed, intended to march, with all poſſible ſpeed, toward <hi>Leipſich,</hi> but was hindred in the ſpeed by the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Major <hi>Stalhauſe,</hi> who having paſſed the River before them, cut off the bridges behind him,<note place="margin">A Conflict betwixt <hi>Stal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſe,</hi> and tho <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> at <hi>Saba,</hi> wherein foure Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all regiments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were ruina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> guarded the advemies with his Canon, and in three ſeverall skirmiſhes with <hi>Hatzfieldt,</hi> wholed the Avantguard, conſiſting of ten Regiments, ruinated foure of them, without much loſſe of his owne partie; and then ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Goetz</hi> was come with the reſt of the hoaſt, in an orderly Retreat, marched up to <hi>Bannier,</hi> and the maine of the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Armie.</p>
               <p>The Forces on both ſides, like ſo many lines drawne from ſeverall points of the Circumference, began to tend to one Center; and as if both parties had ſet up their reſt, and were concluded to venture all at once, ſummoned their aſſociates from their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall ſtations, to the generall Randevouz in <hi>Miſnia.</hi> The Crabats under <hi>Iſolani,</hi> and <hi>Budiani,</hi> were called out of the Dukedome of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> to aſſiſt <hi>Hatz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fielde</hi> in his deſigne againſt the <hi>Swedes</hi> in <hi>Saxonie;</hi> and were by the end of <hi>Februarie</hi> advanced as farre
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:7470:28"/>as <hi>Heſſen Caſſell,</hi> where they not onely preſſed the Lantgraues Subjects which lived in undefenced pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,<note place="margin">The Crabats under <hi>Iſolani</hi> oppreſſe the <hi>Heſſians.</hi>
                  </note> and oppreſſed them with mightie exactions for reliefe, but required Contributions of the great Citie it ſelfe, as deeming it to be under their Command, and threatned <hi>Ertford</hi> in <hi>Thuringen</hi> with a Siege and hoſtile Armes, preſuming that they were able to maſter it, with as much eaſe, as <hi>Bannier</hi> had lately done. But the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Colonell <hi>Goltz,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Citie, prepared to entertaine them; and fortified the place, as much as might be; not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting the hill <hi>Daver,</hi> (the place of advantage, where the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Generall planted his Ordnance, when he had ſurrounded it) amongſt his preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for defence; knowing that the prepoſſeſſing of that hill, was almoſt ſufficient alone, to ſecure the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie from the Crabats violence. This his labour ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his care, to maintaine the place committed to his charge; <hi>no man can conclude certainly of contingent futures;</hi> nor could he, but upon probabilities, haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny aſſurance of what ſucceſſe, theſe bands of Crabats, might haue in <hi>Heſſen-land;</hi> or what forces they might bring againſt him. Otherwiſe, that labour might haue beene ſpared, thoſe forces being diſperſed, the ſtings of thoſe Serpents being taken away, before they could reach the <hi>Thuringer</hi> foreſt, by the Lantgraue <hi>William,</hi> who had formed a new Army of his owne, conſiſting of ten Regiments, and was then aſſiſted with ſeaven <hi>Swediſh</hi> Regiments ſent unto him from the Campe by <hi>Bannier,</hi> under the Command of Colonell <hi>King,</hi> to that purpoſe. This true profeſſor of the Evangelicall faith, thought it unbeſeeming his dignitie, to recede a jot from the promiſe of alliance, which he had made and confirmed by oath, to the Crowne of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and being at that time courted by the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh their partie, coyned ſome new Rix-dollars, with theſe German words upon them;</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:7470:28"/>
               <q>
                  <l>Es iſt beſſer land, vnd leut verlobren,</l>
                  <l>Den, eyu. en falchen eydt geſhworen:</l>
               </q>
               <p>Which may be Enliſhed thus,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>It's better Life and Land forſake,</l>
                  <l>Then to a-null one Oath I make.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Not ſo much, to nippe the <hi>Saxon</hi> for his perfidiouſneſſe, as ſome have judged it, as to teſtifie his owne integritie, and loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and ayded by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> March 1/11. viſited <hi>Budia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi> in his Quarter at <hi>Skenkanfeldt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Budiani</hi> rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, &amp; his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments routed by the Land<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave <hi>William.</hi>
                  </note> where after a ſharpe conflict, in which the <hi>Crabat</hi> ſaw 300 of his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers put to the Sword, himſelfe was forced to ſlight, and that too, ſo full of horrour and confuſion, that to ſave his life, he was faine to caſt away his Coat, Saddle, Sable, &amp; to leave his Horſe &amp; gaje<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie, for feare of being diſcovered and expoſed to danger perſonally, ſheltring himſelfe in the Woods to preſerve him from the rage of the Victor who by this action gained 300 Horſe and their furniture, carried with him to <hi>Caſſel</hi> 26 Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, all or moſt of them men of note, and eminent Commanders in the Army, cleared his Countrey of thoſe Caterpillers and marched up towards the <hi>Weſer</hi> and <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> where hee doubted not to inlarge his Victory, there being then no <hi>Imperiall</hi> Army to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe him. <hi>Iſolani</hi> in the interim, taking his way tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row <hi>Voidlandt,</hi> to attaine to the <hi>Caeſareans</hi> Campe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whoſe protection, hee promiſed himſelfe more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, as being joyned with Confederates, and no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger building upon his owne power.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wrangell,</hi> who at that time was marched 10 leagues up into <hi>Sileſiae,</hi> to invade that Province, and make head againſt the Forces under <hi>Maerazini,</hi> and the Count of <hi>Mansfeldt,</hi> both which, with a new leavied Army there were putting forward towards <hi>Pegaw,</hi> where <hi>Hatzfield,</hi> and <hi>Goetz</hi> expected their comming, recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:7470:29"/>inſtructions from <hi>Banniere</hi> to doe his beſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, to cut them off in their march, or otherwiſe to haſten thence to the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Campe, and joyne with him againſt the whole <hi>Caeſarean</hi> united power. It was more then probable at the firſt, that the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Field-Marſhall might have encountred them (at leaſt) upon equall tearmes, 10000 brave old Souldiers atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him when he firſt paſſed the <hi>Oder</hi> at <hi>Franck-fordt.</hi> 1100. <hi>Polacks,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1100 <hi>Pollacks</hi> mutinying for pay, take ſervice under <hi>Wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell.</hi>
                  </note> which had mutinied for want of pay, and vowed to pillage <hi>Mòravia,</hi> (a rich Countrey an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the Crowne of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and abounding with Corne, being generally ſo full of Tillage, that there was ſcarce any place of Paſture, and hitherto, untou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched in theſe preſent warres) to make up their ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, ſeeing the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> threatned to pay them with Swords, and bullets, revolted, and tooke ſervice under him; The <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> Army was but on rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, Colonell <hi>Truchſes</hi> who had promiſed the decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Emperour to ſupply him with many thouſands of able men out of that Province, fayled of performance, and laying ſtrange impoſitions upon the people grew odious; only <hi>Gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gawe,</hi> and ſome other few places were left to withſtand him; and who would not hence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a doubtleſſe happie iſſue? <hi>The change of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels often turneth the preſent ſtate of things; to ſee a ſuppoſed Favorite brought to diſgrace, infatuates the Common people, with a dotage of new affection to their Commanders. Truchſes</hi> was arreſted as an abuſer of the <hi>Caeſarean</hi> grace and mercy, ſent a Priſoner to <hi>Vien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na; Mansfeildt</hi> authoriſed to ſupply his charge,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Truchſes</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d and ſent to <hi>Vienna.</hi>
                  </note> and he complying with the peoples humour, ſoone raiſed a ſufficient ſtrength to deale with <hi>Wrangell,</hi> who grown weaker by this time then hee was at his firſt going to the Field, having left 4000 of his men in ſeverall Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, and ſcarce confident of the <hi>Poliſh Coſſacks,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:7470:29"/>(diſcrees Commanders will hardly give credit to a revol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Fee. He which alloweth the act will not eaſily truſt the actor)</hi> retreated thence towards <hi>Miſnia</hi> to joyne with his aſſociate and fellow in Armes <hi>Banniere,</hi> and with their united forces, to give battell to the Army of the <hi>Caeſareans.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Death of <hi>BODISLAUS,</hi> D. of <hi>Pomerania.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>SOme remora's there were which hindered his expedition; one an act of humanity, or rather pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, the other an effect of neceſſity; and though the firſt might ſeeme a Nullity, to the over-cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious inquiſitors into each mans comportment, yet the laſt is beyond all exception, and requires no apology for it, nor admits argument againſt it. What Plow-jog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger will not forbeare one day in Harveſt to bury his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Father; though the Corne be ripe and ready to ſhake? what Merchant will not ſtay a little to give his friends the <hi>Foy,</hi> though the wind fill his ſayles, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viteth forth to ſea? An occaſion of more conſequence in <hi>Ethicks</hi> then a common farewell, and of more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance in humanity then the interrement of a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate-man, though a parent, policy attending and play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the handmaid to his piety, ſtayed him. The gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Bough of <hi>Pomerania,</hi> was then cropped, and
<q>
                     <l>— iſthoc avulſo deficit alter</l>
                     <l>Aureus et ſimili non frondet virga metallo.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bodiſlaus</hi> the 14 aged 57 yeares, who had ſate at the Helme of <hi>Pomerania</hi> by the ſpace of 17 yeares perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:7470:30"/>whoſe aunceſtors had governed that Province for 700 yeares, March <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deceaſed childleſſe, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out iſſue; to the great grieſe of his ſubjects and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates, who were the more ſenſible of his loſſe by their knowne aſſurance of his integrity: and this Prince his Funerals together with a provident care, for preſervation of the Dukedome, were one cauſe of ſuch a ſtay there, as might ſhew his affection to the memory of that good Prince, but not indanger his confederates.</p>
               <p>But this was not all, his way was intercepted, and there was no paſſage through the <hi>Imperiall</hi> Army to his freinds, unleſſe the way was cut out with the ſword; The <hi>Caeſarcans</hi> had blocked up his way, and unleſſe he would fight deſperately, and upon extreame diſadvantage, it was vaine as yet to attempt it. The adverſe armies lay then encamped within one <hi>German</hi> league each of other, both ſeverally ſeeking to gaine, neither willing to give occaſion to the other. The <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſareans,</hi> &amp; <hi>Saxons</hi> ſurmounted the <hi>Swedes</hi> in number, the <hi>Swedes</hi> had the odds of them in ammunition for warre, and proviſions of viands. <hi>Banniere</hi> thinking to conſume his adverſaries by famine, lay ſtill in his faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe without ſtriving, and the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> ſuppoſing at the length to catch him upon the hanck, obſerved the ſame order; nothing was done for many dayes to the prejudice of the other: the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> at the end impatient of idleneſſe, and releeved with Ordnance from <hi>Dreſden,</hi> and victuals out of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> gave the firſt onſet upon the regiment under Colonell <hi>Poye,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Swediſh</hi> regiment un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Colone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l <hi>Poye</hi> colected.</note> conſiſting of 400. horſe, and rooted it, then fleſhed with this petit victory, fell foule upon the Earle of <hi>Hoditz,</hi> and came thence conquerours; and growen more confident by that ſucceſſe, devided their army into two parts, whereof one was to paſſe the river of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:7470:30"/>
                  <hi>Mulda</hi> neere <hi>Dreſden,</hi> and the other to abide in their former ſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The <hi>Swede</hi> whoſe watchful eye attended upon this diviſion, prepared ſome ſelected Troopes to watch the <hi>Caeſareans</hi> as they croſſed the water,<note place="margin">The V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard of ſome Imperiall troops defeated upon the <hi>Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da.</hi>
                  </note> and they ſo faithfully performed their truſt, that with a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den volly of ſhot diſcharged upon the enemies as they were paſſing over, they were ſo amazed, that in a ſtrange confuſion, they crouded ſo thicke upon the Bridge of Boates, which was made for their tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, that the Bridge ſunke, and broke under their weight, many men and horſes were drowned in the water, the Standards of thoſe which were paſſed the River became a ſpoyle to the undertakers, and the reſt of the Army was forced in a confuſed retreat to haſten backward to the Campe, which reſided about <hi>Stralen, Riſſa,</hi> and <hi>Oſhatz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Two <hi>Caeſarean</hi> Regiments ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed neere great <hi>Hahin.</hi>
                  </note>Two <hi>Caeſarean</hi> Regiments, were quartered at the ſame time neere great <hi>Hahin,</hi> under the Commands of the Colonels <hi>Shierſtets,</hi> and <hi>Barkerſdorff,</hi> and under a pretence to ſurprize them as it was after given out, <hi>Banniere</hi> who was ſtrongly entrenched about <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaw,</hi> and had an Army of 12000 Horſe, and 8 Brigads of Foote, ſent 8 Regiments, which fired the Suburbes of that ſmall City, rayſed the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> from theyr lodging, routed them by a ſhort but ſmart charge, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued them to the very gates of <hi>Dreſden,</hi> and poſſeſſed themſelves of their baggage; the <hi>Caeſareans</hi> prizing their lives above that pelfe, willingly leaving that Boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to the victors, to ſecure their perſons by an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious flight. But the deſigne tended to a further ſcope: <hi>Marazines</hi> Forces lay in <hi>Luſatia</hi> to keepe the paſſages againſt <hi>Wrangell,</hi> who (as they ſuppoſed) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to march that way to his confederates in his Colleagues Army, and to guard him. Thoſe Forces were commanded abroad by the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Generall,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:7470:31"/>whoſe intent being ſuſpected by <hi>Hatzfield,</hi> the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant Major Generall <hi>Bretta</hi> March 10/30. Was ſent out with 5000 Horſe to oppoſe them.</p>
               <p>Hitherto <hi>Bannier's</hi> Forces are upon the winning at leaſt not on the looſing hand, the <hi>Caeſarcans</hi> ſaved a great ſtake at <hi>Leipſick,</hi> but drew very few, and thoſe of ſmall value; but his Confederates were ſometimes looſers, failing of their owne intendments, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vanquiſhed, or overtaken by the adverſarie. Nothing is ſure under the Sunne, the Moone hath a blemiſh in the middle of her glorious Orbe, the Rivers which ſometimes enlarge themſelves into Lakes, and ſeeming Oceans of freſh waters are againe contracted into narrow Channels, yet the <hi>Macula</hi> of the Moone, makes the glory of her illuminated body more illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, the ſtraightning of the current makes it more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and the loſſe which his Allyes and Friends recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved did not derogate from their glory, nor brought any prejudice (certainely) to their enterprizes. The <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> Honour and Empire was not loſt, though adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured deſperately, upon the valour of three noble Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren againſt a like number of Enemies, when two of their Champions were ſlaine, the third by a politike ſtratagem, and his manhood performing alone what they had all undertaken joyntly; and ſo purchaſing a name to his family, and victory to his Nation; it may be paralleld by this moderne ſtory.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hermanſtein</hi> a Fort of conſequence upon the <hi>Rhine</hi> neere <hi>Coblentz,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Fort of <hi>Hermanſtein</hi> neceſſitated.</note> which yet held out for the King of <hi>France,</hi> was ſtraightly beleaguered by <hi>Iohn de Werth</hi> and reduced to extreame neceſſity; it was not to bee undermiend being ſeated on a Hill, nor to bee forced otherwiſe then by Famine; the place being ſo fortified by Nature and Art, that it was, and is not undeſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed impregnable; the Imperiall Commander
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:7470:31"/>lay before it, and hindered all ſupplyes of reliefe.<note place="margin">The <hi>Landt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grave</hi> attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to releeve it, but is defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted twice.</note> The <hi>Lantgrave</hi> twice adventured to ſupply it ith neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and was twice beaten backe by the aſſeegers with much loſſe. The neighbouring Boores, thought to ſteale thither with Hennes, and ſuch like viands through the hedges and backe wayes, but were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by the way, and hanged for their labour. The Cittadell was ſo much diſtreſſed, that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander (a man of ſingular wiſdome and fortitude) was compelled to divide his proviſions amongſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by weight, and the Baron of <hi>Werth</hi> knowing their neceſſity, and how improbable it was that they ſhould be releeved by and land auxiliaries (his army having ſtopped that way) or by ſuccours from the <hi>Rhine</hi> all the Forts upon the Streame, being under the <hi>Auſtrians</hi> power) concluded, that the Fort muſt yeeld, and had in a manner aſſured himſelfe, to take it in upon what tearmes he himſelfe ſhould be pleaſed to preſcribe to the beſieged: But the River yeelded a paſſage, though the earth denyed one, for conveyance of victuals, and other neceſſaries unto the Caſtle. The Story is thus related, by the <hi>Dutch</hi> from <hi>Hamburg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A <hi>Spaniſh Don</hi> being ſent Embaſſadour from his <hi>Catholicke</hi> Majeſtie to the King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> then at <hi>Weene,</hi> to condole with him for the deceaſed Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and congratulate his accumulated dignities;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ramſey</hi> relee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it by a ſtratagem.</note> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving diſpatched his legation; was ready for his jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney towards <hi>Bruxcls</hi> to viſite the Cardinall <hi>Infant,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to goe by ſhipping from <hi>Mentz</hi> to <hi>Colin,</hi> and thence to <hi>Brabandt.</hi> The deſolation of the upper Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate and a great part of <hi>Franconia,</hi> through which he was to paſſe from the <hi>Danubie</hi> to the <hi>Rhine,</hi> moved him to ſend ſome of his Servants five or ſixe dayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to prepare his lodgings, and neceſſaries for him, ſelfe, and the reſt of his retinew. This was revealed to
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:7470:32"/>
                  <hi>Ramſey</hi> Governour of <hi>Hanaw,</hi> who aſwell to preſerve that City from the Siege, which <hi>Iohn de Werth</hi> threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned it, as ſoone as <hi>Hermenſtein</hi> ſhould bee ſurrendred, as alſo for to ſhew his good affection to his Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, had long beene plotting to releeve them: and now conceited, that if he could but ſurprize the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Harbengers the buſineſſe was halfe done, ſent out ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parties to watch the high wayes, with inſtructions that if they chanced to meet with thoſe <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturers, they ſhould doe them no other violence, then to bring them into the City. His order was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and it fell out in all things according to his wiſh, the Soldiers met with the Gentlemen, brought them to <hi>Hanaw,</hi> and preſented them to the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, who entertained them with all gentleneſſe, and by kindneſſe ſcrewed out of them, the time and day of the <hi>Embaſſadors</hi> comming to the <hi>Rhine,</hi> the number of veſſels deſigned to attend him, their deſcription by their colours, the number of his owne attendants which wayted upon him, their habits, and the habit, and favour of the <hi>Embaſſador</hi> himſelfe: And beeing thus acquainted with each particular circumſtance, trimmed up two ſhips of the like burthen, and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſelected ſome choſen men out of the Garriſon, to perſonate the <hi>Spaniſh Embaſſadours</hi> followers, and one well verſed in his <hi>Sibboleth</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> tongue and garbe to repreſent his perſon, all which being attired in the <hi>Spaniſh dreſſe,</hi> with their haire cut cloſe (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the <hi>Catholick</hi> Kings late edict, of which they ſeemed ſtrict obſervers) and in long mourning clokes were brought to the Veſsels, loaden with neceſsaries for the releefe of the Caſtle, and appearing upon the Decks, ſayled downe the <hi>Rhine</hi> in the face of the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall</hi> Garriſons, who taking, and miſtaking them for <hi>Spaniards,</hi> not onely ſuffered them to Sayle quietly,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:7470:32"/>but ſaluted them friendly with many Muſquetadoes and Canonadoes from the Garriſons; the new <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phitruo,</hi> not ſparing to complement with them in a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> poſture from ſhipboord, till having reached to <hi>Hermenſtein,</hi> the ſubtle <hi>Soſia's</hi> turned in thither, to the vexation of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> allyes, who were ready to bite their fingers, to ſee themſelves thus deluded.</p>
               <p>It was a neate ſtratagem well carryed, and of great conſequence. <hi>Hanaw</hi> which alone of all the Cities in the <hi>Weteraw,</hi> yet held out, had bin much indangered otherwiſe. The <hi>Caeſareans</hi> began to appeare ſtrong a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the Empire, and had done much damage to the <hi>Swedes</hi> and their allyes in the Biſhopricke of <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> the Marke of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and about the <hi>Weſer,</hi> and had certainly reſolved to plunder the <hi>Weteraw,</hi> if the deſigne at <hi>Hermenſtein</hi> had ſucceeded fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lemford</hi> in <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> a Fort of a pretty ſtrength out great conſequence,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lemford</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts.</note> as being one of the inlets of the Territorie about it, was kept and poſſeſſed by a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of <hi>Swediſh</hi> Dragoons, which did much ſpoyle in the Biſhopricke of <hi>Munſter,</hi> and were therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of by the Country people, to the Baron of <hi>Lut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſheim</hi> who commanded in <hi>Dieps-hold,</hi> and he with a Regiment of men ſate downe before it, and forced the <hi>Swedes</hi> in the Caſtle to yeeld upon diſcretion, and to take Service under him. The Praeſidiaries in <hi>Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> and <hi>Oſnabrugge</hi> made out ſixe troopes of Horſe, and 4. Companies of Dragoons, to bee revenged for this loſſe, thinking to have taken <hi>Dieps-hold</hi> by O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlat, and ſurprized the Baron and his Regiment which was lodged there. And to this purpoſe <hi>February</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4/4. marched thitherwards, covering their intention with the darkneſſe and ſilence of the night. But the Baron had received ſome intention of their purpoſe, and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:7470:33"/>having prepared for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">The <hi>Praeſidia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of <hi>Minde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> &amp; <hi>Oſnabrugge,</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>feated at <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eps hold.</hi>
                  </note> charged upon the avantgard, before they expected it, and had then ſurpriſed it, had not the whole band come in ſodainely to their reſcue. But thoſe old Souldiers practiſed in the handling and managing of their armes, needed no word of direction from the mouth of their Commander, the preſent ſtate of their freinds aſſaulted by the enemy, taught them both the what, and the how, in their action. The bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell grew hot, and the <hi>Swedes</hi> being compelled by dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſticke cloſe together, and not to ſever for feare of ambuſcadoes ſought manfully, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 2. of the clock til 5. in the morning, &amp; then perceiving that <hi>Lutterſhem</hi> ſurmounted them in ſtrength, and advantage, betook themſelves to plaine fight, and were purſued to <hi>Oſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brugge,</hi> but without great loſſe, their horſes being good and ſpeedy, and their flight well ordered, and not in confuſion. But this loſſe was ſoone after regained, both in point of honour and benefit by the ſame <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh</hi> garriſons; <hi>Feb:</hi> 10/2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> when they ſurpriſed ſuddainly 4. companies of <hi>Imperiall-ſouldiers,</hi> which lay in the the ſmall City of <hi>Hagell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Surpriſe <hi>Hagell</hi> and put 4 com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of <hi>Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> to the ſword.</note> put them to the ſword, and returned home with 150 horſe, and other good boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and baggage of which they had ſpoyled the <hi>Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe were the checks which were given to the <hi>Swedes</hi> aſſociates, in thoſe parts of the Empire, which the Generall valued the leſſe in reſpect of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage he had done to the <hi>Saxon,</hi> with whom, above any particular Prince of the Empire the Crowne of <hi>Sweden</hi> was moſt offended; which detriment is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed particularly by letters from <hi>Dreſden,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The miſerable con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n of the Dukedome of <hi>Saxony.</hi>
                  </note> March 18/2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wherein with words delivered with an acce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of griefa the whole Dukedome of <hi>Saxony</hi> is ſaid to be totally ruinated, except the Cities of <hi>Leipzick, Wittemberge,</hi> and <hi>Dreſden,</hi> the Churches lying deſolate, the woods
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:7470:33"/>being out downe, the earth untilled and lying waſte, and the villages, and leſſer Cities, made pillars of fire and ſmoake, not onely by the <hi>Swedes</hi> the enemies, but alſo by the ſeeming friends the <hi>Caeſarians,</hi> who ſpare not to burne thoſe places to the ground, where they finde not as much proviſion as they demaund for their armies, as the Duke <hi>Frederick</hi> of <hi>Saxon Alten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> complained to <hi>Hatzfieldt,</hi> deſiring him to order his rude ſouldiers by a better diſcipline, that ſuch acts of inhumanity might be prohibited, and the offenders puniſhed accordingly.</p>
               <p>Thus far we have followed <hi>Bannier,</hi> and <hi>Hatzfield,</hi> both yet abiding in their faſtneſſe, expecting their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous opportunity to ſight. And now wee muſt looke backe to the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and <hi>Wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell</hi> the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Field-marſhall, whom our laſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very left in that Marquiſate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Berlin</hi> the Electors ſeate of reſidence, <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the middle <hi>Mark, Tangermund,</hi> once the ſeate of <hi>Charles</hi> 4. Emperour, and moſt pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of note were brought by <hi>Wrangells</hi> army either to entertaine <hi>Swediſh</hi> garriſons, or contribute to the maintenance of his forces; onely the Forts of <hi>Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daw</hi> and <hi>Kuſtrin</hi> held out for the Elector,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Kuſtrin</hi> belea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guered by the <hi>Swedes.</hi>
                  </note> whom the <hi>Swedes</hi> courted with faire language ſometimes, and ſometimes ſummoned in the language of a ſouldier, to ſurrender thoſe places of ſtrength to him as a ſurety of his good affection and love to the crowne of <hi>Sweden,</hi> or as a token that he would ſtand as a neutrall, and not ſhew himſelfe an enemy. But both his courtſhippe and ſummons were frivolous; the El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> anſwered that thoſe places were Forts of the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap> that hee could not deliver them up to a ſtrange <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>owne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out prejudice to his honour and credit: and as for the <hi>Swedes</hi> menaces, that perhaps it might be in their
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:7470:34"/>power to deale with his territories in what manner they pleaſed, but they ſhould never be able to force him from his firſt reſolution. His anſwer not onely diſpleaſed, but inraged the <hi>Field-marſhall,</hi> who where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon immediately (being then Maſter of the Field) plundered the Countrie as far as <hi>Boeskah</hi> &amp; <hi>Cotbutz,</hi> a towne in the lower <hi>Luſatia,</hi> tooke away ſixe wagons loaden with baggage belonging to the Electour, as they were going to <hi>Kuſtrin,</hi> and ſent them to <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> upon the <hi>Oder;</hi> blocked up <hi>Kuſtrin,</hi> broke downe one of the bridges, and conveyed the <hi>Oder</hi> two Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh miles from the Fort, by a new artificiall channell; the garriſon all this time defending themſelves vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antly, and though fayling of victuals, not fainting in their courages.</p>
               <p>The Electour who was gone from <hi>Berlin</hi> to <hi>Peitz,</hi> to raiſe ſuch forces as might be able to make head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Swedes,</hi> ſent private inſtructions to <hi>Cracht</hi> the Commander in <hi>Kuſtrin</hi> to fortifie himſelfe as much as might be, promiſing faithfully to relieve him, as ſpeedily as might be. The Colonell carefull to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his charge ſpared not coſt; and ſeeing the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs about the Fort were rather ſerviceable for the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy then himſelfe, burned them downe, ſo making good uſe of this conſuming element of fire for his ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; while the other unmercifull deſtroyer water offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it ſelfe to his ſervice: the <hi>Oder</hi> ſwelling above the banks of the new channell, and breaking out violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, drowning ſome <hi>Swediſh</hi> Souldiers, and overflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the low land, in which the Fort is ſcituated; and this accident cauſed them to conſent with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander for a ceſſation of armes for certaine doves, the Commander againe promiſing to requite them with a competent ſumme of money, if they would give o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſeege. It was but a ſmall part of the <hi>Swedes</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:7470:34"/>which were ſate downe before the <hi>Cittadell,</hi> the maine body was then with the Field-marſhall at <hi>Franck ford,</hi> one part thereof was imployed to fetch in victuals, and money from the tributary townes to pay, and refreſh the Army: another to plunder that part of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey which had not ſubmitted, and granted to pay contribution. And theſe laſt, ranging as farre as to <hi>Peitz,</hi> lighted upon ſixe wagons loaden with proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the Electours houſhould; ſeyzed upon them, and preſented them to <hi>Wrangell,</hi> who being himſelfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ufficiently ſtored, and knowing the ſcarcity of the ſCountrey, &amp; deſirous rather to vanquiſh the Electour by curteſie, then violence, ſent them back by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours owne wagoners, and convoy, neither light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the carriages, nor offering any injury to their perſons. And now the winter beginning to be in his ſtrength,<note place="margin">The ſiege inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</note> having well refreſhed his Army at <hi>Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> after he had utterly demoliſhed the bridge, and ſent away all the Cities ammunition, and burnt downe all the bridges neere about the fortreſſe of <hi>Kuſtrin,</hi> ſave onely one, which he could not ſafely come to, it being within leſſe then a musket-ſhot of the Caſtle. He divided his whole Army, which was then 3000. horſe, and 7000. foote, and appointed them to their winter-quarters, the new <hi>Mark</hi> being appointed for the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallary,</hi> and the <hi>Veker</hi> and middle markes for the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantery,</hi> himſelfe in the meane time retiring to <hi>Stetin,</hi> to be preſent at the <hi>Dyet</hi> then held by the States of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merania.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Marquis</hi> Electour made good uſe of the <hi>Swedes</hi> abſence, the <hi>Count</hi> of <hi>Mansfield</hi> had ſupplied him with ſome forces out of <hi>Sileſia, Arnheim</hi> a Colonell of his owne, and kinſman to the late Generall, had rayſed up ſome others in <hi>Luſatia,</hi> and the <hi>Marquiſate;</hi> and armed with thoſe forces one of his Colonels, and the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:7470:35"/>
                  <hi>Swedes</hi> not expecting it, came firſt with his like Regiment (December 18/3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.) of 300 Horſe to <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> forced open the Southeaſt or Copenicker Gate, preſſed in with drawne Swords and Piſtols,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Berlyn</hi> regai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe Elector.</note> ſet a Watch upon the ſeverall Ports, (the Citizens beeing ready to receive their naturall Prince) and tooke Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners about 70 <hi>Swediſh</hi> Souldiers, which were Billi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the City, and ſome prime Officers.</p>
               <p>In the Evening about 5 of the clocke, the Elector himſelfe attended with 600 Dragoons and light Horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Branderburg</hi> taken from the <hi>Swedes.</hi>
                  </note> came into the City; the three Regiments of Horſe under the commands of young <hi>Buckerſdorf.</hi> Duke <hi>Francis Charles,</hi> and <hi>Shierſtett,</hi> beeing lodged that night in the Suburbs, whoſe apparition the next morning, made thoſe few <hi>Swedes</hi> which lodged at <hi>Bernaw,</hi> and were ſevered from their company, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire towards <hi>Newſtadt,</hi> for their more ſecurity. A pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitious ſtarre did then attend the <hi>Brandenburgher,</hi> his happy Fortune was not thus bounded, part of his Army was diſpatched for <hi>Brandenburgh,</hi> and the Froſt having then contracted the <hi>Elve</hi> into a more ſolid body of Ice, thoſe Soldiers tooke that City alſo by a ſudden <hi>Scalado</hi> and put the <hi>Garriſon</hi> to the Sword.</p>
               <p>Newes of the <hi>Brandenburgers</hi> Progreſſe, was brought to the <hi>Field-Marſhall</hi> at <hi>Stetin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Druſſen</hi> block'd up by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> &amp; the ſiege relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed.</note> who inſtantly gave order to the Commander of that City, to blocke up the Fort, and paſſage of <hi>Druſſen,</hi> which he did accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. At the expiration of 8. dayes a rumour was ſpread in that ſmall <hi>Swediſh</hi> Campe, that the <hi>Imperiall Generall Marazini,</hi> with 6000 men, was comming out of <hi>Sileſia</hi> to releeve that Garriſon; and then the Commander left that ſiege, and returned homeward, plundring the inhabitants houſes upon the way. The <hi>Field-Marſhall</hi> himſelfe began to muſter up his diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Regiments, which then lay about <hi>Shiffelbeane, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renſwald,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:7470:35"/>Solden,</hi> and <hi>Lantzberg,</hi> intending againe to put into the Field, though the Winter Seaſon did in a manner prohibite him. With theſe Forces hee firſt marched againſt <hi>Lantzberg,</hi> a frontier City of the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lantzberg</hi> ſurrendred to <hi>Wrangell.</hi>
                  </note> and forced that to yeeld upon compoſition, and thence unto the <hi>Vekermarck,</hi> where the Vangard of the Army encountred with Colonell <hi>Arncheim</hi> a Kinſman of the late Generall of the ſame name,<note place="margin">Colonell <hi>Arnheim</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed by the <hi>Swedes</hi> and ſent Priſoner to <hi>Stetin.</hi>
                  </note> whom after a ſhort conflict, they tooke Priſoner with 400 Dragoons, and ſent to <hi>Stetin,</hi> from whence againe, by the direction of the Lord <hi>Steno Biclke</hi> who in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and inſtead of the Rix-Chancellor is there reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for the direction of affaires, he was tranſported to <hi>Stockholme</hi> in <hi>Swedland,</hi> to be uſed according to the diſcretion of the States.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Druſſen</hi> was ſtill in the <hi>Field-Marſhals</hi> eye, as being a convenient place for the egreſſe and regreſſe of his Forces, and this againe he intended to beſiege, and had provided much amunition, and other proviſions, to effect it, intending to aſſault it by force, if he could not reduce it to a friendly compoſition; but then the ſaid <hi>Embaſſadour</hi> of the Crowne of <hi>Sweden</hi> interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; being ſent to treate of Peace betwixt the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and the Queene of <hi>Sweden</hi> his Necce, the Elector himſelfe giving a willing eare to a friendly treatie, having appointed the Marques <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> with a pleni-potentiary Commiſſion to conferre with the <hi>Swediſh Embaſſadour,</hi> at the little City of <hi>Shwed,</hi> diſtant 7 leagues Southwards from <hi>Stetin,</hi> and this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the <hi>Field-Marſhall</hi> from that ſiege.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Wrangell</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth into <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſia.</hi>
                  </note>There was now a kinde of ceſſation of Armes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Elector and <hi>Field-Marſhall,</hi> in thoſe Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories: and <hi>Wrangel</hi> having plundered the lands and goods belonging to the Count of <hi>Swartzenburg,</hi> and taken Priſoners the chiefeſt of his Officers, garriſoned
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:7470:36"/>the Towns in <hi>Pomerania</hi> and the Dukedome of <hi>Meck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenburg,</hi> marched into <hi>Sileſia,</hi> to oppoſe the <hi>Imperiall</hi> Forces which were raiſed there, and there he received inſtructions from <hi>Banniere,</hi> to come and joyne with his Army, or otherwiſe to hinder <hi>Mansfield</hi> from comming to <hi>Hatzfield,</hi> as it hath beene related for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly.</p>
               <p>It was ſtill a bloudy time in the Electorate of <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony,</hi> and a generall feare was conceived by the adjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Provinces, that the Fury of warre, would not be confined there: the hearts of the people, were terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by a ſtrange Prodigie, which though it admits no particular interpretation —
<q>— Deus omen in Hoſtes</q> 
                  <hi>Convertat;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A ſtrange Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digy at <hi>Iſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nach.</hi>
                  </note> was as terrible, as portentous. The Conduit at <hi>Iſenach</hi> ſcituated in the midſt of the Marketſted, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly inſtead of Water powred out Bloud, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued for the ſpace of two houres, before it yeelded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine that Element, for which that <hi>Aqueduct</hi> was ordained. A bloudy time enſued it, betwixt the <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall</hi> Generals, and <hi>Banniers</hi> Forces, though they kept their Faſtneſſe neere <hi>Targaw,</hi> yet few dayes paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed without blowes. The <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> prepared two Ship-bridges over the <hi>Elve</hi> for the tranſportation of their Forces, one at <hi>Dreſden,</hi> by the South-eaſt or <hi>Pirner-gate,</hi> the other at <hi>Stralen.</hi> To the laſt of theſe places,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stralen</hi> burnt by the <hi>Swedes.</hi>
                  </note> the <hi>Swedes</hi> advanced with ſixe full Regiments, burned downe the City and the Caſtle to the ground, planted their Horſemen on the other ſide of the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to hinder the Imperialiſts march over the Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; ſurpriſed one of the <hi>Caeſarean</hi> quarters neere <hi>Wurtzen,</hi> carryed away 300 Wagons laden with bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, and made havock of the Country Villages, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the <hi>Imperiall</hi> Safeguards, burning the Townes to the ground: the <hi>Caeſareans</hi> herein not being behinde
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:7470:36"/>the <hi>Swedes,</hi> Friends and Enemies (as it were) both conſpiring, ſo to ruine that Country, that <hi>March</hi> 11/21, 44 ſeverall fires within two Leagues compaſſe, might have at once beene diſcovered to the eye. The defeat at <hi>Wurtzen</hi> was given by the Colonell <hi>Slangh,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Imperiall Regiments de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated at <hi>Wurt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>zen</hi> by Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell <hi>Slangh.</hi>
                  </note> whom <hi>Banniere</hi> had ſent with 1500 Horſe, toward the City <hi>Leiſnick, Golditz</hi> and <hi>Eylenburg;</hi> the Colonell re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned <hi>March</hi> 23, <hi>Aprill</hi> 2, giving this accompt of his action: That at <hi>Wurtzen</hi> he had defeated two Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Regiments, carried away their Baggage, ſlaine 600 upon the place, taken many Priſoners, amongſt which were two Rit-maſters, five Lieutenants, and many other Officers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Banniere</hi> in the abſence of the Colonel, purpoſely to bring a generall terror upon the Imperiall Army, that by their diſtraction being aſſaulted in ſeverall places,<note place="margin">200. Imperial Horſe defeated by <hi>Baniev</hi> at <hi>Pegaw.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Slangh</hi> might be more ſecure, ranged about divers of their Quarters, and firſt at <hi>Pegaw,</hi> incountred with 2000 Imperiall horſe, whom he defeated, and routed utterly. That victory incited him to proceed further, and appearing in Battell-array before the Imperiall Campe, provoked them to Battell, but they unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to leave their holds, kept ſtill in their Trenches, which made him returne to his owne quarters. The <hi>Caeſarean</hi> Army lay then betwixt <hi>Torgaw,</hi> and <hi>Meiſen,</hi> on the Eaſt ſide of the River <hi>Elve,</hi> and the greater part of the <hi>Swediſh</hi> horſe and Dragoons, on the other ſide juſt againſt the <hi>Caeſarean</hi> Campe, which they kept waking with perpetuall Alarums. <hi>April</hi> 2. <hi>new ſtile,</hi> the <hi>Caeſarean</hi> Commanders had a deſigne to tranſport ſome Regiments of Horſe, from their head-quarter at <hi>Rieſa,</hi> to the Weſt ſide of the River, that there being no impediment which might ſtay their courſes, they might ſometimes breake in upon the <hi>Swedes,</hi> and gall them with ſodaine skirmiſhes. The <hi>Swedes</hi> who
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:7470:37"/>well underſtood their purpoſe,<note place="margin">3. Regiments of Imperiall Horſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed by the <hi>Swedes.</hi>
                  </note> ſuffered three Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to paſſe the River quietly, intending to requite trick for trick, but then having armed themſelves for the aſſault, charged them ſo furiouſly, that they were forced to retreat in ſuch a confuſion, that above 200. of them were drowned in the <hi>Elve,</hi> and ſo many ſlaine, that the Captives whom they took in the Battell con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that thoſe 3. Regiments were almoſt totally rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The next day following, <hi>Bannier</hi> reſolved to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite the <hi>Caeſarean</hi> Army in their quarters, and to that purpoſe ſelected two Companies out of every Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both of Horſe and Foot; and attended with thoſe expert Soldiers, and the Watch-maſters Regiment, he marched directly to the Imperiall head-watch, which conſiſted of 20. Companies of the beſt and ableſt horſe in the <hi>Caeſarean</hi> Campe, and were commanded by the Sergeant-Major <hi>Bretta.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Head-Watch of the Imperiall Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ght.</note> The conflict betwixt them was ſhort and ſharpe; the <hi>Swedes</hi> came on roundly and charged home upon the <hi>Caeſareans,</hi> which ſtanding together in a cloſe compacted body, endured that ſhocke, and prepared to entertaine the aſſailants again. But then <hi>Bannier</hi> doubled the number of them that gave the charge, and over burthening the <hi>Caeſareans,</hi> with the waight of that heavie body, compelled them to ſlight, in which, they being ſtayed by the inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of a ſmall River, many of them (the number is uncertaine) were cut off, and left dead upon the place, and many taken Priſoners.</p>
               <p>All theſe ſeverall Conflicts betwixt the two Armies, were not without the effuſion of much Chriſtian bloud, but the bloud ſo ſhed was not taken away by way of murther (Warre juſtly grounded, is continued lawfully; the Sword is oft a juſt decider of controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, and though it bee accompted one of the great Plagues, ſent by God, it is not attended with any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:7470:37"/>in the execution.) Black murthers and horrid treaſons hatched in darkneſſe, what ever the pretence thereof may be, are not onely unexcuſable, but deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble alſo to God and man.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Emperors Funerals.</note>The Court at <hi>Vienna,</hi> was about this time clothed in blacke, for the ſolemnization of the late Emperours Funerals, which were ſolemnely celebrated by the <hi>Nuntius Apoſtolicus,</hi> attended with 10. Prelates in their Miters. The Herſe was blacke, but inlayd with ſilver, and garniſhed with many burning white waxe Tapers; the Imperiall Eagles were blazoned about it, in the midſt, ſtood the Corpes; covered with a blacke cloth, intermingled with gold; over his head lay the Imperiall <hi>Hungarian</hi> and <hi>Bohemian</hi> Crownes. At his Feet the Golden-fleece, and betwixt then both, the <hi>Imperiall,</hi> Ball and Scepter; in the middeſt whereof was placed a Crucifixe of ſilver; At his ſides lay his Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier, Dagger, and Spurres. The Boots of the Herſe were adorned with the pictures of Vertues, and upon the top, on a Pyramis, ſtood a Globe, and a Crowne. The Church being hung with blacke, and the ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ended, his heart and bowels were lodged in three Cabinets, and convayed without any pompe, from <hi>Vienna</hi> to <hi>Gratz</hi> by his late Privie-Counſellours, and other Officers of the Court, which are ſince caſhie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; the young King his Sonne inſtantly reforming, and by the hand of the Earle of <hi>Medaw</hi> the <hi>Major domo</hi> upon his Fathers deceaſe; having reduced his Counſell to the number of 5. which were the Biſhop of <hi>Vienna,</hi> the Earle of <hi>Trautmanſdolff,</hi> who is now the <hi>Major Palatii,</hi> and the Earles of <hi>Slavata, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenberg,</hi> and <hi>Venda;</hi> the care of his Chanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ry, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing committed to Doctor <hi>Prickmajor,</hi> under the name and title of Vice-Chancellour.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:7470:38"/>
               <p>The difference betwixt thoſe two great Potentates the Chriſtian and Catholike Kings, drew ſeverall free Princes, and States to their parties, and cauſed ſuch a combuſtion in the City of <hi>Liege,</hi> that the City was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt the Biſhop, and the Biſhop againſt the Burgheſſes: He labouring to advance the <hi>Caeſarean</hi> and Spaniſh cauſe, and therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ing great impoſitions and taxes upon the Citizens, and they rather inclining to the <hi>French</hi> King, though at firſt ſubmitting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Biſhops orders, with a kinde of unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe, paying their contributions, yet in the end flatly oppoſed him: and in the beginning of the yeare, they ſent a complaining petition to the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> againſt him, the heads whereof were theſe. That as a childe, by inſtinct of Nature, in its ſufferings, will have recourſe to the Mother; ſo, they did now humbly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate themſelves at the feet of his Holineſſe, to deſire his aſſiſtance, and releefe in their preſent neceſſities: That their caſe was to be pityed,<note place="margin">The Citizens on <hi>Liege</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ine to the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe againſt their Biſhop.</note> in that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their due obedience, which they had alwayes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to <hi>S. Siege</hi> their proper Biſhop, who recipro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ought to protect them, hee yet oppreſſed them greevouſly, to the great prejudice and diſhonour of the Catholike Religion, the warre rayſed by him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving already conſumed and layd waſte 5000. dwelling houſes in the Country, not without prophanation of the Sanctuaries, Churches, and holy Veſſels, as Chali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Bells, and other ſacred Vtenſils and Ornaments, which were imployed to other uſes, then what they were firſt ordained for; That the hallowed Hoſte was trampled on by them who ought to honour it: that the Church-men deſigned for Divine Service, were chaſed from their Pariſhes, where by that meanes the <hi>Liturgie</hi> was quite aboliſhed in ſome places, and in the Major part much intermitted: That the Religious
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:7470:38"/>women, and others, both Wives and Virgins, were raviſhed before the eyes of their owne husbands, and Fathers. Their Heards of Cattell were driven away, their tillage decayed, and to ſpeake no more, that the ſole inhabitants of <hi>Liege</hi> were conſtrained to contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute above 60000. Florins to the Church to preſerve the City from the Siege, threatned by <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Verdun, Piccolomini,</hi> and <hi>Iohn de Werth,</hi> upon his ſolicitation, who had incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed one party of the <hi>Liegois,</hi> againſt the other; whoſe tyranny cauſed 5. principall Burgheſſes of <hi>Tongres,</hi> to to be led as like ſlaves, before his tryumphant Chariot, putting two of them (in the end) to the Sword, and baſtinadoing the other three, till they had promiſed a good ranſome. Much more was added, and every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular expreſſed with ſuch paſſion, as might have mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a <hi>Scythian</hi> to compaſſion; yet, their onely prayer was, that his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> would excuſe their boldneſſe, and ſend them ſome Cardinall for a Protectour, by whoſe countenance, they might be defended from ſuch oppreſſions. But the effect of this Petition, and what it avayled is not yet diſcovered, though it may bee thought fruitleſſe (if we may gueſſe upon conſequents) by this enſuing Hiſtory.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Count of <hi>Warfuſee's</hi> treaſon at <hi>Liege.</hi>
                  </note>Naturall reſpect muſt needes have moved teares. from the eyes of <hi>Caeſars</hi> Sonne, at his Fathers funerall, But the conſideration of his care in preſervation, and for enlarging the honour of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a ſolemne mourning; his deceaſe miniſtred oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to a bloody aſſaſinate, to attempt a deed of hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, which for his owne credits-ſake he meant to pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liate with a cloake of authority, forging letters to the Biſhop of <hi>Cullen,</hi> and thereby expreſſing an order and commiſſion given him by the King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (doubtles) to mitigate his execrable action, under
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:7470:39"/>pretence of his commiſſion, if he ſhould hap to fayle and be diſcovered (no ſincere interpreter, being able to conceive that ſo heroicall a ſpirit would conſent to ſo foule a treaſon) and to ſuppreſſe them, if hee had happily executed his deſigne. The ſtory (as ſome doe relate it) is thus? The Count <hi>Warfuſee,</hi> who ſome yeares paſt had revolted from the <hi>Catholick-King,</hi> ſtood in diſpleaſure, during the life of the late Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, both with his <hi>Imperiall-Majeſty</hi> and the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and now thinking to winne his Maiſters fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour againe, by the heads, lives, and ſtates of thoſe which entertained him in his rebel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, plotted the death of <hi>la Ruelle,</hi> prime Magiſtrate of <hi>Lieg,</hi> &amp; ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r principall members of that body-politique, &amp; put it thus in practice. The Count being lodged in St. <hi>Iohns-Cloyſter,</hi> in the houſe of a <hi>Prebend</hi> of that Church, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated with a backe-doore toward the water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide; invited to dinner thither, the ſaid <hi>Burger-maſter de la Ruelle,</hi> the Abbot of <hi>Mouſſon,</hi> and divers other principle men of the Citie, whom he intended to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther trayterouſly. To that purpoſe he ſuborned the <hi>Burgundian Count de Milis,</hi> and ſome choice <hi>Spaniſh</hi>-Souldiers drawne out of the Garriſons of <hi>Narrigue,</hi> and <hi>Argentoy,</hi> to ſteale privately by the Poſterne into his houſe, and to lurke there ſecretly till the word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given, they might be prepared for execution, which they ob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erved &amp; performed accordingly. In the middeſt of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſt (as if his malice had not tended to the mine of their bodies, but their Soules alſo) when their hearts were merry with wine, hee began a health to <hi>Lewis King</hi> of <hi>France</hi> ſurnamed the luſt, which had no ſooner paſſed round, but the <hi>Aſſaſinates</hi> armed with Swords &amp; Piſtolls, broke into the dining<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roome, ſurpriſed the <hi>Burgermaiſter,</hi> and the <hi>Abbot,</hi> ſent for a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and as ſoone as he was come, as if
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:7470:39"/>they would doe them ſome favour at their death,<note place="margin">Ruelle <hi>the</hi> Burger-Maſter <hi>murthered.</hi>
                  </note> bade them make their confeſſion, for they muſt dye. The Prieſt who was ſent for to take his confeſſion, was the <hi>Sub-Prior</hi> of the <hi>Covent,</hi> by name <hi>Antory Evrard,</hi> a <hi>Dominican,</hi> who accompanied with his confrater <hi>William L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ncon</hi> (both which have teſtified this relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on under their hands) went, and at their comming to <hi>Warfuſee</hi> the <hi>Sub-prior</hi> hearing his demand to take <hi>Ruelles</hi> confeſſion and give him abſolution, like a man amazed, ſtood agaſt, inquiring the reaſon of that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and what his Lordſhip meant, by requiring him to that ſervice, which he might not doe but with licence from his Ordinary; except onely in ſome ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, in which upon the appearance of imminent death, it was lawfull for him ſo to doe if the Prieſt deputed thereunto, by his Superiour was not to be found. To this the <hi>Count</hi> replied, that <hi>Ruelle</hi> muſt dye, and that within the ſpace of one quarter of an houre, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore commanded him to diſpatch immediatly, as hee would anſwer upon his Soule the <hi>Burger-maiſters</hi> ſalvation, being deſperate if he ſhould die unconfeſſed. The Frier ſeeing the inraged countenance of the <hi>Count,</hi> &amp; fearing his owne life if he ſhould diſobey, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered onely that he would not doe it till the <hi>Burger-maiſter</hi> called him; there needed no further words. A ſervant that ſtood by apprehended what his Lord meant, and going in, and comming ſuddainly againe from the Chamber where <hi>Ruelle</hi> lay bound, he tels the Frier that he deſired him to come in. The ſight of the Magiſtrate bound like a malefactor put the <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nican</hi> into a greater paſſion, and compaſſion for him; and with ſome language expreſſing ſorrow, wiſhed him to prepare for death, the <hi>Count</hi> being reſolved to murther him; <hi>Ruelle</hi> much diſtracted with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of his eſtate, one while according to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:7470:40"/>of the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> commended himſelfe to God and the bleſſed <hi>Virgin</hi> preparing for death, and then againe, hoping for life, deſired the Fryar to be an advocate for him to <hi>Worfuſee,</hi> as willing to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by him to any priſon or gallies, if he had done him injury: all which was related againe by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour to the <hi>Count</hi> who ſtopped his eares againſt him and conſtrained the Good-man, to that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wellcome worke of his office, which was but the immediate <hi>Prodromus</hi> to the <hi>Burger-Maiſters</hi> execution.</p>
               <p>There was no remedy but patience; they ſaw the guides which muſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duct them to the black-chambers of death before them, made their confeſſion, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to bid the world good-night.<note place="margin">Ruelle <hi>the</hi> Burger-Maſter <hi>mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>thered.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Ruelle</hi> was the firſt who had diſcarged his Soule of the burthen of ſinnes upon it, and he was inſtantly delivered by <hi>Warfu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee</hi> to the <hi>Count de Millis,</hi> who tooke him into an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other chamber, thruſt him through the body 7 times with a rapier, and ſo murthered him. The <hi>Abbot</hi> of <hi>Mouſſon,</hi> a French-gentleman, named <hi>Mounſier de Saiſon,</hi> and two ſervants of the <hi>Burger-maiſters,</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized at the ſame time with thoſe two prime men, were adviſed, in the interim, by the Traytor, to goe to confeſſion, and prepare for their diſſolution. The <hi>Abbot</hi> a well-ſpoken man, a good Orator, and now improved in that faculty, by the goodneſſe of his cauſe, began to plead for his owne life, and his compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, declaring their innocency, laying before the murtherer the hainouſneſſe of his offence. But words were vaine, <hi>Millis</hi> returned ſodainely from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer execution, drew out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s boſome a formall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, and ſentence againſt them, in the name of the new Emperour (as they ſtiled him,) the <hi>Cardinall Infant,</hi> and the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Liege,</hi> as offenders againſt his <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:7470:40"/>Majeſty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Abbot</hi> of <hi>Mouſſon,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſtrangely delivered.</note> which they conceiting to bee an act of of Court, and not to be reverſed, pleaded no more for life, but prepared for death. <hi>Familiarity of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, doth ſometimes raiſe a ſtrange affection,</hi> while the <hi>Abbot</hi> was under confeſſion, a Souldier of <hi>Nairaigne,</hi> who had formerly bin intimately acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with one of the <hi>Burger-Maſters</hi>-ſervants, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with compaſſion, toward him, rounded him in the eare, and ſhewed him a way by which he might e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape, and ſave his life. It was needleſſe to repeate that leſſon againe unto him. <hi>Extremity miniſters capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the apprehenſion of an eminent danger, rouſeth up a dul ſpirit to ſeek meanes to avoid it.</hi> The way was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen enough, but too praecipitious to be attempted with ſecurity, Danger attended the counſell of eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping (yet that perhaps might be avoided) but certain deſtruction waited upon his ſtay. A chamber-window proffered a paſſage, and through that the young-man eſcaped, crying out, Treaſon, <hi>Ruelle</hi> is murthered, Treaſon, <hi>Ruelle</hi> is murthered in the houſe of <hi>Count Warfuſee,</hi> Treaſon, Treaſon, Treaſon. The noyſe was full of horror, and the name of <hi>Ruelle</hi> much honoured among the Cittizens, who inſtantly tooke up their armes, aſſaulted the houſe, which being ſtrong, and built of ſquare ſtone, was by the ſpace of two houres maintained againſt the Cittizens, by <hi>Warfuſees</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers and ſervants, who being in all ſeventy ſtrong, and more carefull of their owne preſervation, then the intended murther, left the <hi>Abbot,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The rage of the Cittizens, &amp; the end of the <hi>Aſſaſinates.</hi>
                  </note> the French-gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and the other ſervant bound, to provide for their owne ſafety. But it was vaine for the defendants, to conteſt againſt ſuch a multitude of aſſailants. The Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens were ten thouſand in number, and they in the end broke open the doores, fell upon the murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers (who cryed for quarter) without pitty, haled <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſee</hi>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:7470:41"/>into the open ſtreets, where he no ſooner appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, but was hewen perce-meale by the Cittizens, the truncke of his body drawne, &amp; hanged upon a gibbet, which w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s raiſed ſuddainely for that purpoſe, and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tely. <hi>Milis</hi> the <hi>Burgundian</hi> had no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> a fate, and the common-ſouldiers employed in that maſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, had as bad a fortune, being all burned in and with the houſe, in which they were aſſembled for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention of their villany. The rage of the Citizens was not thus extinguiſhed. The <hi>Ioſuits,</hi> who were ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the plotters of this device, were the next day after inquired into, and many fier-locks, carabines, &amp; piſtolls ready charged, being fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in their cels, two of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dres,</hi> were put to the ſword, &amp; the reſt baniſhed the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. A more ſtrict watch the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had bin kept formerly, was pointed preſently, &amp; <hi>Ap.</hi> 8/8 when their beloved Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour was buried in the church of St. <hi>La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bert,</hi> under the greate crown with this reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance ingraven on his tombe.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Pour eſtre fidel à ma Patrie</l>
                  <l>P ay perdu mon ſang &amp; ma vie.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which may be thus Engliſhed.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My ſtudie for my Countries good,</l>
                  <l>Hath coſt my life and deareſt blood.</l>
               </q>
               <p>While the 32. Companies of the City were met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, it was condeſcended that the 20. penny of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> man, lands and goods ſhould be levied immediately, to raiſe and maintaine a freſh traine-Band of 1000. men, which at an houres warning ſhould attend the colours of <hi>Bartholus Rolandus</hi> the Cities Generall, to ſerve the City in caſe of neceſſity.</p>
               <p>This is the Hiſtory. And now ſee how the crime would conceale its owne ſhame by the countenance of authority. This enſuing Letter, ſealed with 3. ſeales, was taken out of the Traytors boſome at his firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion; directed in theſe words:</p>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:7470:41"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>TO HIS MOST ILLVSTRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Highneſſe, my Lord Elector of <hi>Coln.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y ayde of the Soldiers, which I raiſed for the Service of his <hi>Imperiall</hi> Majeſty,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Warf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                                 <desc>••••</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> counterfeited Letter.</note> and by order and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Commiſsion from his ſayd Maieſty, I have ſlaine the Burger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter <hi>Ruelle,</hi> he having firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed himſelfe, and ſubmitted to the will of GOD and his Maieſtie. By his order alſo, have apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Abbot <hi>Mouſſon,</hi> Mounſ. <hi>de Seſan,</hi> and ſome others, over whom I keepe a ſtrict guard. Had I ſtayed but two houres longer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I put the project into executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I ſhould furely have bin a dead man, to the diſgrace of his <hi>Imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:7470:42"/>Majeſty</hi> and your <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> as I ſhall ſhorrly ſhow your <hi>Highneſse</hi> more particularly, and at large. It is much to be feared, that the <hi>French</hi> will now murther my onely Son: yet herein I reioyce, that I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered him up for the advantage, of your <hi>Highneſse,</hi> his ſaid <hi>Imperiall Maſ.</hi> and my <hi>King.</hi> I am reſolved to continue their Servant, and will not omit to certifie your <hi>Highnes</hi> daily, of all that ſhall happen here, and what I ſhall effect. And now, Time forbidding me to write more largely, I humbly kiſſe your <hi>Highnes</hi> hand, and ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine as long as I live,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your Highneſſe, moſt obedient, humble, and faithfull Servant, <hi>R. Count of WARFUSEE.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>Liege, Ap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>. <date>
                              <hi>1637.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="history">
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:7470:42"/>
            <head>Hiſtoria Varia.</head>
            <p>Hitherto we haue brought downe a continued Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, the wheeles of the worke, anſwering each other though farre diſtant by place. Now by a various, and incertexted relation, wee ſhall diſcover the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable paſſages, which haue happened, ſince the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod of our laſt diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The cauſe of the <hi>Turks</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> the Mediterranian part of <hi>Dacia,</hi> a rich Countrey, and noted by Antiquity, for it's fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe was terrified with <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Armies, the halfe Moones being there diſplayed, in the behalfe of <hi>Iſtuan Bethleem,</hi> againſt the Prince <hi>Ragotsky,</hi> who then ſate at the ſterne of that Province. The occaſion was this: <hi>Solimy David,</hi> one of the greateſt Lords of <hi>Tranſilva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> Coſin to <hi>Eſtienne,</hi> or <hi>Iſtuan Bethleem,</hi> who preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded himſelfe, the lawfull heire of that Principality, then (as it was conceived) uſurped by <hi>Ragotsky,</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with the fame of the late deceaſed King of <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> ſent to him in the yeare 1631. to tender him his ſervice, and unwilling to come alone, reſolved ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to raiſe 2000. men, whereof himſelfe would bee the Chiefetaine. His deſigne could not bee carried ſo privately, from that ſtirring and warlike Nation, as to be confined with ſo ſmall a number. Upon the beating of his Drumme, and report of his intendment, inſtead of 2000 alone, ſuch a number of Voluntieres came to preſent themſelues to the Liſt; that <hi>Ragotskie,</hi> who before had carried a jealous eye over him, now more ſuſpecting ſome deſigne againſt himſelfe, then former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; muſtred up his forces, and with them diſperſed and diſarmed <hi>Bethleems</hi> new raiſed Army. This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe ſo inraged <hi>Solymies</hi> friends (who had bin aſſiſted in this action by ſome other Lords of <hi>Tranſilvania</hi>) that they conſpired to murther <hi>Ragotskie,</hi> their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe being palliated with a new forme of hunting, to the which they meant to invite him. For execution
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:7470:43"/>whereof, it being thought that none could be more affectionated than <hi>Solimy David,</hi> who was now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to breake his word, with that renowned King, to whom he had promiſed ſo great matters, drew him alſo into their conjuration.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Solimy,</hi> more civilized, and not ſo inclined to cruelty, as others of that Province (though at the firſt hee ſeemed to conſent) yet afterwards, diſtaſting that courſe, the ſame day, when as the Plot ſhould have bin put into execution; poſted to the Prince, diſcovered the Treaſon, and with prayers, and teares, prevailed with him, to refraine from that daies ſport. <hi>Ragotskie</hi> made good uſe of his tale, and carrying for the preſent, a face of love towards <hi>Solimy,</hi> diſmiſſed him friendly; but armed withall a Squadron of Horſe, againſt the Conſpirators; who ſurpriſed them eaſily, (becauſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expectedly) and tortured them with divers kinds of puniſhments to death; onely the Prince <hi>Iſtuan,</hi> who was the prime Projector, (diſguiſed) lurked upon an adjoyning Mountaine, to ſee the effect of the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, and ſaw how his Friends were uſed, ſaving himſelfe by fright into the Grand Signiors Territorie. <hi>A thought of treaſon, is treaſon; and however, a Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator may thinke to merit his Princes favour, by revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling it; yet if he defer the diſcovery to the laſt houre, and then, either ſtung with the pricks of Conſcience, or allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the hope of reward, reveale it; his Princes cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie may pardon his tranſgreſſion, his merit cannot be ſaid to have deſerved it; the execution of Iuſtice, being due to him that ſhall give conſent to ſo horrid an action, though hee may afterward ſeeme to repent. Solimy</hi> not looking back to that part of the Wallet, which was behind him, or thinking of that ſpeckled toad, which be had lodged in his heart, his treaſon; with a kind of confidence, of merit from the Prince, went againe to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:7470:43"/>the Court, preſſed the ſervice he had done to his Lord boldly, demanded recompence, not thinking that hee had been diſcovered, as a partie in that treaſon. But the Prince, who had already examined the matter throughly, and found him to be a Conſpirator, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him extremity of Juſtice, in ſtead of Mercie; bound him hand and foot; caſt him into a ſtinking, loathſome, and terrible Priſon, made more horrid by its ſolitude; all people being forbid to come thither (under paine of death) to give him ſo much as a viſit, (thoſe onely excepted) who were appointed to guard his perſon, and to give him the ſtrict allowance of bread, and water, to the amazement of <hi>Solimy,</hi> who by this meanes, being brought to a frenzie, behaved himſelfe ſo rudely, that the people ſuppoſed him to have beene poſſeſſed with a Devill. Newes of his ſtrange comportment, raiſed by reaſon of the rigour of his impriſonment, was brought into the Empire, and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> moved to compaſſion in reſpect of his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, wrote in his behalfe to <hi>Ragotskie,</hi> to abate his puniſhing hand, to admit ſome Ieſuites to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe unto him, for his inſtruction; that he might not loſe his Soule together with his Body; <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camentum pejus morbo;</hi> and to conſider, that the effect of the ſervice hee had done unto him, might at leaſt, ſtand in an equall poiſe, againſt the treaſon to which he had conſented: To all which, the Prince gave no other anſwer, but that if the Devill had got no new one, <hi>Solimy</hi> might be his Secretary. <hi>Iſtuan,</hi> in the meane time ceaſed not to intercede by Friends for his owne reconciliation, but not prevailing, hee implo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ayde of the Grand Signior, who furniſhed him with an Armie, and promiſed to inveſt him in the Principality of <hi>Tranſilvania. Regotskie,</hi> to oppoſe him, ſent to the Emperour, and the <hi>Polonian</hi> for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:7470:44"/>of which though hee failed, neither of them being willing to provoke ſuch an enemie, with his owne forces encountred the Baſſaw in the Field; and by foiling the <hi>Turkes</hi> in their firſt onſet, cleared his Country of thoſe <hi>Mahometan</hi> Invaders.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King, who had lately given order for the billetting his Armie, and ſupplying in with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Proviſions; ſeeing the inconvenience which happened thereupon, by a continuall acceſſe of men of Armes, Light-horſe, and Carabines, to the moleſtation and great charge of his Subjects, after the old Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies were layd in Garriſon; put forth another De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, as the Rule of his former Ordinance, the ſumme whereof was this: That the Contribution and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhould not bee afterwards delivered,<note place="margin">The King of <hi>France</hi> his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for his Souldiers, and caſe of the people.</note> but for 60 Maſters of every Company of men of Armes; for fifty of each Company of Carabines, comprehending there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their Chieftaines, and other Officers; provided ſtill, that there be that number in each Company effectivé; forbidding expreſſely, all the Commanders of the ſayd Companies, to exact, or compell the Villages and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces lyable to thoſe Contributions, to deliver more then as preſcribed, for ſuch a number of men as is limitted by this Ordinance, upon paine of ſuffering as Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners. This Order both pleaſed the people, being thereby ſecured from further oppreſſion, and the inrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Souldiers, ſuch good order being taken for their ſubſiſtance and maintenance.</p>
            <p>This billeting of Souldiers in the Frontiers was not unneceſſary. <hi>Iohn de Werth,</hi> &amp; <hi>Pycolimini,</hi> who were gone towards the Frontiers of <hi>Luxenburg,</hi> were upon the returne to invade the Kings Dominions, <hi>Decem</hi> 8/1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they were come over the Bridge of <hi>Gyvais,</hi> upon the <hi>Maaſe.</hi> The Marqueſſe <hi>De la Force</hi> underſtanding of the enterpriſe, made head againſt them, to the terrour
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:7470:44"/>of the common Souldiers under the Spaniſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mande, their Generall commanding the Bridge to bee broken downe behind him, thinking thereby to cauſe his men to fight; the common Souldiers oppoſed it, and fearing to bee hemmed in betwixt the River and the French Army, made more haſte then good ſpeed to returne; and in a tumultuous confuſion, haſting back towards the River (the Bridge being peſtered with their owne Carriages) they preſſed ſo thick one upon another, that to the number of foure hundred men were thruſt into the water and drovvned, and many Waggons overturned into the River. And this ill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, made the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Generall betake himſelfe to the Forreſt of <hi>Liege,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn de Wethe <hi>flight.</hi>
               </note> being purſued by the Count of <hi>Quinſe,</hi> the Marqueſte <hi>De la Force,</hi> and the Collonell <hi>Gaſſion,</hi> who cut off many of the Reareguard, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſtill flying towards the Biſhopricke of <hi>Triers,</hi> where hee was appointed to take up his Winter-Quarter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gaſsion,</hi> being now free from any offenſive Enemy, ranne over the Country of <hi>Henault,</hi> plundering it, and exacting of the Villages there, the ſame ſumms of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Contributions which <hi>Don Marcos de Lima</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Governour in <hi>La Capelie</hi> exacted from the French Villages in that Vicinage. The <hi>Cardinall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant,</hi> as well to retaliate the French Frontiers with the like Inrodes, as to reinforce his Gariſons, ſent into <hi>Irſon,</hi> (a Towne upon the River of <hi>Oiſe.</hi> lately apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe;</hi> but taken by the Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards in the late Invaſion) the Regiments of Horſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Command of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Bath,</hi> and <hi>De la Granges,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in all about ſix hundred, as a reinforcement to the Preſidiaries there, and then that Garriſon being growne confident of their owne ſtrength, began to plunder the Neightour Territories. <hi>Decemb,</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>/26 <hi>Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:7470:45"/>had Intelligence, that the next day at ten in the morning, the Garriſon intended to goe a forraging in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into the Villages about <hi>Neufmaiſon.</hi> To loſe no time hee preſently commanded the Sergeant-Maior of his owne Regiment, to take foure Companies out of his Regiment, which was then at <hi>Vervin,</hi> with inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to lye in ambuſh in a Wood, and to attend the iſſuing out of the Garriſon; Himſelfe not being in caſe for that Service, becauſe of an old would upon him, which then began to bleed afreſh. The Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant-Maior performed his Directions ſo ſpeedily, that within one hower after his Trumpets were ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (the <hi>Boute-ſelle</hi> being given immediately) the Horſemen were all ready, and were inſtantly about their buſineſſe, wayting in their Ambuſhment till the next day at Noone, at which time the Enemies were diſcovered to bee ready to ſally forth of the Citie. By the ſpace of two and twentie howers, in vvhich the French Cavallery attended the Spaniards comming out of their Hold,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oo Walloon Horſe defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by <hi>Gaſsion</hi> neere <hi>Neuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſon.</hi>
               </note> no noyſe was heard in that ſmall Campe, nor were they diſcovered by the Garriſon, though lodged within a quarter of an Engliſh mile from thence. An high tree, which raiſed his loftie head above the reſt of the Thicket, vvas prepared by the Sergeant-Maior, as a Watch-tovver to diſcover the Spaniſh preparations. Foure Scouts were ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Commander to that purpoſe; one in the topp of that boughie Tree, who could caſily looke into the Caſtle, and himſelfe unſeene, ſee eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing done therein, and obſerve eſpecially the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe, and egreſſe of them that came in, and went out thence. Another Scout vvas placed in the middle of the Tree, a third at the foot, and a fourth twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie paces thence, with fifteene French Horſe, and the Bodie of the Armie fifteene paces thence, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:7470:45"/>was given in a trice of the Spaniards ſally, the ſecond Sentinell receiving it from the firſt, the third from the ſecond, the fourth from him, and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie from the laſt. The Cavallery thereupon kept cloſe in their Ambuſhment, vvhile the Spaniſh for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces about three hundred Horſe, having paſſed the River of <hi>Irſon,</hi> and the Wood wherein they lay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcovered, tooke their March toward <hi>Neufmaiſon.</hi> The Spaniard ſurpaſſing the French in number, and the advantage of the place, made the French Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander adviſe with his Captaines, whether it was fit at that time to incounter them. The feare of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, by the neighbour-Garriſon, and the countenance of the Spaniards ſhewing a couragious Reſolution, diſ-hartened the Commander from attempting any thing: but three Captaines of that Band, <hi>Rauonelle, La Lande,</hi> and <hi>Balthaſar,</hi> ſprightly Gentlemen, and aſhamed to returne to the Collonell, without ſome tokens of their Valour, reſolved to take fifteene Horſe out of each Companie, which under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of <hi>Balthaſar,</hi> ſhould give the firſt charge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Spaniards, whileſt the other remainder of the Armie, being divided into three Squadrons, might come up conveniently to ſecond them. The Spaniards ſtood then in a firme Body, and having ſent an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Horſe into the Village of <hi>Neufmaiſon,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two hundred attended armed in three Squadrons to ſecure the pillagers from the French Military men, if any ſhould happen to march that way. And now began the hurly burly: <hi>Balthaſar</hi> came on bravely, and in his firſt Charge had ſeven of his men woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Spaniſh opponents. But that ſcratch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hartened not the French Aſſaylants, who comming up to his ſuccour, charged upon the firſt Squadron with their Piſtolets, and with the firſt volly of Shot, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:7470:46"/>ſlaine above twentie of the Enemies, routed the reſt of the Squardron; whoſe ſudden flight cauſed the other two Squadrons to betake themſelves to their heeles in a ſtrange confuſion; the <hi>French</hi> troopes purſuing them eagerly, and in the purſuit having ſlaine ſeventy others, conſtrained the reſt to take the River, wherein forty three of them were found drowned immediately, and ſeventy two begging Quarter, had it granted them. The ſtorme was not yet ſpent, the Peſants of <hi>Neufmaiſon,</hi> and the other Neighbour Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, heard the report of this defeat and ſallied from the Woods, in which they had hid themſelves for feare of the Enemie, and incouraged by the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, fell upon the remnant of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> ſlew fifteene or ſixteene of them, tooke the reſt about ninety in number Priſoners, whom they brought to <hi>Vervins,</hi> with two hundred Horſe, upon which the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Souldiers were mounted; ſo gaining foure fold, what they had loſt, by thoſe Pillagers. In ſhort, none eſcaped, ſave onely nineteen Souldiers, and their Captaine <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſanſano,</hi> and his Cornet, who in this confuſion, got over the River where it was wadeable, and ſaved themſelves in that Garriſon. All the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners tooke ſervice under <hi>Gaſſion,</hi> ſix onely excepted, men of r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and qualitie, which having their wives and children in <hi>Irſon,</hi> durſt not ſerve under his Colours, but proff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red a good ranſome.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Picardy</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hus freed, in the end of the old yeare, of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> bands, the Countie of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and the Province of <hi>Guien,</hi> onely remained to bee ſecured from thoſe invaders. <hi>Ionville,</hi> a Citie in the <hi>French</hi> Countie, upon the River of <hi>Saone,</hi> was made a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazine for Victualls, and other Proviſions, and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitions for Warre, by <hi>Gallas,</hi> when hee made his firſt inrode into the Dutchie of <hi>Burgundy.</hi> Duke
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:7470:46"/>
               <hi>Barnard</hi> in that time of Winter, reſolved to beſiege it, and to that purpoſe, taking with him three ſmall Pieces of Canon, began to batter it; but thoſe Guns, not able to bore the Wall, hee ſent for three greater, which were brought unto his Armie, not without much difficultie; the fowle waies, and deepe waters being ready to ſinke them, unleſſe they had beene ſupported by ſtrength of men. This incumbrance, did ſomewhat ſlacken the execution of what hee inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. The Garriſon was One thouſand ſtrong, the Enemies ſuccors began to appeare in perſon, for their aſſiſtance, and Duke <hi>Barnard,</hi> too weake with that handfull of men hee had deſigned for this occaſion, ſent to the Cardinall <hi>De Valette</hi> for more helpe, who ſent thither, the Vicount <hi>De Turenne</hi> with Two thouſand Foot, and the Collonell <hi>Tupadell</hi> with Ten Regiments of Horſe: And they comming in maturely, plied their Batteries cloſe, and having made a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble breach in the Wall, threatned to aſſault it. The Praeſidiaries, though ſo many in number, as might have defended the Citie, yet wanting courage (for they were not all Souldiers that bore Armes, Five hundred Burgeſſes and Peſants being imployed in that ſervice) or not truly affecting the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> for Foure hundred of the Souldiers were ſtrangers, and none of his Subjects; hung out a Flag of Truce immediately, and conſented to deliver up the Towne, onely with leave to depart, with their Armes and Baggage, which was granted, and the Garriſon diſmiſſed, ſave onely <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bercourt</hi> the Commander, who was detained Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and the Town ſurrendred to Duke <hi>Barnard.</hi> And thus the laſt yeares Tumults were ended about the Dutchie of <hi>Burgundy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Guien,</hi> the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Forces were ſtill buſie, ſince the prize of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn de Luz</hi> (whence thirty Religious
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:7470:47"/>
               <hi>Reformadoes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Fort of St. <hi>Barba</hi> taken by the Count of <hi>Grammont.</hi>
               </note> rather deſired to depart, and leave all they had, than to give the Oath of Allegeance to their Enemies, which they ought unto their King) and the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> ſeeing that the Holds which they poſſeſſed neere S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn de Luz</hi> &amp; <hi>Cibouro,</hi> could yield them no advantage; to proceed further with their Forces (a River running through the middle of the Valley, in which thoſe Forts were placed, whoſe current hindred their Progreſſe) they deviſed in the month of <hi>October,</hi> to raiſe a Fort neere the Church dedicated to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba,</hi> where there is a very ſtrong Tower, and ſuch a one as might ſerve almoſt for their deſigne. Six weeks together, their Labourers and Pioners had been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed for that worke, and they followed it ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly, that by the ninth of <hi>December</hi> new ſtile, they had brought it to defence, and garriſoned it with two hundred of their beſt men, and fortified it with two Pieces of Canon. The Count of <hi>Grammont,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour for the King in <hi>Bayon,</hi> conſidering how ſerviceable the Fort was for the Enemies, who might not onely from thence protect their ſpoiling Bands, ſent into <hi>France,</hi> but diſcover alſo the <hi>French</hi> troopes, that ſhould march from <hi>Bayon,</hi> againſt them; reſolved to defer it no longer, but inſtantly to aſſault it. To this purpoſe, <hi>December</hi> 19. new ſtile, hee ſelected nine hundred men out of the Garriſon of <hi>Bayon,</hi> and firſt the day following, having fallen upon fiftie Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dues of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> partie, ſurpriſed them; and incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by this beginning, ran furiouſly with his Armie to the Fort, ſcaled it at once in twentie ſeverall places, and though the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> fighting bravely, kept the Combate doubtfull by the ſpace of halfe an houre, yet in the end, became Maſter of the great <hi>Baſtion,</hi> and ſlew all the Souldiers appointed to guard it, ſave onely fifteene which fled to the Church, preſerved as a place
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:7470:47"/>of Refuge, by 12 of their companie, if the Fort ſhould chance to be ſurpriſed by that onſlat. <hi>Valour, not number, is moſt prevalent in warlike actions.</hi> Thoſe twentie ſeven alone, which had made a Cittadell of the Sanctuary, did more hurt to the <hi>French</hi> Aſſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, than the whole companie appointed for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the <hi>Baeſtion.</hi> They baricadoed the Church dores, and by the advantage of the Tower, renewed a deſperate fight, of two howers long againſt the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiegers. In the end wearied, not vanquiſhed, they began to ſlacken the Combare, and that little inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, giving time to the <hi>French,</hi> to expedite the worke, a new Scalao was made, and the <hi>French</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Maſters of the Tower. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> caſe then grew deſperate; yet as the Nation is more jealous of their Honour, than carefull of their lives, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to fight it out, though diſadvantagiouſly, and not yield cowardly. The reſiſtance they made, was rather deſperate, than grounded upon true fortitude. To preſerve their lives by fight, it was very impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, and to eſcape by flight impoſſible: Yet fight they did, almoſt to the laſt man, and all were ſlaine, ſave three onely, who complying with neceſſity, yielded themſelves, and were taken as Priſoners of war Time would not permit the Count of <hi>Grammont,</hi> to adviſe what to doe. Carry away the two Pieces of Canon hee could not, wanting ſuch equipage, as was needfull for that worke, and therefore hee tumbled them into the Sea. To ſtand to garriſon the F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t, hee might not; during the Combare, the groſſe body of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armie, which was then at <hi>Bordagaine,</hi> began to play with their Ordance upon him and ſent 200 Horſe in 2 Squadrons againſt him, who appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in the vally, which ſeparated the French fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heir Enemies, the Count poſted ſpeedily to aſſaile them, and
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:7470:48"/>charged them ſo furiouſly, that hee compelled them to fly to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohn de Luz,</hi> where another groſſe body of their Armie was inquartered, and then returned to the fort, which he demoliſhed and made unſerviceable for the Enemie, and thence marched home to <hi>Bayon,</hi> to raiſe up ſtronger Forces to oppoſe the Invaders.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Priches,</hi> a frontier towne of <hi>Picardy,</hi> plundred by the French Captaine <hi>Rand.</hi>
               </note>One more Relation onely, I find worth the recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for that laſt yeare. The Marques of <hi>Praſlin,</hi> having ſent One hundred Horſe to the Froutiers of <hi>Picardy,</hi> to informe him of the poſture of the <hi>Spaniards, Rand</hi> the Captaine of the Companie, perceived himſelfe of a ſudden, to be come ſo neere the Town of <hi>Priches;</hi> then poſſeſſed by the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> that he thought it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for him to retire, before the Inhabitants of the place had raiſed the Countrey againſt him; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, reſolved to prevent them, and aſſault the Towne firſt. To this end, having disburthened ſome of his Horſes, of Twentie Muſquetiers, that number of Horſe, ſerving as Dragons in this Expedition, they charging, diſcharging, &amp; recharging nimbly, made his way againſt ſome few Defendants, which had guarded the Advenues, and barricadoed them againſt all Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; himſelfe following, with the reſt of his Forces, broke them up, and entred the Towne, otherwiſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defenced, ſaving by a ſmall Fort, plundered it, and burnt it to the ground. Some Priſeners hee tooke, and carried to the Marqueſſe, who being informed by one of them, that the wife of <hi>Don Marcos de Lima,</hi> Governour for the <hi>Catholick</hi> King in <hi>La Capella,</hi> was comming to viſit her Husband, hee inſtantly tooke Two hundred Light-horſe, and made an Ambuſcado wich them, in a pace called <hi>Flamangre,</hi> neere the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, where hee was ſcarce arrived, before he had In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence by a Corporall, that three <hi>Wallon</hi> Captaines, <hi>Lorgue, Franquin,</hi> and <hi>Anbrestrot,</hi> which ſerved in
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:7470:48"/>that Citie, were comming abroad to forrage;<note place="margin">The Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of <hi>Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons</hi> defeated, and rowted by the Marqueſſe <hi>praſlin.</hi>
               </note> preſently tooke up his Sword and Piſtoll, wiſhing the reſt of his men to be in a readineſſe after his example; and himſelfe went ſecretly to one ſide of the Hill, whence he might diſcover the whole Plaine, through which the Enemie was to march, intreating the Earle of <hi>Quinſay,</hi> to repaire to another place, where he might obſerve their Poſture. The Earle and his attendants had them firſt in view, and went inſtantly to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe of <hi>Praſlin,</hi> to certifie him of their comming. The <hi>French</hi> no ſooner heard the tidings thereof, but prepared to Battell, ſcarce being able to contain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their Ambuſcado; yet the indiſcretion of a Spie, appointed by the Count of <hi>Quinſay,</hi> by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſignalls, to notifie the whole troupe, of the neer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and diſtance of the Enemy, had like to have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the enterpriſe. The often waving of his Cap was perceived by the <hi>Wallons,</hi> who thereupon ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti g a traine laid for them, were upon Retreate, and had eſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ped without blowes; had not the Marqueſſe of <hi>Praſlin,</hi> with a round gallop<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> made up to them, and charged them ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>agerly, that of a ſudden they were put to a precipitious flight, not being ſafe till they had reached the Fort of <hi>Grand-Floyon,</hi> whither they were purſued by the <hi>French Cavalarie,</hi> who ſlew forty of them in their flight, and tooke as many Priſoners. And here the laſt yeares Obſervarions are terminated. Wee muſt now looke on to the new yeare, and the new Actions and Occurrances thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1637"/> 
               <hi>Janus</hi> had ſcar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> left off his Infant-ſmile, when the Cardinall <hi>Infant,</hi> breathing out War againſt the united Provinces, ſent out his Proclamation to his Officers, to practiſe all hoſtility ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt the Friends, and Allies of the States in the <hi>Netherlands.</hi> The words ran thus:</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:7470:49"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>By the King. S.</head>
                  <p>TO our moſt deare and faithfull Chancellor, and to our Councell of <hi>Brabant,</hi> greeting, &amp;c. Whereas wee are informed, That our enemies have lately preſumed to impoſe heavy burthens,<note place="margin">A Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſet forth by the Cardinall <hi>Infant,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions.</note> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Contribution for their owne advantage, upon the Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lages and Market Townes neere <hi>Thienen,</hi> intending to augment them, by exacting the like from other places neer that Iuriſdiction, to the great damage of our good and loving subjects, whom wee deſire to preſerve in ſecuritie, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o free from the like Exactions. Wee therefore ordaine and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand by theſe Preſents, That you ſhall immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and without delay make Proclamation in each place of the foreſaid Iuriſdiction, where ſuch Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caràs are commonly proclaimed, That no man, upon paine of our diſpleaſure, and a ſevere and exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry puniſhment, ſhall conſent to collect or pay any ſuch Contributions, more or leſſe, to the advantage of our Enemies, but ſhall to the utmoſt of their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, hinder our enemies, thoſe Rebels, from levying ſuch aydes, injoyning withall, our Souldiers that now are in Garriſon, or hereafter may be; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding all and every one reſiding in the Villages and Market-townes of the ſaid Iuriſdiction, which are able to beare Armes, to arme immediatly, upon the firſt report of our Enemies, or their adherents invaſion; to iſſault and ſlay them that ſhall be found in the ſame dominion, neither admitting them as
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:7470:49"/>priſoners of warre, nor permitting them quarter, which we allow not in any of theſe parts wherein the Contribution is prohibited. Furthermore wee will and require, that a carefull watch by night be kept in every Village where it is needfull, and that the ſame bee performed by a competent number of able Souldiers we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l armed, who a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtone as they ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcry any of the ſaid Rebeils, ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll ſtrike upan All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arme, and purſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fter them: That day and night there ſhall be placed in the Steeples of each Church, Sentinells, and Watch-man to give a warning peale by the ſound of a Bell; upon the hearing whereof, the Neighbouring-villages are enjoyned to take Armes, and to doe their beſt endevour to encounter and purſue after our aforeſaid Enemies and Rebels, and their adherents: Expreſly withall forbidaing all and every one (of what condition ſoever) not to connive or diſſemble in the execution hereof, upon paire of a rigourous, and their exemplary pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. And for the better incouragement of thoſe, whoſe valour and forwardneſſe heerein ſhall teſſifie their Loyaltie; Wee have graunted, and doe graunt, that to each of them who ſhall take Priſoner, or ſlay one of thoſe Enemies, or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells, and bring him to us, either alive or dead; they ſhall bee payed in hand, and immediat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ie Gilders a time, by the Officers appoynted for our Receipt, who ſhall need no further diſcharge for their payment, then this our preſent Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And for the better execition of what is heere required; nee have prohibited all Hoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:7470:50"/>Inne-keepers, Vintners, and Victuallers, which lodge ſtrangers, either within Cities, Market<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>townes, and Villages, or without, to receive any ſuch, as are knowne, or ſuſpected to bee in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of our En mies, bee they their neerest Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or Friends, but command them to adviſe the Officer, Magiſtrate, or Governour of the place thereof immediately, upon paine to forfeit his life, in caſe of his knowledge, and in caſe of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpition, five and twentie Gilders. This is Our pleaſure. <hi>Given in our Citie of Bruxells, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nua. 17/17 1637.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The States replyed againe in words, and in the ſame Language ſet foorth a Placard, againſt the Subjects of the Catholike King; yet neither partie came to blowes, preparations onely for warre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then undertaken, the time not fitting the field, to which the proſecution was referred.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Italie,</hi> an hotter Climate, was more pregnant, and ſooner ſhewed the new fruites of the Spring. <hi>Piacenza</hi> was ſtill beleaguered with the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Troopes, though <hi>Leganez,</hi> the Generall of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, and Governour of <hi>Milan,</hi> was retyred home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for his owne repoſe; the Armies ſtill abode in the Field, which by cloſing up the <hi>Poe,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereepting the Land-paſſages, block't up the Citie, and relu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed it to ſuch extremitie, that the Siſter of the <hi>Grand Duke,</hi> wife to the <hi>Parmeſan,</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, by the middle of <hi>Ianuarie,</hi> to become a Supplya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Armie for her departure, which was gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted her, in regard of her blood, and her Brothers confederacie with the Crowne of <hi>Spaine;</hi> the Duke himſelfe yet relying upon the <hi>French</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:7470:50"/>ſtill abiding in the Citie,<note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> agree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </note> to preſerve it againſt the Aſſailants: His conſtancie to the Chriſtian King, was admired through the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Campe; which knowing his extremitie, and ſeeing his friends faile him, with faire words began to ſolicite him, to relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh the <hi>French</hi> partie, and to renue his amitie with the Catholick King; promiſing as honorable Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as could be demanded of them, or expected from them: There was no great choice. The <hi>French</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors were ſtill at <hi>Aſti;</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> grew ſtronger, and himſelfe weaker: And though they had theſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, they ſtood not upon extremities, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded freely, That if the Duke would be onely a neutrall, and not ſide with the Chriſtian King, againſt his Catholick Majeſtie; they would remove all their Forces out of his Country, reſtore the forts and towns they had taken from him, and eſteeme him as a Friend and Confederate.<note place="margin">The Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement with the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
               </note> The Duke conformed himſelfe to the time, and his owne occaſion; and willingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Propoſition, yet durſt not acquaint the <hi>French</hi> Praeſidiaries with his purpoſe, for feare, that they in a ſudden diſpleaſure ſhould plunder the Citie, nor would he by force of Armes bring it to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect. At laſt, he pretended a generall Muſter without the Gates, and thither drew all the Souldiers, upon a promiſe of paying them their Monies due for wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; but being there, hee calls forth the Collonels and Officers; declaring to them, That the non-performance of things promiſed him by the King of <hi>France,</hi> had brought all this trouble, both upon himſelfe, and his Territorie: That, inforcing neceſſitie had compelled him to capitulate with the Crowne of <hi>Spaine;</hi> and ſhewed them withall, the Articles of the Treatie, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by himſelfe, and the Count of <hi>Leganez,</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Millan,</hi> in behalfe of the Catholick King,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:7470:51"/>rendered thanks to the Souldiers for their ſervice, paid them their ſtipends, which they accepted better than his words, and cauſed them to be conducted to the Frontiers of <hi>Piemont,</hi> by 500 <hi>Spaniſh</hi> horſemen.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Parmeſan</hi> himſelfe was thus quit of his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, entertained in State at <hi>Millan,</hi> commerce of trade was granted betwixt his Subjects and the <hi>Millanoys;</hi> but <hi>Fabio Scotti</hi> his Embaſſador, to the Chriſtian King; upon his returne from <hi>Paris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fabio Scotti,</hi> the <hi>Pormeſans</hi> Embaſſadour, ſent Priſoner to <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </note> whence hee came with Letters to the Confederate Generalls, the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> and the Marſhall <hi>Crequi,</hi> was ſent back by them, as a Priſoner to the King of <hi>France;</hi> the Duke concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (as hee thought) a juſt diſpleaſure againſt the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> for capitulating with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who threatned to invade his Territories; and ſoone after, invaded <hi>Montferat,</hi> driving away 700 great Cattell from the Territorie of <hi>Aſti,</hi> which cauſed him to fortifie his Frontiers, eſpecially at <hi>Turino</hi> and other places bordering upon the Dutchie of <hi>Millan,</hi> and to give a ſudden aſſault againſt the ſtrong Fort of <hi>Fraſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netta;</hi> which hee tooke by onſlat, and garriſoned with 1000 men.</p>
            <p>While theſe things were tranſacting in <hi>Italy,</hi> there paſſed ſome light overtures of War in the Dukedome of <hi>Loraine,</hi> and the <hi>Franch</hi> Countie. <hi>Chavanes,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called <hi>Chavagne,</hi> a ſtrong Piece in the <hi>Franch</hi> Countie, placed betwixt two Hills, upon the banke of the River of <hi>Suran,</hi> neere the Frontier of <hi>France,</hi> and the Territorie of <hi>Breſſe,</hi> garriſoned with 2 <hi>Spaniſh</hi> companies of Horſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chavanes</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by <hi>Thian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et of <hi>Treffor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> bad lately pillaged <hi>Simanère</hi> a Towne in the <hi>Breſſoys,</hi> burned down five or ſix dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houſes, ſlaine the Inhabitants, even to women and children, and the newes thereof being brought to <hi>Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anges,</hi> Covernour of <hi>Trefford;</hi> he, with a ſelected com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of that Garriſon; ſome Voluntiers of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:7470:51"/>400 men of the Train-bands of <hi>Breſſe</hi> and <hi>Bugey,</hi> and 300 old Souldiers of the Regiments of <hi>Anguien</hi> and <hi>Rebe,</hi> making in all 700 foot, and 50 horſe, reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, if it was poſſible, to ſurpriſe it. The enterpriſe was put in practiſe about the middle of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> but not carried ſo ſecretly, as to be concealed from the Garriſon, who acquainted the neighbour Forts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, defired them to have a vigilant eye upon the <hi>French</hi> Commander, and they jointly blocked up the Paſſages, attending the march of the <hi>French</hi> Armie; but the number of the Defendants, was too ſmall to withſtand the Aſſailants; they made their vvay vvith Sword and Piſtoll, vvere at the Tovvn unexpectedly, applied the Petards to the gates, and thoſe engines working effectually, they forced the Garriſon to yield upon diſcretion, vvith their lives ſaved, in the ſight of five troopes of Light-horſe, and three companies of Dragoons, vvhich were ſent from the neighbouring Garriſons for their ſuccour; carried avvay Priſoners, the tvvo Captaines of the Horſe, vvith all their Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Cavaliers, whom they carried to <hi>Burg,</hi> having enriched the Souldiers with their Horſe and Baggage, and the hopes of great Ranſomes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ericourt</hi> beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by part of <hi>Gallas</hi> his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie.</note>
               <hi>Ericourt,</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Monbeliard,</hi> was about the ſame time beſieged by part of <hi>Gallas</hi> his Army, bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with the Cannon, ſome of the out-workes taken, and the Mill neere the gate of the citie ſurprized: by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit whereof, 400 of the Imperiall Army paſſed the water,<note place="margin">400 <hi>Caeſarean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> ſlaine, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Priſoners before <hi>Eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court.</hi>
               </note> and tooke up their Quarter betwixt the River and the City. The Baron of <hi>Annevoux</hi> underſtanding how the place was endangered, with 300 Foot of his owne, and 40 Horſe, attempted hereupon to relieve it; the Quarter betwixt the River and the Citie, was the place he firſt aſſaulted; which being but weakly guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and ſcarce brought to defence, the Souldiers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:7470:52"/>in became a prey to the Aſſay lants, who ſlew 300 of them upon the place, (amongſt which was the Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Grana</hi> his Regiment) took the moſt part of the reſt oriſoners, and amongſt them the Lieutenant to <hi>Tieff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bach,</hi> who afterward dyed of his wounds. This beginning was but an introduction to his further proceeding. The Baron, who commanded a Regiment of 14 French Companies in <hi>Monbeliard</hi> for the King, was informed afterwards, that Collonell <hi>Mercie,</hi> and the Baron of <hi>Suitz,</hi> the Imperiall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders there, ſince the laſt defeat, were reinforced by a new accrewt of ſome troops appertaining to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Gallas;</hi> had continued the ſiege, and brought the Garriſon to the point of ſurrendring for want of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cors: Hereupon, he had a deſigne to relieve it; to bring his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to effect, he aſſayed to doe it many times in the night; but then they having doubled their Guards, and himſelfe failing of the Enterpriſe, hee reſolved to accompliſh that by day-light, which hee could not bring to paſſe in the darke; nor was his counſell croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with an unhappy iſſue. The command of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantery, being deputed to <hi>Tilloy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Siege rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> and <hi>Bailly;</hi> himſelfe in the head of his Horſe fell upon the Trenches of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, put to the ſword a guard of Cavalliers, conſiſting of about 50 Maiſters, 10 only excepted, who were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken priſoners, compelled the Imperiall Foot to forſake a Fort which they had built upon the paſſage betwixt <hi>Monbeliard</hi> and <hi>Ericourt;</hi> rowted ſome other <hi>Corpſes du guard,</hi> and ſent the Auxiliaries into the Citie, under the commaund of his owne Lieutenant <hi>Goliefer,</hi> who alſo carried with him all manner of Ammunition for warre, even to very Hand-mills, whereof the beſieged had much need; to the great incouragement of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, and Praeſidiaries; who thus inheartened, the next night, made out two ſallies; in one of which they
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:7470:52"/>nayled foure pieces of Cannon, and ſlue divers Caeſare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; &amp; to the great diſ-hartening of the Imperiall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſouldiers and Generals, who ſeeing that place thus provided, both of military and alimentary proviſions, after they had loſt above 1000 men before it, made 400 Cannon-ſhot againſt it, caſt in ſeverall Bombards, and Granadoes to fire it, and broke downe ſome piece of the wall, <hi>Ian.</hi> 27. old ſtile, raiſed the ſiege, marched the ſame night to <hi>Granges,</hi> in the way to <hi>Burgundy,</hi> where the next day they divided their Forces, the Baron of <hi>Suitz</hi> taking the way of <hi>Germany</hi> to joyne with <hi>Gallas</hi> his Army, and <hi>Mercie</hi> the way of the <hi>Franch Countie,</hi> to Duke <hi>Charles,</hi> who yet remained there.</p>
            <p>Fortune ſmiled all this while upon the <hi>French;</hi> by Sea and Land the affaires of that Kingdome went on, if not proſperouſly, yet not unhappily. <hi>Zarquemine,</hi> a frontier towne betwixt <hi>Alſatia</hi> and <hi>Loraine,</hi> in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Caeſareans</hi> and <hi>Loranois,</hi> was as a pricke in the ſides of the Villages about <hi>Haguenau,</hi> and the Countie of <hi>Bitche,</hi> in the alliance, and under the obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of the <hi>French</hi> King; but the Garriſon there was forced,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zarque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ine</hi> ſurpriſed by <hi>Brevill</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of <hi>Bitche.</hi>
               </note> and the Towne yielded to obedience by the Armes of <hi>Brevill,</hi> Governour of the Countie, Towne, and Caſtle of <hi>Bitche</hi> (againſt which place, thoſe of <hi>Zarquemine</hi> had a deſigne formerly; who aſſiſted with 100 Souldiers, ſent unto him from <hi>Aiguebonne,</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Haguenau,</hi> about the middle of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> old ſtile, marched againſt it, came to the Fort, broke it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, &amp; became Maſters of the place; burning down the houſe of the Provoſt, &amp; Controller of the Town, the 2 Boutefeaues, and principal Authors of their hoſtilities, ſparing the Inhabitants (except one who was ſent Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner to <hi>Haguenau,</hi> till hee had paid his Ranſome) giving them this caution, That they ſhould comport themſelves fairely, toward the Kings Subjects and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:7470:53"/>the Crowne of <hi>France:</hi> threatning otherwiſe, That they would returne thither, and deale with them, as they had done with that Provoſt, and Controller, who had ſuffered exemplarily, to deter the reſt from giving eare hereafter to ſuch wicked Counſels.</p>
            <p>The ſame day, which was ſo fortunate to the <hi>French</hi> Commander in the North-eaſt, by land, was as proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in the North-weſt by Sea. The <hi>Ides</hi> of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> miniſtred a fortunate adventure, and the firſt was ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by ſome others. The Pirates of <hi>Dunkerque,</hi> who often times had roved thrivingly upon the Coaſt of <hi>Callis,</hi> were ranging about for more ſpoile. The Count of <hi>Charoſt,</hi> Governor of the Citie, being adviſed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, diſpatched to Sea a Frigate well armed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dunkerquer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Rovers taken by the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Callis,</hi>
               </note> meerly to diſcover the number of the <hi>Dunkerquers.</hi> A ſmall boat of <hi>Dunkerque,</hi> haling a rich <hi>Holland</hi> Ship, which the Fleet had taken 4 daies before, appeared ſingly, which being guarded only with 13 <hi>Wallons,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Pinace ſubdued, and brought into <hi>Callis</hi> with the <hi>Hollander;</hi> to the incouragement of the Seamen in the Port, who preſently rigg'd up a ſmall Navie, put forth to Sea, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving not to returne with emptie hands; and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe ſucceeded ſo well, that the next day they brought into the harbor three other Prizes: one wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, was a Veſſell laden with all ſorts of Marchandiſe from <hi>Spaine,</hi> and bound for the <hi>Low-countries,</hi> in which bottom, and the two others, were found alſo many Priſoners. This good event, rouzed up the courage of ſome other Adventurers to attempt the like. The 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> of the Calends of <hi>February,</hi> Intelligence was given, That ſome of the <hi>Dunkerquers</hi> were in the Channell neere that Coaſt, with ſome Ships which they had taken as prize from the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and that occaſion was ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfully perſwaſive, that the Marriners needed no other Orator, to incourage them to put to Sea, and fight
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:7470:53"/>with them. Three <hi>French</hi> Frigates were inſtantly lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out of the Haven, and upon the firſt ſight of the <hi>Dunkerquers,</hi> the winds filling their Sailes, made up to them without delay, let fly their Ordnance, and the <hi>Dunkerquers,</hi> rather willing to ſave themſelves, than fight to preſerve their Prize; left the <hi>Hollanders</hi> Ships to the <hi>French</hi> Adventurers, who returned with them to <hi>Gallis,</hi> and thereby ſo hartened the Sea-men, that the Port which lately wanted Sailers, and could ſcarſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford one good Commander, ſoone after abounded both with Captaines and Marriners.</p>
            <p>But theſe peteete Victories, though the newes of them ſoone after arrived at the Court of <hi>France,</hi> were not ſo pleaſing to the Chriſtian King, as the reconclia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Monſiour his Brother, was to his Matie, for the Prince having vanquiſhed himſelfe, &amp; diſpoſſeſſed his heart of thoſe jealouſies, which made him depart as a Malecontent from the Court, returned againe of his owne accord, in the beginning of <hi>February;</hi> and gave the King ſuch a plenary aſſurance of his loyaltie, bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly affection,<note place="margin">The Chriſtian King, and the Monſieur re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled.</note> and true zeale to the Crowne and State of <hi>France,</hi> that the King by his owne Letters, made a kind of Proclamation through his whole Kingdom, of the reunion of their fraternall affections, and aſſurance of his fidelitie. Thus his Letters ran:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Kings let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls, &amp;c.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>TO all Generalls of our Armies, and Governours of our Provinces, Greeting.</salute>
                     <salute>My good Coſins,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p> ſince that the departure of my brother the Duke of <hi>Orleance</hi> to Bloys, in the Moneth of November laſt, without our permiſſion, hath given the world occaſion to ſuſpect his good intentions; and I my ſelfe beleeved, that if hee had (accordingly as hee ought) with attention examined the Motives of his Action, (according to our Letters ſent after him immediatly, to give him as good evidence (as be
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:7470:54"/>could deſire) of our good will toward him; by that imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which hee had in the Command, and Conduct of the principall Forces of the Realme) hee might eaſily have knowne, that thoſe Aviſements, and Motives which cauſed him to eloyne himſelfe from us, were not onely contrary to truth, but alſo to his proper good; Yet this credulitie never hindered me, from taking all care to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent thoſe evill conſequents, which might have followed this our ſeparation: But thanks be to God, whatever hath enſued, hath ſerved to no other end, then to make me know the fidelitie of my Subjects; whoſe conſtancy I have found unmoevable. My Brother, who hath well concluded, that the union of Hearts, in theſe times of danger, is as neceſſary as the forces of the Kingdome, to oppoſe with the more puiſſance, the Enemies of the greatneſſe of this Crowne, and its tranquilitie: Of his owne accord, hath applyed himſelfe to all which I could deſire; and no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner acknowledged his tranſgreſſion,<note place="margin">His Majeſtie undertaketh, for his zeale to the State, &amp;c.</note> then I was ready, with all my heart, to forget it, giving ſuch credit to the Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances he hath given me of his good affection, and zeale to the good of this State, that I my ſelfe doe undertake, and am a Suretie for him to my ſelfe. I am alſo reſolved, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the intreatie of my ſaid Brother, to pardon my Coſin the Count of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> not onely his fault for retyring to <hi>Sedan,</hi> without my licence, but alſo for his behaviour there all the time ſince; though it hath bin otherwiſe then I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected. All which I doe moſt willingly; provided, that my ſaid Goſin within the ſpace of fifteene dayes after the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication of this Declaration (which I make freely and of my owne good grace) returue to his obedience. All which I would have you underſtand by this Letter, to the end that you may impart it to all my Servants and Subjects in the extents of your commands: praying God (my good Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins) that he would take you into his protection.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Written at <hi>Orleance</hi> 
                        <date>the <hi>9</hi> day of <hi>Febr. 1637.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Signed <hi>Lovis.</hi>
                     </signed> And a little lower, <signed>Sublet.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:7470:54"/>
            <p>Some diſcourſe interceded at the ſame time of a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall peace to be concluded at <hi>Coln,</hi> and of a particular peace betwixt the Chriſtian and Catholick Kings, and the report was delivered ſo confidently, that the compromit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors in that negotiation, were named expreſly; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Spaniards</hi> prevailing in <hi>Italy</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> as the <hi>French</hi> would haue it, or the <hi>French</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents refuſall, to goe upon the ſafe paſport of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the third (in whoſe name that Inſtrument was ſealed) as by an Imperiall power, (the <hi>French</hi> not allowing him the title of <hi>Caeſar</hi>) the treatie held not, it is uncertaine. This is ſure, that ſtrong preparations for warre, were ſuddenly made of either ſide. The <hi>French</hi> ſet forth a Navie of 26.<note place="margin">The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> preparations for warr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Gallies, to invade the Iſland of <hi>Sardignia,</hi> attended with 22. other veſſells which carried over 8000. land-men. The <hi>Spaniard</hi> on the other ſide, knowing that moneyes were not onely the ligaments, but the very foundations of warre, ſent firſt 1000. cheſts, containing two millions and a halfe of gold in Royalls of Eight to <hi>Genoa,</hi> for payment of his Souldiers in <hi>Germany,</hi> and <hi>Italy;</hi> then leavied in the Dukedome of <hi>Millan</hi> 8000. foot; and in the Kingdome of <hi>Sicilie,</hi> a Regiment for 2500. foot, under the command of the Marqueſſe <hi>di Spava-Forno,</hi> to be imployed in his Navie; and laſtly, by the helpe of the Duke of <hi>Florence,</hi> (who aſſiſted him with ten Gallies) ſent out a convenient Fleete to oppoſe them. The <hi>French</hi> in their gallantrie rowed and ſailed to the Iſland; and comming on furiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, tooke the Port <hi>Oreſtano,</hi> neere <hi>Cagliano,</hi> affrighted the Inhabitants of that Countrey, who at firſt hid themſelues in the woods, and caues, and holes, for ſafeguard of their liues; yet of a ſodaine betooke themſelues to Armes, beat out thoſe who were landed, ſurprized their baggage, and forced the Fleete to returne, to <hi>Tolour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Crequi</hi> ſent to the King of <hi>France</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy.</hi>
               </note> a harbour in <hi>Province.</hi> And now the warre by land began to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed. The Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> who till this, never felt the fire of warre burning in his Dominions, found that Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liske ready to infect his Territories; and to prepare an
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:7470:55"/>Antidote againſt this poyſon, ſent for the Marſhall <hi>Crequi,</hi> beſtowed upon him a Diamond worth 1000. Crownes, and his Dutcheſſe another eſteemed worth 600; not for ſervice already done, but to be done hereafter, diſpatched him by Poſt to <hi>Paris,</hi> himſelfe ſoone after faigning to goe to <hi>Chambery,</hi> but (as it was thought) intending to goe to <hi>Lyon</hi> to conferre with the Chriſtian King there, for reliefe in that extremitie.</p>
            <p>About the ſame time, <hi>viz.</hi> about the beginning of <hi>March</hi> (as it is wrote from <hi>Triers</hi>) a private conſpiracy, being made in <hi>Diete hofen</hi> and <hi>Walderfangen</hi> by ſome of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, to deliver thoſe Townes and Forts into the hands of the <hi>French</hi> Allies, (ſome of the Souldiers that lay in garriſon in <hi>Dietenhofen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>French</hi> project diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered at <hi>Die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenhofen,</hi> and their forces defeated.</note> being corrupted with money, to kill the Commander of that place, &amp; nayle the Canons, that lay to guard the paſſage thither by the river of <hi>Moſel</hi>) and the laſt of theſe performed really; the <hi>French</hi> being made acquainted therewith, ſailed downe the river with ſcaling ladders, and other needfull implements to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute what was thus projected; but the plot was of too diſhonourable a birth to haue a glorious iſſue. A <hi>French</hi> man, who being married in the Towne, was maſter of a ſmall fortune, and father of ſome children, was made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted by the conſpirators of their intention, and he not knowing, what might fall to his fortune in that confuſion, diſcovered the treaſon to the Magiſtrate, who doubled his watches, kept a ſtrong Corps du guard at each Port, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the walls, and armed the Citizens to oppoſe theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcomely expected gueſts; who finding their purpoſe prevented by this care, marched from thence to <hi>Walder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fangen,</hi> where the Commander (having notice thereof from <hi>Dietenhofen</hi> the night before) gaue them ſo rude en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment, that of 400 foot, and 100 horſe, which were deſigned for this bufineſſe, ſcarce the one halfe returned; and after their departure, made inquirie for the conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, proceeded againſt them legally, condemned them, and as they had deſerved, put them to a ſhame full death.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:7470:55"/>
            <p>In the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>altoline,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> expeditions began at the ſame time to flag. The <hi>Griſons,</hi> an unconſtant and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine people (as all Democraticall States are) had often murmured againſt the Chriſtian King, and his Generall there the Duke <hi>Rohan;</hi> and oft-times been appeaſed with money from <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Duke of <hi>Rohan</hi> his goods arre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted by the <hi>Griſons,</hi>
               </note> and the good order which was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the <hi>French</hi> Commander; but now, what they had long praeconceived, of disburthening themſelues of the <hi>French</hi> Forces, was brought into action. A generall Diet for the ſetling of that State was appointed to be held at <hi>Chur,</hi> or <hi>Coire,</hi> at the ſame time, when the multitude made head againſt the <hi>French,</hi> and to expell them by force out of the Countrey, were gathered together to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of 4 or 5000. men, and reſolved to ſurprize the Duke of <hi>Rohan</hi> in perſon, if it were poſſible. A ſuperiour provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence over-ruleth the wiſeſt Counſells, and often infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuateth their determinations, which would be accounted moſt prudent: The Duke was then abroad on hunting, and ſo by accident prevented that miſ-fortune. The <hi>Gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> perceiving that courſe to fayle, arreſted his good<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which were at <hi>Chur,</hi> and by that violence diſcovered an alienation of their affections from him. It was not done ſo privately, as to be kept ſecret, the valley ecchoed with the ſame of what was done in the Citie, the report was quickly brought to the <hi>French</hi> Generalls eares, who up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the tydings repayred to the <hi>Staig,</hi> aſtrong peece, and hardly to be taken, while well manned, and defended. Thus ſecured, he ſtood upon tearmes of Capitulation, as holding it too diſhonourable for himſelfe and his Nation to leaue the Province, which he had gained by his pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and managed by his valour, upon the mutinie of the giddie multitude, which for their owne advantage, and hope of gaine, might happily haue complied with the Chriſtian Kings profeſſed enemie, and the States of that Province, by mediation of thoſe of <hi>Zur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch,</hi> giving eare to counſell, came to a faire parley, aſſured him of the good reſpect they had of the amitie of the Chriſtian King; that,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:7470:56"/>they intended no combination, and confederacie with the enemies of the Crowne of <hi>France;</hi> but that (as hitherto they had been a free State, not over-ruled by ſtrangers) ſo now againe, they onely deſired to be Maſters of their own Dominions, promiſing withall, with their owne Armes, and at their proper coſts, to ſecure thoſe paſſages, (which were then held by the <hi>French</hi>) againſt the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> if he would freely reſtore them. The treatie was upon une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall tearmes, the Duke was their priſoner, and might not ſtand to make his owne conditions; To gaine his ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to be aſſured of the <hi>Griſons,</hi> he condeſcended to ſeale mutually to theſe Articles. That the <hi>Staig,</hi> the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Bormeo,</hi> and <hi>Chiavenna,</hi> ſhould be preſently redeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to the States of thoſe Provinces, and the money which was due unto them payed with all expedition: And the <hi>Griſons,</hi> on the other ſide, condeſcended, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme their amitie with the King and Crowne of <hi>France;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions agreed upon, betwixt the <hi>Griſons,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Rohan.</hi>
               </note> and to maintaine the paſſages againſt the <hi>Spaniard.</hi> All which, being ſealed unto by the Duke in behalfe of the King his Maſter, and by the Colonell <hi>Gaſper Smith,</hi> in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of the <hi>Griſons,</hi> April 8. <hi>old ſtile,</hi> and the places were ſurrendred to the <hi>Griſons</hi> accordingly.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the counterbuffes and ſpots, with which the flouriſhing fortune and ſplendour of the <hi>French</hi> glory was at that time checked and ſullyed, which yet was ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what reſtored and revived by another happy adventure of the Chriſtian Kings Forces in <hi>Loraine</hi> about the ſame day when the Duke was almoſt ſurprized. The <hi>Caeſareans</hi> who had ſome moneths before taken the Citie of <hi>Switz,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Switz</hi> beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and taken by the <hi>French</hi>
               </note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Dukedome of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and <hi>Switzerland,</hi> had thereby intercluded the paſſage, and communion, betwixt <hi>France,</hi> and the Allies of that Crowne in that Territorie. To regaine it the <hi>French</hi> Garriſons at <hi>Beffort, Bruntrant,</hi> and <hi>Ericourt,</hi> muſtered up 2000. men, armed them with neceſſary proviſions for a battery, ſent them againſt that Citie and Caſtle, and then after two dayes battery, with 8. Pieces of Ordnance, forced the Garriſon to yeeld upon
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:7470:56"/>compoſition, to depart with their low weapons onely, and ſo opened the way for commerce betwixt that State and the Kings Subjects. But, this gaine, had been a ſmall requitall to the former loſſes, had it come ſingly, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>attended without any other. It was the concomitant of better fortunes to the <hi>French,</hi> who under the Duke of <hi>Longueville,</hi> did much harme to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Garriſons in the Dukedome of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> ſurprized the Citie of <hi>Amur</hi> under the conduct of the Lord <hi>Thianges,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Honorita</hi> and <hi>Margarita</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered by the <hi>French.</hi>
               </note> and cut in pieces the <hi>Caeſareans</hi> there; and by their Fleete, <hi>March.</hi> 19. <hi>old ſtile,</hi> at night aſſaulted the Iland <hi>Margarita,</hi> and landed ſome Forces under the Count of <hi>Harcourt,</hi> tooke in the firſt Fort, &amp; after beleaguered the Fort Royall; where the Garriſon, after a tedious Siege began to parley, and at laſt agreed upon compoſition, and ſo marched out, leaving the whole Iſland againe to the <hi>French,</hi> who now goe to aſſault and beſiege the other Iſland named St. <hi>Honorata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Spring began now to come on, and the united States of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and the Cardinall <hi>Infant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Preparations for warre by the Cardinall <hi>Infant.</hi> &amp; the united <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tates.</note> began to prepare for warre. The States began with the caſtigation of ſome rude Souldiers, caſhiering at <hi>Maſtricht</hi> 4. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies of foote, and at <hi>Venlo,</hi> and <hi>Roermond</hi> ſome others, who being out of pay, and knowing nothow to liue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, than by warre, promiſed to reforme themſelues, and were placed under other more ſevere Commanders; and this done, diſpatches were ſent and Proclamation pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, that all Commanders ſhould haue their Companies ready by the beginning of <hi>May.</hi> The Cardinall <hi>Infant,</hi> who was engaged elſe-where, and not onely againſt the States, made great preparation both by ſea &amp; land to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe his deſignes. Great ſtore of Bisket was baked at <hi>Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werp</hi> to ſupply the Dunkerkers, who with two men of warre and 16 Frigates, had already put to Sea. <hi>Picolomini</hi> was furniſhed with money, and a full Commiſſion, and ſent into upper <hi>Germany,</hi> to levie ſome thouſands of men for the <hi>Infante's</hi> ſervice, who had prepared his waggons for carriage of the Baggage; and Prince <hi>Francis</hi> of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine,</hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:7470:57"/>who already had the Command of 4. Regiments, received order to rayſe two new ones, and to joyne with the Earle <hi>Picolomins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The time of action was not yet come, the harveſt was ſtill in the blade, and the fields afforded no forrage. No Armies could yet be brought into <hi>Campagnia,</hi> onely ſome private parties were imployed abroad by the Garriſons, more for ſpoyle, and pillage, than in hope of victory. From <hi>Breda</hi> 100. valiant and experienced Souldiers were ſent out on plundering, who were ſurprized, and rowted neere <hi>Balen</hi> by another partie of the States Garriſon at the <hi>Boſh,</hi> which though it ſurpaſſed the <hi>Brabantiers</hi> in number yet obtained not the victory by meere valour &amp; ſtrength, but by a fineneſſe adjoyned thereto; which nevertheleſſe was not ſo prevalent as to giue them a cleere victory, without much loſſe of their own bloud.<note place="margin">A bloudie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight betwixt apartie of the <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> and another of the States Souldiers.</note> The States Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, knowing of the enemies march, divided themſelues into two bands, the one conſiſting of 80. the other of 40. men. The minor Company, appeared to the view of the <hi>Brabantiers,</hi> while the other and greater part remained hidden &amp; undiſcovered. The eye of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Souldiers was no ſooner fixed upon the leſſer band, but they made towards them with all haſt, whilſt they pretending a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full flight, haſted to gaine two ſtrong farme houſes, neere the place where their complices lay, as places of refuge in that neceſſitie. Their enemy purſued them with all eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, aſſaulted the houſes with all violence, whilſt thoſe within playing upon them with their ſmall ſhot, and the ambuſh riſing from behinde them, made them know, that the victory was hardlier to be atchieved, than they imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Neither the odds of twenty men in number, nor the unexpected troope comming on ſo ſodainely, did utterly diſcourage theſe reſolved men, but made them recollect their ſpirits, and prepare to fight; droping, if not to obtaine the conqueſt, yet to goe off without much loſſe. The fight was hot on both ſides, the Muſquetiers were both good markmen, and nimble fingerens of that deadly engine; and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:7470:57"/>charged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> diſcharged ſo nimbly, that the ground was purpled with the bloud of the wounded,<note place="margin">The Statiſts get the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</note> ſo many being ſlaine on both ſides, that after the combate was done, ten waggons were laden with the dead corpſes of thoſe two pettie Armies, yet in the end, the victory fell to the Statiſts, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Souldiers being forced to flie.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> ſoone after, had a deſigne againſt <hi>Hulſt,</hi> a Town of importance in the frontiers of <hi>Brabant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Prince of <hi>Orarge</hi> his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne againſt <hi>Hulſt</hi> preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> and the Key of the Countrey from <hi>Zealand</hi> to that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, and the Earledome of <hi>Flanders.</hi> He had made pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration to ſurprize it, and was about the expedition when certaine notice came unto him, that his project was diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, which made him forbeare the attempt, deeming it leſſe diſhonour, not at all to begin a work of that difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which might put himſelfe and his Army into hazard, than to goe on deſperately, and be repulſed ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
            <p>And thus, we haue deſcribed the occurrences of theſe few moneths, omitting nothing worth obſervation, which hath happened in theſe Weſterne parts of the world. In the Eaſterne parts amongſt the <hi>Turkes,</hi> we heare of tumults, civill diſſentions, rebellions managed with a ſtrong power, and ſuch like barbariſmes. The <hi>Belgerbeg</hi> Baſha in <hi>Morea,</hi> attended with twentie thouſand Souldiers, made head there againſt his Soveraigne, not contenting himfelfe with that high office, but ayming at a higher kinde of dominion in that Peninſula, and to effect his deſigne, called in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther twelue thouſand <hi>Alboneſes,</hi> to aſſiſt him; and with thoſe Forces, poſſeſſed himſelfe of the Citie and Port <hi>de Santa Maura</hi> in <hi>Morea.</hi> The Grand Signior, enraged with this affront ſummoned him to appeare at his Court at <hi>Conſtantinopl;</hi> and (he not comming in) confiſcated his lands and goods, and ſent an Armie againſt him to ſurprize his perſon, and diſperſe the Rebells;<note place="margin">The Baſha in <hi>Morea</hi> rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth againſt the Turke.</note> but with what ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, it is not yet knowne. The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>izier</hi> baſha who had bin imployed againſt the <hi>Perſian,</hi> was threatned alſo to be
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:7470:58"/>ſtrangled (a miſerable caſe, when ſervice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by the event) by a Capigie, who was ſent p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>poſely to the Armie, to deprive the <hi>Baſha</hi> of his life, becauſe he had not beene fortunate in his warres againſt the <hi>Sophy.</hi> The <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ezier</hi> knowing the fury of the Mahometan Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and jealous of what was intended againſt him, for ſafeguard of himſelfe, fell to the <hi>Perſian,</hi> and left the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my without Commander,<note place="margin">The <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ezier Baſha,</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed lately againſt the <hi>Perſian,</hi> fleeth to the <hi>Sophy.</hi>
               </note> and ſo prevented the <hi>Capigie</hi> in the diſpatch of his Commiſſion. The <hi>Sultan</hi> miſſing his deſigne againſt the <hi>Vezier,</hi> proceeded in rage againſt the <hi>Capigie,</hi> ſmote off his head, and ſent <hi>Camacan,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Baſha's, with the power and title of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, to command his Armies, whoſe proceedings wee muſt expect hereafter.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
